Psalm 1

^1Blessed is the man that walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly, nor standeth in the way of sinners, nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful.
^2But his delight is in the law of the Lord; and in his law doth he meditate day and night.
^3And he shall be like a tree planted by the rivers of water, that bringeth forth his fruit in his season; his leaf also shall not wither; and whatsoever he doeth shall prosper.
^4The ungodly are not so: but are like the chaff which the wind driveth away.
^5Therefore the ungodly shall not stand in the judgment, nor sinners in the congregation of the righteous.
^6For the Lord knoweth the way of the righteous: but the way of the ungodly shall perish.

Psalm 2

^1Why do the heathen rage, and the people imagine a vain thing?
^2The kings of the earth set themselves, and the rulers take counsel together, against the Lord, and against his anointed, saying,
^3Let us break their bands asunder, and cast away their cords from us.
^4He that sitteth in the heavens shall laugh: the Lord shall have them in derision.
^5Then shall he speak unto them in his wrath, and vex them in his sore displeasure.
^6Yet have I set my king upon my holy hill of Zion.
^7I will declare the decree: the Lord hath said unto me, Thou art my Son; this day have I begotten thee.
^8Ask of me, and I shall give thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermost parts of the earth for thy possession.
^9Thou shalt break them with a rod of iron; thou shalt dash them in pieces like a potter’s vessel.
^10Be wise now therefore, O ye kings: be instructed, ye judges of the earth.
^11Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice with trembling.
^12Kiss the Son, lest he be angry, and ye perish from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little. Blessed are all they that put their trust in him.

Psalm 3

^1Lord, how are they increased that trouble me! many are they that rise up against me.
^2Many there be which say of my soul, There is no help for him in God. Selah.
^3But thou, O Lord, art a shield for me; my glory, and the lifter up of mine head.
^4I cried unto the Lord with my voice, and he heard me out of his holy hill. Selah.
^5I laid me down and slept; I awaked; for the Lord sustained me.
^6I will not be afraid of ten thousands of people, that have set themselves against me round about.
^7Arise, O Lord; save me, O my God: for thou hast smitten all mine enemies upon the cheek bone; thou hast broken the teeth of the ungodly.
^8Salvation belongeth unto the Lord: thy blessing is upon thy people. Selah.

Psalm 4

^1Hear me when I call, O God of my righteousness: thou hast enlarged me when I was in distress; have mercy upon me, and hear my prayer.
^2O ye sons of men, how long will ye turn my glory into shame? how long will ye love vanity, and seek after leasing? Selah.
^3But know that the Lord hath set apart him that is godly for himself: the Lord will hear when I call unto him.
^4Stand in awe, and sin not: commune with your own heart upon your bed, and be still. Selah.
^5Offer the sacrifices of righteousness, and put your trust in the Lord.
^6There be many that say, Who will shew us any good? Lord, lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us.
^7Thou hast put gladness in my heart, more than in the time that their corn and their wine increased.
^8I will both lay me down in peace, and sleep: for thou, Lord, only makest me dwell in safety.

Psalm 5

^1Give ear to my words, O Lord, consider my meditation.
^2Hearken unto the voice of my cry, my King, and my God: for unto thee will I pray.
^3My voice shalt thou hear in the morning, O Lord; in the morning will I direct my prayer unto thee, and will look up.
^4For thou art not a God that hath pleasure in wickedness: neither shall evil dwell with thee.
^5The foolish shall not stand in thy sight: thou hatest all workers of iniquity.
^6Thou shalt destroy them that speak leasing: the Lord will abhor the bloody and deceitful man.
^7But as for me, I will come into thy house in the multitude of thy mercy: and in thy fear will I worship toward thy holy temple.
^8Lead me, O Lord, in thy righteousness because of mine enemies; make thy way straight before my face.
^9For there is no faithfulness in their mouth; their inward part is very wickedness; their throat is an open sepulchre; they flatter with their tongue.
^10Destroy thou them, O God; let them fall by their own counsels; cast them out in the multitude of their transgressions; for they have rebelled against thee.
^11But let all those that put their trust in thee rejoice: let them ever shout for joy, because thou defendest them: let them also that love thy name be joyful in thee.
^12For thou, Lord, wilt bless the righteous; with favour wilt thou compass him as with a shield.

Psalm 6

^1O Lord, rebuke me not in thine anger, neither chasten me in thy hot displeasure.
^2Have mercy upon me, O Lord; for I am weak: O Lord, heal me; for my bones are vexed.
^3My soul is also sore vexed: but thou, O Lord, how long?
^4Return, O Lord, deliver my soul: oh save me for thy mercies’ sake.
^5For in death there is no remembrance of thee: in the grave who shall give thee thanks?
^6I am weary with my groaning; all the night make I my bed to swim; I water my couch with my tears.
^7Mine eye is consumed because of grief; it waxeth old because of all mine enemies.
^8Depart from me, all ye workers of iniquity; for the Lord hath heard the voice of my weeping.
^9The Lord hath heard my supplication; the Lord will receive my prayer.
^10Let all mine enemies be ashamed and sore vexed: let them return and be ashamed suddenly.

Psalm 7

^1O Lord my God, in thee do I put my trust: save me from all them that persecute me, and deliver me:
^2Lest he tear my soul like a lion, rending it in pieces, while there is none to deliver.
^3O Lord my God, If I have done this; if there be iniquity in my hands;
^4If I have rewarded evil unto him that was at peace with me; (yea, I have delivered him that without cause is mine enemy:)
^5Let the enemy persecute my soul, and take it; yea, let him tread down my life upon the earth, and lay mine honour in the dust. Selah.
^6Arise, O Lord, in thine anger, lift up thyself because of the rage of mine enemies: and awake for me to the judgment that thou hast commanded.
^7So shall the congregation of the people compass thee about: for their sakes therefore return thou on high.
^8The Lord shall judge the people: judge me, O Lord, according to my righteousness, and according to mine integrity that is in me.
^9Oh let the wickedness of the wicked come to an end; but establish the just: for the righteous God trieth the hearts and reins.
^10My defence is of God, which saveth the upright in heart.
^11God judgeth the righteous, and God is angry with the wicked every day.
^12If he turn not, he will whet his sword; he hath bent his bow, and made it ready.
^13He hath also prepared for him the instruments of death; he ordaineth his arrows against the persecutors.
^14Behold, he travaileth with iniquity, and hath conceived mischief, and brought forth falsehood.
^15He made a pit, and digged it, and is fallen into the ditch which he made.
^16His mischief shall return upon his own head, and his violent dealing shall come down upon his own pate.
^17I will praise the Lord according to his righteousness: and will sing praise to the name of the Lord most high.

Psalm 8

^1O Lord, our Lord, how excellent is thy name in all the earth! who hast set thy glory above the heavens.
^2Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings hast thou ordained strength because of thine enemies, that thou mightest still the enemy and the avenger.
^3When I consider thy heavens, the work of thy fingers, the moon and the stars, which thou hast ordained;
^4What is man, that thou art mindful of him? and the son of man, that thou visitest him?
^5For thou hast made him a little lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and honour.
^6Thou madest him to have dominion over the works of thy hands; thou hast put all things under his feet:
^7All sheep and oxen, yea, and the beasts of the field;
^8The fowl of the air, and the fish of the sea, and whatsoever passeth through the paths of the seas.
^9O Lord our Lord, how excellent is thy name in all the earth!

Psalm 9

^1I will praise thee, O Lord, with my whole heart; I will shew forth all thy marvellous works.
^2I will be glad and rejoice in thee: I will sing praise to thy name, O thou most High.
^3When mine enemies are turned back, they shall fall and perish at thy presence.
^4For thou hast maintained my right and my cause; thou satest in the throne judging right.
^5Thou hast rebuked the heathen, thou hast destroyed the wicked, thou hast put out their name for ever and ever.
^6O thou enemy, destructions are come to a perpetual end: and thou hast destroyed cities; their memorial is perished with them.
^7But the Lord shall endure for ever: he hath prepared his throne for judgment.
^8And he shall judge the world in righteousness, he shall minister judgment to the people in uprightness.
^9The Lord also will be a refuge for the oppressed, a refuge in times of trouble.
^10And they that know thy name will put their trust in thee: for thou, Lord, hast not forsaken them that seek thee.
^11Sing praises to the Lord, which dwelleth in Zion: declare among the people his doings.
^12When he maketh inquisition for blood, he remembereth them: he forgetteth not the cry of the humble.
^13Have mercy upon me, O Lord; consider my trouble which I suffer of them that hate me, thou that liftest me up from the gates of death:
^14That I may shew forth all thy praise in the gates of the daughter of Zion: I will rejoice in thy salvation.
^15The heathen are sunk down in the pit that they made: in the net which they hid is their own foot taken.
^16The Lord is known by the judgment which he executeth: the wicked is snared in the work of his own hands. Higgaion. Selah.
^17The wicked shall be turned into hell, and all the nations that forget God.
^18For the needy shall not alway be forgotten: the expectation of the poor shall not perish for ever.
^19Arise, O Lord; let not man prevail: let the heathen be judged in thy sight.
^20Put them in fear, O Lord: that the nations may know themselves to be but men. Selah.

Psalm 10

^1Why standest thou afar off, O Lord? why hidest thou thyself in times of trouble?
^2The wicked in his pride doth persecute the poor: let them be taken in the devices that they have imagined.
^3For the wicked boasteth of his heart’s desire, and blesseth the covetous, whom the Lord abhorreth.
^4The wicked, through the pride of his countenance, will not seek after God: God is not in all his thoughts.
^5His ways are always grievous; thy judgments are far above out of his sight: as for all his enemies, he puffeth at them.
^6He hath said in his heart, I shall not be moved: for I shall never be in adversity.
^7His mouth is full of cursing and deceit and fraud: under his tongue is mischief and vanity.
^8He sitteth in the lurking places of the villages: in the secret places doth he murder the innocent: his eyes are privily set against the poor.
^9He lieth in wait secretly as a lion in his den: he lieth in wait to catch the poor: he doth catch the poor, when he draweth him into his net.
^10He croucheth, and humbleth himself, that the poor may fall by his strong ones.
^11He hath said in his heart, God hath forgotten: he hideth his face; he will never see it.
^12Arise, O Lord; O God, lift up thine hand: forget not the humble.
^13Wherefore doth the wicked contemn God? he hath said in his heart, Thou wilt not require it.
^14Thou hast seen it; for thou beholdest mischief and spite, to requite it with thy hand: the poor committeth himself unto thee; thou art the helper of the fatherless.
^15Break thou the arm of the wicked and the evil man: seek out his wickedness till thou find none.
^16The Lord is King for ever and ever: the heathen are perished out of his land.
^17Lord, thou hast heard the desire of the humble: thou wilt prepare their heart, thou wilt cause thine ear to hear:
^18To judge the fatherless and the oppressed, that the man of the earth may no more oppress.

Psalm 11

^1In the Lord put I my trust: how say ye to my soul, Flee as a bird to your mountain?
^2For, lo, the wicked bend their bow, they make ready their arrow upon the string, that they may privily shoot at the upright in heart.
^3If the foundations be destroyed, what can the righteous do?
^4The Lord is in his holy temple, the Lord’s throne is in heaven: his eyes behold, his eyelids try, the children of men.
^5The Lord trieth the righteous: but the wicked and him that loveth violence his soul hateth.
^6Upon the wicked he shall rain snares, fire and brimstone, and an horrible tempest: this shall be the portion of their cup.
^7For the righteous Lord loveth righteousness; his countenance doth behold the upright.

Psalm 12

^1Help, Lord; for the godly man ceaseth; for the faithful fail from among the children of men.
^2They speak vanity every one with his neighbour: with flattering lips and with a double heart do they speak.
^3The Lord shall cut off all flattering lips, and the tongue that speaketh proud things:
^4Who have said, With our tongue will we prevail; our lips are our own: who is lord over us?
^5For the oppression of the poor, for the sighing of the needy, now will I arise, saith the Lord; I will set him in safety from him that puffeth at him.
^6The words of the Lord are pure words: as silver tried in a furnace of earth, purified seven times.
^7Thou shalt keep them, O Lord, thou shalt preserve them from this generation for ever.
^8The wicked walk on every side, when the vilest men are exalted.

Psalm 13

^1How long wilt thou forget me, O Lord? for ever? how long wilt thou hide thy face from me?
^2How long shall I take counsel in my soul, having sorrow in my heart daily? how long shall mine enemy be exalted over me?
^3Consider and hear me, O Lord my God: lighten mine eyes, lest I sleep the sleep of death;
^4Lest mine enemy say, I have prevailed against him; and those that trouble me rejoice when I am moved.
^5But I have trusted in thy mercy; my heart shall rejoice in thy salvation.
^6I will sing unto the Lord, because he hath dealt bountifully with me.

Psalm 14

^1The fool hath said in his heart, There is no God. They are corrupt, they have done abominable works, there is none that doeth good.
^2The Lord looked down from heaven upon the children of men, to see if there were any that did understand, and seek God.
^3They are all gone aside, they are all together become filthy: there is none that doeth good, no, not one.
^4Have all the workers of iniquity no knowledge? who eat up my people as they eat bread, and call not upon the Lord.
^5There were they in great fear: for God is in the generation of the righteous.
^6Ye have shamed the counsel of the poor, because the Lord is his refuge.
^7Oh that the salvation of Israel were come out of Zion! when the Lord bringeth back the captivity of his people, Jacob shall rejoice, and Israel shall be glad.

Psalm 15

^1Lord, who shall abide in thy tabernacle? who shall dwell in thy holy hill?
^2He that walketh uprightly, and worketh righteousness, and speaketh the truth in his heart.
^3He that backbiteth not with his tongue, nor doeth evil to his neighbour, nor taketh up a reproach against his neighbour.
^4In whose eyes a vile person is contemned; but he honoureth them that fear the Lord. He that sweareth to his own hurt, and changeth not.
^5He that putteth not out his money to usury, nor taketh reward against the innocent. He that doeth these things shall never be moved.

Psalm 16

^1Preserve me, O God: for in thee do I put my trust.
^2O my soul, thou hast said unto the Lord, Thou art my Lord: my goodness extendeth not to thee;
^3But to the saints that are in the earth, and to the excellent, in whom is all my delight.
^4Their sorrows shall be multiplied that hasten after another god: their drink offerings of blood will I not offer, nor take up their names into my lips.
^5The Lord is the portion of mine inheritance and of my cup: thou maintainest my lot.
^6The lines are fallen unto me in pleasant places; yea, I have a goodly heritage.
^7I will bless the Lord, who hath given me counsel: my reins also instruct me in the night seasons.
^8I have set the Lord always before me: because he is at my right hand, I shall not be moved.
^9Therefore my heart is glad, and my glory rejoiceth: my flesh also shall rest in hope.
^10For thou wilt not leave my soul in hell; neither wilt thou suffer thine Holy One to see corruption.
^11Thou wilt shew me the path of life: in thy presence is fulness of joy; at thy right hand there are pleasures for evermore.

Psalm 17

^1Hear the right, O Lord, attend unto my cry, give ear unto my prayer, that goeth not out of feigned lips.
^2Let my sentence come forth from thy presence; let thine eyes behold the things that are equal.
^3Thou hast proved mine heart; thou hast visited me in the night; thou hast tried me, and shalt find nothing; I am purposed that my mouth shall not transgress.
^4Concerning the works of men, by the word of thy lips I have kept me from the paths of the destroyer.
^5Hold up my goings in thy paths, that my footsteps slip not.
^6I have called upon thee, for thou wilt hear me, O God: incline thine ear unto me, and hear my speech.
^7Shew thy marvellous lovingkindness, O thou that savest by thy right hand them which put their trust in thee from those that rise up against them.
^8Keep me as the apple of the eye, hide me under the shadow of thy wings,
^9From the wicked that oppress me, from my deadly enemies, who compass me about.
^10They are inclosed in their own fat: with their mouth they speak proudly.
^11They have now compassed us in our steps: they have set their eyes bowing down to the earth;
^12Like as a lion that is greedy of his prey, and as it were a young lion lurking in secret places.
^13Arise, O Lord, disappoint him, cast him down: deliver my soul from the wicked, which is thy sword:
^14From men which are thy hand, O Lord, from men of the world, which have their portion in this life, and whose belly thou fillest with thy hid treasure: they are full of children, and leave the rest of their substance to their babes.
^15As for me, I will behold thy face in righteousness: I shall be satisfied, when I awake, with thy likeness.

Psalm 18

^1I will love thee, O Lord, my strength.
^2The Lord is my rock, and my fortress, and my deliverer; my God, my strength, in whom I will trust; my buckler, and the horn of my salvation, and my high tower.
^3I will call upon the Lord, who is worthy to be praised: so shall I be saved from mine enemies.
^4The sorrows of death compassed me, and the floods of ungodly men made me afraid.
^5The sorrows of hell compassed me about: the snares of death prevented me.
^6In my distress I called upon the Lord, and cried unto my God: he heard my voice out of his temple, and my cry came before him, even into his ears.
^7Then the earth shook and trembled; the foundations also of the hills moved and were shaken, because he was wroth.
^8There went up a smoke out of his nostrils, and fire out of his mouth devoured: coals were kindled by it.
^9He bowed the heavens also, and came down: and darkness was under his feet.
^10And he rode upon a cherub, and did fly: yea, he did fly upon the wings of the wind.
^11He made darkness his secret place; his pavilion round about him were dark waters and thick clouds of the skies.
^12At the brightness that was before him his thick clouds passed, hail stones and coals of fire.
^13The Lord also thundered in the heavens, and the Highest gave his voice; hail stones and coals of fire.
^14Yea, he sent out his arrows, and scattered them; and he shot out lightnings, and discomfited them.
^15Then the channels of waters were seen, and the foundations of the world were discovered at thy rebuke, O Lord, at the blast of the breath of thy nostrils.
^16He sent from above, he took me, he drew me out of many waters.
^17He delivered me from my strong enemy, and from them which hated me: for they were too strong for me.
^18They prevented me in the day of my calamity: but the Lord was my stay.
^19He brought me forth also into a large place; he delivered me, because he delighted in me.
^20The Lord rewarded me according to my righteousness; according to the cleanness of my hands hath he recompensed me.
^21For I have kept the ways of the Lord, and have not wickedly departed from my God.
^22For all his judgments were before me, and I did not put away his statutes from me.
^23I was also upright before him, and I kept myself from mine iniquity.
^24Therefore hath the Lord recompensed me according to my righteousness, according to the cleanness of my hands in his eyesight.
^25With the merciful thou wilt shew thyself merciful; with an upright man thou wilt shew thyself upright;
^26With the pure thou wilt shew thyself pure; and with the froward thou wilt shew thyself froward.
^27For thou wilt save the afflicted people; but wilt bring down high looks.
^28For thou wilt light my candle: the Lord my God will enlighten my darkness.
^29For by thee I have run through a troop; and by my God have I leaped over a wall.
^30As for God, his way is perfect: the word of the Lord is tried: he is a buckler to all those that trust in him.
^31For who is God save the Lord? or who is a rock save our God?
^32It is God that girdeth me with strength, and maketh my way perfect.
^33He maketh my feet like hinds’ feet, and setteth me upon my high places.
^34He teacheth my hands to war, so that a bow of steel is broken by mine arms.
^35Thou hast also given me the shield of thy salvation: and thy right hand hath holden me up, and thy gentleness hath made me great.
^36Thou hast enlarged my steps under me, that my feet did not slip.
^37I have pursued mine enemies, and overtaken them: neither did I turn again till they were consumed.
^38I have wounded them that they were not able to rise: they are fallen under my feet.
^39For thou hast girded me with strength unto the battle: thou hast subdued under me those that rose up against me.
^40Thou hast also given me the necks of mine enemies; that I might destroy them that hate me.
^41They cried, but there was none to save them: even unto the Lord, but he answered them not.
^42Then did I beat them small as the dust before the wind: I did cast them out as the dirt in the streets.
^43Thou hast delivered me from the strivings of the people; and thou hast made me the head of the heathen: a people whom I have not known shall serve me.
^44As soon as they hear of me, they shall obey me: the strangers shall submit themselves unto me.
^45The strangers shall fade away, and be afraid out of their close places.
^46The Lord liveth; and blessed be my rock; and let the God of my salvation be exalted.
^47It is God that avengeth me, and subdueth the people under me.
^48He delivereth me from mine enemies: yea, thou liftest me up above those that rise up against me: thou hast delivered me from the violent man.
^49Therefore will I give thanks unto thee, O Lord, among the heathen, and sing praises unto thy name.
^50Great deliverance giveth he to his king; and sheweth mercy to his anointed, to David, and to his seed for evermore.

Psalm 19

^1The heavens declare the glory of God; and the firmament sheweth his handywork.
^2Day unto day uttereth speech, and night unto night sheweth knowledge.
^3There is no speech nor language, where their voice is not heard.
^4Their line is gone out through all the earth, and their words to the end of the world. In them hath he set a tabernacle for the sun,
^5Which is as a bridegroom coming out of his chamber, and rejoiceth as a strong man to run a race.
^6His going forth is from the end of the heaven, and his circuit unto the ends of it: and there is nothing hid from the heat thereof.
^7The law of the Lord is perfect, converting the soul: the testimony of the Lord is sure, making wise the simple.
^8The statutes of the Lord are right, rejoicing the heart: the commandment of the Lord is pure, enlightening the eyes.
^9The fear of the Lord is clean, enduring for ever: the judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.
^10More to be desired are they than gold, yea, than much fine gold: sweeter also than honey and the honeycomb.
^11Moreover by them is thy servant warned: and in keeping of them there is great reward.
^12Who can understand his errors? cleanse thou me from secret faults.
^13Keep back thy servant also from presumptuous sins; let them not have dominion over me: then shall I be upright, and I shall be innocent from the great transgression.
^14Let the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart, be acceptable in thy sight, O Lord, my strength, and my redeemer.

Psalm 20

^1The Lord hear thee in the day of trouble; the name of the God of Jacob defend thee;
^2Send thee help from the sanctuary, and strengthen thee out of Zion;
^3Remember all thy offerings, and accept thy burnt sacrifice; Selah.
^4Grant thee according to thine own heart, and fulfil all thy counsel.
^5We will rejoice in thy salvation, and in the name of our God we will set up our banners: the Lord fulfil all thy petitions.
^6Now know I that the Lord saveth his anointed; he will hear him from his holy heaven with the saving strength of his right hand.
^7Some trust in chariots, and some in horses: but we will remember the name of the Lord our God.
^8They are brought down and fallen: but we are risen, and stand upright.
^9Save, Lord: let the king hear us when we call.

Psalm 21

^1The king shall joy in thy strength, O Lord; and in thy salvation how greatly shall he rejoice!
^2Thou hast given him his heart’s desire, and hast not withholden the request of his lips. Selah.
^3For thou preventest him with the blessings of goodness: thou settest a crown of pure gold on his head.
^4He asked life of thee, and thou gavest it him, even length of days for ever and ever.
^5His glory is great in thy salvation: honour and majesty hast thou laid upon him.
^6For thou hast made him most blessed for ever: thou hast made him exceeding glad with thy countenance.
^7For the king trusteth in the Lord, and through the mercy of the most High he shall not be moved.
^8Thine hand shall find out all thine enemies: thy right hand shall find out those that hate thee.
^9Thou shalt make them as a fiery oven in the time of thine anger: the Lord shall swallow them up in his wrath, and the fire shall devour them.
^10Their fruit shalt thou destroy from the earth, and their seed from among the children of men.
^11For they intended evil against thee: they imagined a mischievous device, which they are not able to perform.
^12Therefore shalt thou make them turn their back, when thou shalt make ready thine arrows upon thy strings against the face of them.
^13Be thou exalted, Lord, in thine own strength: so will we sing and praise thy power.

Psalm 22

^1My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? why art thou so far from helping me, and from the words of my roaring?
^2O my God, I cry in the day time, but thou hearest not; and in the night season, and am not silent.
^3But thou art holy, O thou that inhabitest the praises of Israel.
^4Our fathers trusted in thee: they trusted, and thou didst deliver them.
^5They cried unto thee, and were delivered: they trusted in thee, and were not confounded.
^6But I am a worm, and no man; a reproach of men, and despised of the people.
^7All they that see me laugh me to scorn: they shoot out the lip, they shake the head, saying,
^8He trusted on the Lord that he would deliver him: let him deliver him, seeing he delighted in him.
^9But thou art he that took me out of the womb: thou didst make me hope when I was upon my mother’s breasts.
^10I was cast upon thee from the womb: thou art my God from my mother’s belly.
^11Be not far from me; for trouble is near; for there is none to help.
^12Many bulls have compassed me: strong bulls of Bashan have beset me round.
^13They gaped upon me with their mouths, as a ravening and a roaring lion.
^14I am poured out like water, and all my bones are out of joint: my heart is like wax; it is melted in the midst of my bowels.
^15My strength is dried up like a potsherd; and my tongue cleaveth to my jaws; and thou hast brought me into the dust of death.
^16For dogs have compassed me: the assembly of the wicked have inclosed me: they pierced my hands and my feet.
^17I may tell all my bones: they look and stare upon me.
^18They part my garments among them, and cast lots upon my vesture.
^19But be not thou far from me, O Lord: O my strength, haste thee to help me.
^20Deliver my soul from the sword; my darling from the power of the dog.
^21Save me from the lion’s mouth: for thou hast heard me from the horns of the unicorns.
^22I will declare thy name unto my brethren: in the midst of the congregation will I praise thee.
^23Ye that fear the Lord, praise him; all ye the seed of Jacob, glorify him; and fear him, all ye the seed of Israel.
^24For he hath not despised nor abhorred the affliction of the afflicted; neither hath he hid his face from him; but when he cried unto him, he heard.
^25My praise shall be of thee in the great congregation: I will pay my vows before them that fear him.
^26The meek shall eat and be satisfied: they shall praise the Lord that seek him: your heart shall live for ever.
^27All the ends of the world shall remember and turn unto the Lord: and all the kindreds of the nations shall worship before thee.
^28For the kingdom is the Lord’s: and he is the governor among the nations.
^29All they that be fat upon earth shall eat and worship: all they that go down to the dust shall bow before him: and none can keep alive his own soul.
^30A seed shall serve him; it shall be accounted to the Lord for a generation.
^31They shall come, and shall declare his righteousness unto a people that shall be born, that he hath done this.

Psalm 23

^1The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want.
^2He maketh me to lie down in green pastures: he leadeth me beside the still waters.
^3He restoreth my soul: he leadeth me in the paths of righteousness for his name’s sake.
^4Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil: for thou art with me; thy rod and thy staff they comfort me.
^5Thou preparest a table before me in the presence of mine enemies: thou anointest my head with oil; my cup runneth over.
^6Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me all the days of my life: and I will dwell in the house of the Lord for ever.

Psalm 24

^1The earth is the Lord’s, and the fulness thereof; the world, and they that dwell therein.
^2For he hath founded it upon the seas, and established it upon the floods.
^3Who shall ascend into the hill of the Lord? or who shall stand in his holy place?
^4He that hath clean hands, and a pure heart; who hath not lifted up his soul unto vanity, nor sworn deceitfully.
^5He shall receive the blessing from the Lord, and righteousness from the God of his salvation.
^6This is the generation of them that seek him, that seek thy face, O Jacob. Selah.
^7Lift up your heads, O ye gates; and be ye lift up, ye everlasting doors; and the King of glory shall come in.
^8Who is this King of glory? The Lord strong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battle.
^9Lift up your heads, O ye gates; even lift them up, ye everlasting doors; and the King of glory shall come in.
^10Who is this King of glory? The Lord of hosts, he is the King of glory. Selah.

Psalm 25

^1Unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my soul.
^2O my God, I trust in thee: let me not be ashamed, let not mine enemies triumph over me.
^3Yea, let none that wait on thee be ashamed: let them be ashamed which transgress without cause.
^4Shew me thy ways, O Lord; teach me thy paths.
^5Lead me in thy truth, and teach me: for thou art the God of my salvation; on thee do I wait all the day.
^6Remember, O Lord, thy tender mercies and thy lovingkindnesses; for they have been ever of old.
^7Remember not the sins of my youth, nor my transgressions: according to thy mercy remember thou me for thy goodness’ sake, O Lord.
^8Good and upright is the Lord: therefore will he teach sinners in the way.
^9The meek will he guide in judgment: and the meek will he teach his way.
^10All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth unto such as keep his covenant and his testimonies.
^11For thy name’s sake, O Lord, pardon mine iniquity; for it is great.
^12What man is he that feareth the Lord? him shall he teach in the way that he shall choose.
^13His soul shall dwell at ease; and his seed shall inherit the earth.
^14The secret of the Lord is with them that fear him; and he will shew them his covenant.
^15Mine eyes are ever toward the Lord; for he shall pluck my feet out of the net.
^16Turn thee unto me, and have mercy upon me; for I am desolate and afflicted.
^17The troubles of my heart are enlarged: O bring thou me out of my distresses.
^18Look upon mine affliction and my pain; and forgive all my sins.
^19Consider mine enemies; for they are many; and they hate me with cruel hatred.
^20O keep my soul, and deliver me: let me not be ashamed; for I put my trust in thee.
^21Let integrity and uprightness preserve me; for I wait on thee.
^22Redeem Israel, O God, out of all his troubles.

Psalm 26

^1Judge me, O Lord; for I have walked in mine integrity: I have trusted also in the Lord; therefore I shall not slide.
^2Examine me, O Lord, and prove me; try my reins and my heart.
^3For thy lovingkindness is before mine eyes: and I have walked in thy truth.
^4I have not sat with vain persons, neither will I go in with dissemblers.
^5I have hated the congregation of evil doers; and will not sit with the wicked.
^6I will wash mine hands in innocency: so will I compass thine altar, O Lord:
^7That I may publish with the voice of thanksgiving, and tell of all thy wondrous works.
^8Lord, I have loved the habitation of thy house, and the place where thine honour dwelleth.
^9Gather not my soul with sinners, nor my life with bloody men:
^10In whose hands is mischief, and their right hand is full of bribes.
^11But as for me, I will walk in mine integrity: redeem me, and be merciful unto me.
^12My foot standeth in an even place: in the congregations will I bless the Lord.

Psalm 27

^1The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom shall I fear? the Lord is the strength of my life; of whom shall I be afraid?
^2When the wicked, even mine enemies and my foes, came upon me to eat up my flesh, they stumbled and fell.
^3Though an host should encamp against me, my heart shall not fear: though war should rise against me, in this will I be confident.
^4One thing have I desired of the Lord, that will I seek after; that I may dwell in the house of the Lord all the days of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to enquire in his temple.
^5For in the time of trouble he shall hide me in his pavilion: in the secret of his tabernacle shall he hide me; he shall set me up upon a rock.
^6And now shall mine head be lifted up above mine enemies round about me: therefore will I offer in his tabernacle sacrifices of joy; I will sing, yea, I will sing praises unto the Lord.
^7Hear, O Lord, when I cry with my voice: have mercy also upon me, and answer me.
^8When thou saidst, Seek ye my face; my heart said unto thee, Thy face, Lord, will I seek.
^9Hide not thy face far from me; put not thy servant away in anger: thou hast been my help; leave me not, neither forsake me, O God of my salvation.
^10When my father and my mother forsake me, then the Lord will take me up.
^11Teach me thy way, O Lord, and lead me in a plain path, because of mine enemies.
^12Deliver me not over unto the will of mine enemies: for false witnesses are risen up against me, and such as breathe out cruelty.
^13I had fainted, unless I had believed to see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living.
^14Wait on the Lord: be of good courage, and he shall strengthen thine heart: wait, I say, on the Lord.

Psalm 28

^1Unto thee will I cry, O Lord my rock; be not silent to me: lest, if thou be silent to me, I become like them that go down into the pit.
^2Hear the voice of my supplications, when I cry unto thee, when I lift up my hands toward thy holy oracle.
^3Draw me not away with the wicked, and with the workers of iniquity, which speak peace to their neighbours, but mischief is in their hearts.
^4Give them according to their deeds, and according to the wickedness of their endeavours: give them after the work of their hands; render to them their desert.
^5Because they regard not the works of the Lord, nor the operation of his hands, he shall destroy them, and not build them up.
^6Blessed be the Lord, because he hath heard the voice of my supplications.
^7The Lord is my strength and my shield; my heart trusted in him, and I am helped: therefore my heart greatly rejoiceth; and with my song will I praise him.
^8The Lord is their strength, and he is the saving strength of his anointed.
^9Save thy people, and bless thine inheritance: feed them also, and lift them up for ever.

Psalm 29

^1Give unto the Lord, O ye mighty, give unto the Lord glory and strength.
^2Give unto the Lord the glory due unto his name; worship the Lord in the beauty of holiness.
^3The voice of the Lord is upon the waters: the God of glory thundereth: the Lord is upon many waters.
^4The voice of the Lord is powerful; the voice of the Lord is full of majesty.
^5The voice of the Lord breaketh the cedars; yea, the Lord breaketh the cedars of Lebanon.
^6He maketh them also to skip like a calf; Lebanon and Sirion like a young unicorn.
^7The voice of the Lord divideth the flames of fire.
^8The voice of the Lord shaketh the wilderness; the Lord shaketh the wilderness of Kadesh.
^9The voice of the Lord maketh the hinds to calve, and discovereth the forests: and in his temple doth every one speak of his glory.
^10The Lord sitteth upon the flood; yea, the Lord sitteth King for ever.
^11The Lord will give strength unto his people; the Lord will bless his people with peace.

Psalm 30

^1I will extol thee, O Lord; for thou hast lifted me up, and hast not made my foes to rejoice over me.
^2O Lord my God, I cried unto thee, and thou hast healed me.
^3O Lord, thou hast brought up my soul from the grave: thou hast kept me alive, that I should not go down to the pit.
^4Sing unto the Lord, O ye saints of his, and give thanks at the remembrance of his holiness.
^5For his anger endureth but a moment; in his favour is life: weeping may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.
^6And in my prosperity I said, I shall never be moved.
^7Lord, by thy favour thou hast made my mountain to stand strong: thou didst hide thy face, and I was troubled.
^8I cried to thee, O Lord; and unto the Lord I made supplication.
^9What profit is there in my blood, when I go down to the pit? Shall the dust praise thee? shall it declare thy truth?
^10Hear, O Lord, and have mercy upon me: Lord, be thou my helper.
^11Thou hast turned for me my mourning into dancing: thou hast put off my sackcloth, and girded me with gladness;
^12To the end that my glory may sing praise to thee, and not be silent. O Lord my God, I will give thanks unto thee for ever.

Psalm 31

^1In thee, O Lord, do I put my trust; let me never be ashamed: deliver me in thy righteousness.
^2Bow down thine ear to me; deliver me speedily: be thou my strong rock, for an house of defence to save me.
^3For thou art my rock and my fortress; therefore for thy name’s sake lead me, and guide me.
^4Pull me out of the net that they have laid privily for me: for thou art my strength.
^5Into thine hand I commit my spirit: thou hast redeemed me, O Lord God of truth.
^6I have hated them that regard lying vanities: but I trust in the Lord.
^7I will be glad and rejoice in thy mercy: for thou hast considered my trouble; thou hast known my soul in adversities;
^8And hast not shut me up into the hand of the enemy: thou hast set my feet in a large room.
^9Have mercy upon me, O Lord, for I am in trouble: mine eye is consumed with grief, yea, my soul and my belly.
^10For my life is spent with grief, and my years with sighing: my strength faileth because of mine iniquity, and my bones are consumed.
^11I was a reproach among all mine enemies, but especially among my neighbours, and a fear to mine acquaintance: they that did see me without fled from me.
^12I am forgotten as a dead man out of mind: I am like a broken vessel.
^13For I have heard the slander of many: fear was on every side: while they took counsel together against me, they devised to take away my life.
^14But I trusted in thee, O Lord: I said, Thou art my God.
^15My times are in thy hand: deliver me from the hand of mine enemies, and from them that persecute me.
^16Make thy face to shine upon thy servant: save me for thy mercies’ sake.
^17Let me not be ashamed, O Lord; for I have called upon thee: let the wicked be ashamed, and let them be silent in the grave.
^18Let the lying lips be put to silence; which speak grievous things proudly and contemptuously against the righteous.
^19Oh how great is thy goodness, which thou hast laid up for them that fear thee; which thou hast wrought for them that trust in thee before the sons of men!
^20Thou shalt hide them in the secret of thy presence from the pride of man: thou shalt keep them secretly in a pavilion from the strife of tongues.
^21Blessed be the Lord: for he hath shewed me his marvellous kindness in a strong city.
^22For I said in my haste, I am cut off from before thine eyes: nevertheless thou heardest the voice of my supplications when I cried unto thee.
^23O love the Lord, all ye his saints: for the Lord preserveth the faithful, and plentifully rewardeth the proud doer.
^24Be of good courage, and he shall strengthen your heart, all ye that hope in the Lord.

Psalm 32

^1Blessed is he whose transgression is forgiven, whose sin is covered.
^2Blessed is the man unto whom the Lord imputeth not iniquity, and in whose spirit there is no guile.
^3When I kept silence, my bones waxed old through my roaring all the day long.
^4For day and night thy hand was heavy upon me: my moisture is turned into the drought of summer. Selah.
^5I acknowledge my sin unto thee, and mine iniquity have I not hid. I said, I will confess my transgressions unto the Lord; and thou forgavest the iniquity of my sin. Selah.
^6For this shall every one that is godly pray unto thee in a time when thou mayest be found: surely in the floods of great waters they shall not come nigh unto him.
^7Thou art my hiding place; thou shalt preserve me from trouble; thou shalt compass me about with songs of deliverance. Selah.
^8I will instruct thee and teach thee in the way which thou shalt go: I will guide thee with mine eye.
^9Be ye not as the horse, or as the mule, which have no understanding: whose mouth must be held in with bit and bridle, lest they come near unto thee.
^10Many sorrows shall be to the wicked: but he that trusteth in the Lord, mercy shall compass him about.
^11Be glad in the Lord, and rejoice, ye righteous: and shout for joy, all ye that are upright in heart.

Psalm 33

^1Rejoice in the Lord, O ye righteous: for praise is comely for the upright.
^2Praise the Lord with harp: sing unto him with the psaltery and an instrument of ten strings.
^3Sing unto him a new song; play skilfully with a loud noise.
^4For the word of the Lord is right; and all his works are done in truth.
^5He loveth righteousness and judgment: the earth is full of the goodness of the Lord.
^6By the word of the Lord were the heavens made; and all the host of them by the breath of his mouth.
^7He gathereth the waters of the sea together as an heap: he layeth up the depth in storehouses.
^8Let all the earth fear the Lord: let all the inhabitants of the world stand in awe of him.
^9For he spake, and it was done; he commanded, and it stood fast.
^10The Lord bringeth the counsel of the heathen to nought: he maketh the devices of the people of none effect.
^11The counsel of the Lord standeth for ever, the thoughts of his heart to all generations.
^12Blessed is the nation whose God is the Lord; and the people whom he hath chosen for his own inheritance.
^13The Lord looketh from heaven; he beholdeth all the sons of men.
^14From the place of his habitation he looketh upon all the inhabitants of the earth.
^15He fashioneth their hearts alike; he considereth all their works.
^16There is no king saved by the multitude of an host: a mighty man is not delivered by much strength.
^17An horse is a vain thing for safety: neither shall he deliver any by his great strength.
^18Behold, the eye of the Lord is upon them that fear him, upon them that hope in his mercy;
^19To deliver their soul from death, and to keep them alive in famine.
^20Our soul waiteth for the Lord: he is our help and our shield.
^21For our heart shall rejoice in him, because we have trusted in his holy name.
^22Let thy mercy, O Lord, be upon us, according as we hope in thee.

Psalm 34

^1I will bless the Lord at all times: his praise shall continually be in my mouth.
^2My soul shall make her boast in the Lord: the humble shall hear thereof, and be glad.
^3O magnify the Lord with me, and let us exalt his name together.
^4I sought the Lord, and he heard me, and delivered me from all my fears.
^5They looked unto him, and were lightened: and their faces were not ashamed.
^6This poor man cried, and the Lord heard him, and saved him out of all his troubles.
^7The angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear him, and delivereth them.
^8O taste and see that the Lord is good: blessed is the man that trusteth in him.
^9O fear the Lord, ye his saints: for there is no want to them that fear him.
^10The young lions do lack, and suffer hunger: but they that seek the Lord shall not want any good thing.
^11Come, ye children, hearken unto me: I will teach you the fear of the Lord.
^12What man is he that desireth life, and loveth many days, that he may see good?
^13Keep thy tongue from evil, and thy lips from speaking guile.
^14Depart from evil, and do good; seek peace, and pursue it.
^15The eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, and his ears are open unto their cry.
^16The face of the Lord is against them that do evil, to cut off the remembrance of them from the earth.
^17The righteous cry, and the Lord heareth, and delivereth them out of all their troubles.
^18The Lord is nigh unto them that are of a broken heart; and saveth such as be of a contrite spirit.
^19Many are the afflictions of the righteous: but the Lord delivereth him out of them all.
^20He keepeth all his bones: not one of them is broken.
^21Evil shall slay the wicked: and they that hate the righteous shall be desolate.
^22The Lord redeemeth the soul of his servants: and none of them that trust in him shall be desolate.

Psalm 35

^1Plead my cause, O Lord, with them that strive with me: fight against them that fight against me.
^2Take hold of shield and buckler, and stand up for mine help.
^3Draw out also the spear, and stop the way against them that persecute me: say unto my soul, I am thy salvation.
^4Let them be confounded and put to shame that seek after my soul: let them be turned back and brought to confusion that devise my hurt.
^5Let them be as chaff before the wind: and let the angel of the Lord chase them.
^6Let their way be dark and slippery: and let the angel of the Lord persecute them.
^7For without cause have they hid for me their net in a pit, which without cause they have digged for my soul.
^8Let destruction come upon him at unawares; and let his net that he hath hid catch himself: into that very destruction let him fall.
^9And my soul shall be joyful in the Lord: it shall rejoice in his salvation.
^10All my bones shall say, Lord, who is like unto thee, which deliverest the poor from him that is too strong for him, yea, the poor and the needy from him that spoileth him?
^11False witnesses did rise up; they laid to my charge things that I knew not.
^12They rewarded me evil for good to the spoiling of my soul.
^13But as for me, when they were sick, my clothing was sackcloth: I humbled my soul with fasting; and my prayer returned into mine own bosom.
^14I behaved myself as though he had been my friend or brother: I bowed down heavily, as one that mourneth for his mother.
^15But in mine adversity they rejoiced, and gathered themselves together: yea, the abjects gathered themselves together against me, and I knew it not; they did tear me, and ceased not:
^16With hypocritical mockers in feasts, they gnashed upon me with their teeth.
^17Lord, how long wilt thou look on? rescue my soul from their destructions, my darling from the lions.
^18I will give thee thanks in the great congregation: I will praise thee among much people.
^19Let not them that are mine enemies wrongfully rejoice over me: neither let them wink with the eye that hate me without a cause.
^20For they speak not peace: but they devise deceitful matters against them that are quiet in the land.
^21Yea, they opened their mouth wide against me, and said, Aha, aha, our eye hath seen it.
^22This thou hast seen, O Lord: keep not silence: O Lord, be not far from me.
^23Stir up thyself, and awake to my judgment, even unto my cause, my God and my Lord.
^24Judge me, O Lord my God, according to thy righteousness; and let them not rejoice over me.
^25Let them not say in their hearts, Ah, so would we have it: let them not say, We have swallowed him up.
^26Let them be ashamed and brought to confusion together that rejoice at mine hurt: let them be clothed with shame and dishonour that magnify themselves against me.
^27Let them shout for joy, and be glad, that favour my righteous cause: yea, let them say continually, Let the Lord be magnified, which hath pleasure in the prosperity of his servant.
^28And my tongue shall speak of thy righteousness and of thy praise all the day long.

Psalm 36

^1The transgression of the wicked saith within my heart, that there is no fear of God before his eyes.
^2For he flattereth himself in his own eyes, until his iniquity be found to be hateful.
^3The words of his mouth are iniquity and deceit: he hath left off to be wise, and to do good.
^4He deviseth mischief upon his bed; he setteth himself in a way that is not good; he abhorreth not evil.
^5Thy mercy, O Lord, is in the heavens; and thy faithfulness reacheth unto the clouds.
^6Thy righteousness is like the great mountains; thy judgments are a great deep: O Lord, thou preservest man and beast.
^7How excellent is thy lovingkindness, O God! therefore the children of men put their trust under the shadow of thy wings.
^8They shall be abundantly satisfied with the fatness of thy house; and thou shalt make them drink of the river of thy pleasures.
^9For with thee is the fountain of life: in thy light shall we see light.
^10O continue thy lovingkindness unto them that know thee; and thy righteousness to the upright in heart.
^11Let not the foot of pride come against me, and let not the hand of the wicked remove me.
^12There are the workers of iniquity fallen: they are cast down, and shall not be able to rise.

Psalm 37

^1Fret not thyself because of evildoers, neither be thou envious against the workers of iniquity.
^2For they shall soon be cut down like the grass, and wither as the green herb.
^3Trust in the Lord, and do good; so shalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou shalt be fed.
^4Delight thyself also in the Lord: and he shall give thee the desires of thine heart.
^5Commit thy way unto the Lord; trust also in him; and he shall bring it to pass.
^6And he shall bring forth thy righteousness as the light, and thy judgment as the noonday.
^7Rest in the Lord, and wait patiently for him: fret not thyself because of him who prospereth in his way, because of the man who bringeth wicked devices to pass.
^8Cease from anger, and forsake wrath: fret not thyself in any wise to do evil.
^9For evildoers shall be cut off: but those that wait upon the Lord, they shall inherit the earth.
^10For yet a little while, and the wicked shall not be: yea, thou shalt diligently consider his place, and it shall not be.
^11But the meek shall inherit the earth; and shall delight themselves in the abundance of peace.
^12The wicked plotteth against the just, and gnasheth upon him with his teeth.
^13The Lord shall laugh at him: for he seeth that his day is coming.
^14The wicked have drawn out the sword, and have bent their bow, to cast down the poor and needy, and to slay such as be of upright conversation.
^15Their sword shall enter into their own heart, and their bows shall be broken.
^16A little that a righteous man hath is better than the riches of many wicked.
^17For the arms of the wicked shall be broken: but the Lord upholdeth the righteous.
^18The Lord knoweth the days of the upright: and their inheritance shall be for ever.
^19They shall not be ashamed in the evil time: and in the days of famine they shall be satisfied.
^20But the wicked shall perish, and the enemies of the Lord shall be as the fat of lambs: they shall consume; into smoke shall they consume away.
^21The wicked borroweth, and payeth not again: but the righteous sheweth mercy, and giveth.
^22For such as be blessed of him shall inherit the earth; and they that be cursed of him shall be cut off.
^23The steps of a good man are ordered by the Lord: and he delighteth in his way.
^24Though he fall, he shall not be utterly cast down: for the Lord upholdeth him with his hand.
^25I have been young, and now am old; yet have I not seen the righteous forsaken, nor his seed begging bread.
^26He is ever merciful, and lendeth; and his seed is blessed.
^27Depart from evil, and do good; and dwell for evermore.
^28For the Lord loveth judgment, and forsaketh not his saints; they are preserved for ever: but the seed of the wicked shall be cut off.
^29The righteous shall inherit the land, and dwell therein for ever.
^30The mouth of the righteous speaketh wisdom, and his tongue talketh of judgment.
^31The law of his God is in his heart; none of his steps shall slide.
^32The wicked watcheth the righteous, and seeketh to slay him.
^33The Lord will not leave him in his hand, nor condemn him when he is judged.
^34Wait on the Lord, and keep his way, and he shall exalt thee to inherit the land: when the wicked are cut off, thou shalt see it.
^35I have seen the wicked in great power, and spreading himself like a green bay tree.
^36Yet he passed away, and, lo, he was not: yea, I sought him, but he could not be found.
^37Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace.
^38But the transgressors shall be destroyed together: the end of the wicked shall be cut off.
^39But the salvation of the righteous is of the Lord: he is their strength in the time of trouble.
^40And the Lord shall help them, and deliver them: he shall deliver them from the wicked, and save them, because they trust in him.

Psalm 38

^1O lord, rebuke me not in thy wrath: neither chasten me in thy hot displeasure.
^2For thine arrows stick fast in me, and thy hand presseth me sore.
^3There is no soundness in my flesh because of thine anger; neither is there any rest in my bones because of my sin.
^4For mine iniquities are gone over mine head: as an heavy burden they are too heavy for me.
^5My wounds stink and are corrupt because of my foolishness.
^6I am troubled; I am bowed down greatly; I go mourning all the day long.
^7For my loins are filled with a loathsome disease: and there is no soundness in my flesh.
^8I am feeble and sore broken: I have roared by reason of the disquietness of my heart.
^9Lord, all my desire is before thee; and my groaning is not hid from thee.
^10My heart panteth, my strength faileth me: as for the light of mine eyes, it also is gone from me.
^11My lovers and my friends stand aloof from my sore; and my kinsmen stand afar off.
^12They also that seek after my life lay snares for me: and they that seek my hurt speak mischievous things, and imagine deceits all the day long.
^13But I, as a deaf man, heard not; and I was as a dumb man that openeth not his mouth.
^14Thus I was as a man that heareth not, and in whose mouth are no reproofs.
^15For in thee, O Lord, do I hope: thou wilt hear, O Lord my God.
^16For I said, Hear me, lest otherwise they should rejoice over me: when my foot slippeth, they magnify themselves against me.
^17For I am ready to halt, and my sorrow is continually before me.
^18For I will declare mine iniquity; I will be sorry for my sin.
^19But mine enemies are lively, and they are strong: and they that hate me wrongfully are multiplied.
^20They also that render evil for good are mine adversaries; because I follow the thing that good is.
^21Forsake me not, O Lord: O my God, be not far from me.
^22Make haste to help me, O Lord my salvation.

Psalm 39

^1I said, I will take heed to my ways, that I sin not with my tongue: I will keep my mouth with a bridle, while the wicked is before me.
^2I was dumb with silence, I held my peace, even from good; and my sorrow was stirred.
^3My heart was hot within me, while I was musing the fire burned: then spake I with my tongue,
^4Lord, make me to know mine end, and the measure of my days, what it is: that I may know how frail I am.
^5Behold, thou hast made my days as an handbreadth; and mine age is as nothing before thee: verily every man at his best state is altogether vanity. Selah.
^6Surely every man walketh in a vain shew: surely they are disquieted in vain: he heapeth up riches, and knoweth not who shall gather them.
^7And now, Lord, what wait I for? my hope is in thee.
^8Deliver me from all my transgressions: make me not the reproach of the foolish.
^9I was dumb, I opened not my mouth; because thou didst it.
^10Remove thy stroke away from me: I am consumed by the blow of thine hand.
^11When thou with rebukes dost correct man for iniquity, thou makest his beauty to consume away like a moth: surely every man is vanity. Selah.
^12Hear my prayer, O Lord, and give ear unto my cry; hold not thy peace at my tears: for I am a stranger with thee, and a sojourner, as all my fathers were.
^13O spare me, that I may recover strength, before I go hence, and be no more.

Psalm 40

^1I waited patiently for the Lord; and he inclined unto me, and heard my cry.
^2He brought me up also out of an horrible pit, out of the miry clay, and set my feet upon a rock, and established my goings.
^3And he hath put a new song in my mouth, even praise unto our God: many shall see it, and fear, and shall trust in the Lord.
^4Blessed is that man that maketh the Lord his trust, and respecteth not the proud, nor such as turn aside to lies.
^5Many, O Lord my God, are thy wonderful works which thou hast done, and thy thoughts which are to us-ward: they cannot be reckoned up in order unto thee: if I would declare and speak of them, they are more than can be numbered.
^6Sacrifice and offering thou didst not desire; mine ears hast thou opened: burnt offering and sin offering hast thou not required.
^7Then said I, Lo, I come: in the volume of the book it is written of me,
^8I delight to do thy will, O my God: yea, thy law is within my heart.
^9I have preached righteousness in the great congregation: lo, I have not refrained my lips, O Lord, thou knowest.
^10I have not hid thy righteousness within my heart; I have declared thy faithfulness and thy salvation: I have not concealed thy lovingkindness and thy truth from the great congregation.
^11Withhold not thou thy tender mercies from me, O Lord: let thy lovingkindness and thy truth continually preserve me.
^12For innumerable evils have compassed me about: mine iniquities have taken hold upon me, so that I am not able to look up; they are more than the hairs of mine head: therefore my heart faileth me.
^13Be pleased, O Lord, to deliver me: O Lord, make haste to help me.
^14Let them be ashamed and confounded together that seek after my soul to destroy it; let them be driven backward and put to shame that wish me evil.
^15Let them be desolate for a reward of their shame that say unto me, Aha, aha.
^16Let all those that seek thee rejoice and be glad in thee: let such as love thy salvation say continually, The Lord be magnified.
^17But I am poor and needy; yet the Lord thinketh upon me: thou art my help and my deliverer; make no tarrying, O my God.

Psalm 41

^1Blessed is he that considereth the poor: the Lord will deliver him in time of trouble.
^2The Lord will preserve him, and keep him alive; and he shall be blessed upon the earth: and thou wilt not deliver him unto the will of his enemies.
^3The Lord will strengthen him upon the bed of languishing: thou wilt make all his bed in his sickness.
^4I said, Lord, be merciful unto me: heal my soul; for I have sinned against thee.
^5Mine enemies speak evil of me, When shall he die, and his name perish?
^6And if he come to see me, he speaketh vanity: his heart gathereth iniquity to itself; when he goeth abroad, he telleth it.
^7All that hate me whisper together against me: against me do they devise my hurt.
^8An evil disease, say they, cleaveth fast unto him: and now that he lieth he shall rise up no more.
^9Yea, mine own familiar friend, in whom I trusted, which did eat of my bread, hath lifted up his heel against me.
^10But thou, O Lord, be merciful unto me, and raise me up, that I may requite them.
^11By this I know that thou favourest me, because mine enemy doth not triumph over me.
^12And as for me, thou upholdest me in mine integrity, and settest me before thy face for ever.
^13Blessed be the Lord God of Israel from everlasting, and to everlasting. Amen, and Amen.

Psalm 42

^1As the hart panteth after the water brooks, so panteth my soul after thee, O God.
^2My soul thirsteth for God, for the living God: when shall I come and appear before God?
^3My tears have been my meat day and night, while they continually say unto me, Where is thy God?
^4When I remember these things, I pour out my soul in me: for I had gone with the multitude, I went with them to the house of God, with the voice of joy and praise, with a multitude that kept holyday.
^5Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou disquieted in me? hope thou in God: for I shall yet praise him for the help of his countenance.
^6O my God, my soul is cast down within me: therefore will I remember thee from the land of Jordan, and of the Hermonites, from the hill Mizar.
^7Deep calleth unto deep at the noise of thy waterspouts: all thy waves and thy billows are gone over me.
^8Yet the Lord will command his lovingkindness in the day time, and in the night his song shall be with me, and my prayer unto the God of my life.
^9I will say unto God my rock, Why hast thou forgotten me? why go I mourning because of the oppression of the enemy?
^10As with a sword in my bones, mine enemies reproach me; while they say daily unto me, Where is thy God?
^11Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou disquieted within me? hope thou in God: for I shall yet praise him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God.

Psalm 43

^1Judge me, O God, and plead my cause against an ungodly nation: O deliver me from the deceitful and unjust man.
^2For thou art the God of my strength: why dost thou cast me off? why go I mourning because of the oppression of the enemy?
^3O send out thy light and thy truth: let them lead me; let them bring me unto thy holy hill, and to thy tabernacles.
^4Then will I go unto the altar of God, unto God my exceeding joy: yea, upon the harp will I praise thee, O God my God.
^5Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou disquieted within me? hope in God: for I shall yet praise him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God.

Psalm 44

^1We have heard with our ears, O God, our fathers have told us, what work thou didst in their days, in the times of old.
^2How thou didst drive out the heathen with thy hand, and plantedst them; how thou didst afflict the people, and cast them out.
^3For they got not the land in possession by their own sword, neither did their own arm save them: but thy right hand, and thine arm, and the light of thy countenance, because thou hadst a favour unto them.
^4Thou art my King, O God: command deliverances for Jacob.
^5Through thee will we push down our enemies: through thy name will we tread them under that rise up against us.
^6For I will not trust in my bow, neither shall my sword save me.
^7But thou hast saved us from our enemies, and hast put them to shame that hated us.
^8In God we boast all the day long, and praise thy name for ever. Selah.
^9But thou hast cast off, and put us to shame; and goest not forth with our armies.
^10Thou makest us to turn back from the enemy: and they which hate us spoil for themselves.
^11Thou hast given us like sheep appointed for meat; and hast scattered us among the heathen.
^12Thou sellest thy people for nought, and dost not increase thy wealth by their price.
^13Thou makest us a reproach to our neighbours, a scorn and a derision to them that are round about us.
^14Thou makest us a byword among the heathen, a shaking of the head among the people.
^15My confusion is continually before me, and the shame of my face hath covered me,
^16For the voice of him that reproacheth and blasphemeth; by reason of the enemy and avenger.
^17All this is come upon us; yet have we not forgotten thee, neither have we dealt falsely in thy covenant.
^18Our heart is not turned back, neither have our steps declined from thy way;
^19Though thou hast sore broken us in the place of dragons, and covered us with the shadow of death.
^20If we have forgotten the name of our God, or stretched out our hands to a strange god;
^21Shall not God search this out? for he knoweth the secrets of the heart.
^22Yea, for thy sake are we killed all the day long; we are counted as sheep for the slaughter.
^23Awake, why sleepest thou, O Lord? arise, cast us not off for ever.
^24Wherefore hidest thou thy face, and forgettest our affliction and our oppression?
^25For our soul is bowed down to the dust: our belly cleaveth unto the earth.
^26Arise for our help, and redeem us for thy mercies’ sake.

Psalm 45

^1My heart is inditing a good matter: I speak of the things which I have made touching the king: my tongue is the pen of a ready writer.
^2Thou art fairer than the children of men: grace is poured into thy lips: therefore God hath blessed thee for ever.
^3Gird thy sword upon thy thigh, O most mighty, with thy glory and thy majesty.
^4And in thy majesty ride prosperously because of truth and meekness and righteousness; and thy right hand shall teach thee terrible things.
^5Thine arrows are sharp in the heart of the king’s enemies; whereby the people fall under thee.
^6Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever: the sceptre of thy kingdom is a right sceptre.
^7Thou lovest righteousness, and hatest wickedness: therefore God, thy God, hath anointed thee with the oil of gladness above thy fellows.
^8All thy garments smell of myrrh, and aloes, and cassia, out of the ivory palaces, whereby they have made thee glad.
^9Kings’ daughters were among thy honourable women: upon thy right hand did stand the queen in gold of Ophir.
^10Hearken, O daughter, and consider, and incline thine ear; forget also thine own people, and thy father’s house;
^11So shall the king greatly desire thy beauty: for he is thy Lord; and worship thou him.
^12And the daughter of Tyre shall be there with a gift; even the rich among the people shall intreat thy favour.
^13The king’s daughter is all glorious within: her clothing is of wrought gold.
^14She shall be brought unto the king in raiment of needlework: the virgins her companions that follow her shall be brought unto thee.
^15With gladness and rejoicing shall they be brought: they shall enter into the king’s palace.
^16Instead of thy fathers shall be thy children, whom thou mayest make princes in all the earth.
^17I will make thy name to be remembered in all generations: therefore shall the people praise thee for ever and ever.

Psalm 46

^1God is our refuge and strength, a very present help in trouble.
^2Therefore will not we fear, though the earth be removed, and though the mountains be carried into the midst of the sea;
^3Though the waters thereof roar and be troubled, though the mountains shake with the swelling thereof. Selah.
^4There is a river, the streams whereof shall make glad the city of God, the holy place of the tabernacles of the most High.
^5God is in the midst of her; she shall not be moved: God shall help her, and that right early.
^6The heathen raged, the kingdoms were moved: he uttered his voice, the earth melted.
^7The Lord of hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our refuge. Selah.
^8Come, behold the works of the Lord, what desolations he hath made in the earth.
^9He maketh wars to cease unto the end of the earth; he breaketh the bow, and cutteth the spear in sunder; he burneth the chariot in the fire.
^10Be still, and know that I am God: I will be exalted among the heathen, I will be exalted in the earth.
^11The Lord of hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our refuge. Selah.

Psalm 47

^1O clap your hands, all ye people; shout unto God with the voice of triumph.
^2For the Lord most high is terrible; he is a great King over all the earth.
^3He shall subdue the people under us, and the nations under our feet.
^4He shall choose our inheritance for us, the excellency of Jacob whom he loved. Selah.
^5God is gone up with a shout, the Lord with the sound of a trumpet.
^6Sing praises to God, sing praises: sing praises unto our King, sing praises.
^7For God is the King of all the earth: sing ye praises with understanding.
^8God reigneth over the heathen: God sitteth upon the throne of his holiness.
^9The princes of the people are gathered together, even the people of the God of Abraham: for the shields of the earth belong unto God: he is greatly exalted.

Psalm 48

^1Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised in the city of our God, in the mountain of his holiness.
^2Beautiful for situation, the joy of the whole earth, is mount Zion, on the sides of the north, the city of the great King.
^3God is known in her palaces for a refuge.
^4For, lo, the kings were assembled, they passed by together.
^5They saw it, and so they marvelled; they were troubled, and hasted away.
^6Fear took hold upon them there, and pain, as of a woman in travail.
^7Thou breakest the ships of Tarshish with an east wind.
^8As we have heard, so have we seen in the city of the Lord of hosts, in the city of our God: God will establish it for ever. Selah.
^9We have thought of thy lovingkindness, O God, in the midst of thy temple.
^10According to thy name, O God, so is thy praise unto the ends of the earth: thy right hand is full of righteousness.
^11Let mount Zion rejoice, let the daughters of Judah be glad, because of thy judgments.
^12Walk about Zion, and go round about her: tell the towers thereof.
^13Mark ye well her bulwarks, consider her palaces; that ye may tell it to the generation following.
^14For this God is our God for ever and ever: he will be our guide even unto death.

Psalm 49

^1Hear this, all ye people; give ear, all ye inhabitants of the world:
^2Both low and high, rich and poor, together.
^3My mouth shall speak of wisdom; and the meditation of my heart shall be of understanding.
^4I will incline mine ear to a parable: I will open my dark saying upon the harp.
^5Wherefore should I fear in the days of evil, when the iniquity of my heels shall compass me about?
^6They that trust in their wealth, and boast themselves in the multitude of their riches;
^7None of them can by any means redeem his brother, nor give to God a ransom for him:
^8(For the redemption of their soul is precious, and it ceaseth for ever:)
^9That he should still live for ever, and not see corruption.
^10For he seeth that wise men die, likewise the fool and the brutish person perish, and leave their wealth to others.
^11Their inward thought is, that their houses shall continue for ever, and their dwelling places to all generations; they call their lands after their own names.
^12Nevertheless man being in honour abideth not: he is like the beasts that perish.
^13This their way is their folly: yet their posterity approve their sayings. Selah.
^14Like sheep they are laid in the grave; death shall feed on them; and the upright shall have dominion over them in the morning; and their beauty shall consume in the grave from their dwelling.
^15But God will redeem my soul from the power of the grave: for he shall receive me. Selah.
^16Be not thou afraid when one is made rich, when the glory of his house is increased;
^17For when he dieth he shall carry nothing away: his glory shall not descend after him.
^18Though while he lived he blessed his soul: and men will praise thee, when thou doest well to thyself.
^19He shall go to the generation of his fathers; they shall never see light.
^20Man that is in honour, and understandeth not, is like the beasts that perish.

Psalm 50

^1The mighty God, even the Lord, hath spoken, and called the earth from the rising of the sun unto the going down thereof.
^2Out of Zion, the perfection of beauty, God hath shined.
^3Our God shall come, and shall not keep silence: a fire shall devour before him, and it shall be very tempestuous round about him.
^4He shall call to the heavens from above, and to the earth, that he may judge his people.
^5Gather my saints together unto me; those that have made a covenant with me by sacrifice.
^6And the heavens shall declare his righteousness: for God is judge himself. Selah.
^7Hear, O my people, and I will speak; O Israel, and I will testify against thee: I am God, even thy God.
^8I will not reprove thee for thy sacrifices or thy burnt offerings, to have been continually before me.
^9I will take no bullock out of thy house, nor he goats out of thy folds.
^10For every beast of the forest is mine, and the cattle upon a thousand hills.
^11I know all the fowls of the mountains: and the wild beasts of the field are mine.
^12If I were hungry, I would not tell thee: for the world is mine, and the fulness thereof.
^13Will I eat the flesh of bulls, or drink the blood of goats?
^14Offer unto God thanksgiving; and pay thy vows unto the most High:
^15And call upon me in the day of trouble: I will deliver thee, and thou shalt glorify me.
^16But unto the wicked God saith, What hast thou to do to declare my statutes, or that thou shouldest take my covenant in thy mouth?
^17Seeing thou hatest instruction, and casteth my words behind thee.
^18When thou sawest a thief, then thou consentedst with him, and hast been partaker with adulterers.
^19Thou givest thy mouth to evil, and thy tongue frameth deceit.
^20Thou sittest and speakest against thy brother; thou slanderest thine own mother’s son.
^21These things hast thou done, and I kept silence; thou thoughtest that I was altogether such an one as thyself: but I will reprove thee, and set them in order before thine eyes.
^22Now consider this, ye that forget God, lest I tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver.
^23Whoso offereth praise glorifieth me: and to him that ordereth his conversation aright will I shew the salvation of God.

Psalm 51

^1Have mercy upon me, O God, according to thy lovingkindness: according unto the multitude of thy tender mercies blot out my transgressions.
^2Wash me throughly from mine iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin.
^3For I acknowledge my transgressions: and my sin is ever before me.
^4Against thee, thee only, have I sinned, and done this evil in thy sight: that thou mightest be justified when thou speakest, and be clear when thou judgest.
^5Behold, I was shapen in iniquity; and in sin did my mother conceive me.
^6Behold, thou desirest truth in the inward parts: and in the hidden part thou shalt make me to know wisdom.
^7Purge me with hyssop, and I shall be clean: wash me, and I shall be whiter than snow.
^8Make me to hear joy and gladness; that the bones which thou hast broken may rejoice.
^9Hide thy face from my sins, and blot out all mine iniquities.
^10Create in me a clean heart, O God; and renew a right spirit within me.
^11Cast me not away from thy presence; and take not thy holy spirit from me.
^12Restore unto me the joy of thy salvation; and uphold me with thy free spirit.
^13Then will I teach transgressors thy ways; and sinners shall be converted unto thee.
^14Deliver me from bloodguiltiness, O God, thou God of my salvation: and my tongue shall sing aloud of thy righteousness.
^15O Lord, open thou my lips; and my mouth shall shew forth thy praise.
^16For thou desirest not sacrifice; else would I give it: thou delightest not in burnt offering.
^17The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit: a broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not despise.
^18Do good in thy good pleasure unto Zion: build thou the walls of Jerusalem.
^19Then shalt thou be pleased with the sacrifices of righteousness, with burnt offering and whole burnt offering: then shall they offer bullocks upon thine altar.

Psalm 52

^1Why boastest thou thyself in mischief, O mighty man? the goodness of God endureth continually.
^2The tongue deviseth mischiefs; like a sharp razor, working deceitfully.
^3Thou lovest evil more than good; and lying rather than to speak righteousness. Selah.
^4Thou lovest all devouring words, O thou deceitful tongue.
^5God shall likewise destroy thee for ever, he shall take thee away, and pluck thee out of thy dwelling place, and root thee out of the land of the living. Selah.
^6The righteous also shall see, and fear, and shall laugh at him:
^7Lo, this is the man that made not God his strength; but trusted in the abundance of his riches, and strengthened himself in his wickedness.
^8But I am like a green olive tree in the house of God: I trust in the mercy of God for ever and ever.
^9I will praise thee for ever, because thou hast done it: and I will wait on thy name; for it is good before thy saints.

Psalm 53

^1The fool hath said in his heart, There is no God. Corrupt are they, and have done abominable iniquity: there is none that doeth good.
^2God looked down from heaven upon the children of men, to see if there were any that did understand, that did seek God.
^3Every one of them is gone back: they are altogether become filthy; there is none that doeth good, no, not one.
^4Have the workers of iniquity no knowledge? who eat up my people as they eat bread: they have not called upon God.
^5There were they in great fear, where no fear was: for God hath scattered the bones of him that encampeth against thee: thou hast put them to shame, because God hath despised them.
^6Oh that the salvation of Israel were come out of Zion! When God bringeth back the captivity of his people, Jacob shall rejoice, and Israel shall be glad.

Psalm 54

^1Save me, O God, by thy name, and judge me by thy strength.
^2Hear my prayer, O God; give ear to the words of my mouth.
^3For strangers are risen up against me, and oppressors seek after my soul: they have not set God before them. Selah.
^4Behold, God is mine helper: the Lord is with them that uphold my soul.
^5He shall reward evil unto mine enemies: cut them off in thy truth.
^6I will freely sacrifice unto thee: I will praise thy name, O Lord; for it is good.
^7For he hath delivered me out of all trouble: and mine eye hath seen his desire upon mine enemies.

Psalm 55

^1Give ear to my prayer, O God; and hide not thyself from my supplication.
^2Attend unto me, and hear me: I mourn in my complaint, and make a noise;
^3Because of the voice of the enemy, because of the oppression of the wicked: for they cast iniquity upon me, and in wrath they hate me.
^4My heart is sore pained within me: and the terrors of death are fallen upon me.
^5Fearfulness and trembling are come upon me, and horror hath overwhelmed me.
^6And I said, Oh that I had wings like a dove! for then would I fly away, and be at rest.
^7Lo, then would I wander far off, and remain in the wilderness. Selah.
^8I would hasten my escape from the windy storm and tempest.
^9Destroy, O Lord, and divide their tongues: for I have seen violence and strife in the city.
^10Day and night they go about it upon the walls thereof: mischief also and sorrow are in the midst of it.
^11Wickedness is in the midst thereof: deceit and guile depart not from her streets.
^12For it was not an enemy that reproached me; then I could have borne it: neither was it he that hated me that did magnify himself against me; then I would have hid myself from him:
^13But it was thou, a man mine equal, my guide, and mine acquaintance.
^14We took sweet counsel together, and walked unto the house of God in company.
^15Let death seize upon them, and let them go down quick into hell: for wickedness is in their dwellings, and among them.
^16As for me, I will call upon God; and the Lord shall save me.
^17Evening, and morning, and at noon, will I pray, and cry aloud: and he shall hear my voice.
^18He hath delivered my soul in peace from the battle that was against me: for there were many with me.
^19God shall hear, and afflict them, even he that abideth of old. Selah. Because they have no changes, therefore they fear not God.
^20He hath put forth his hands against such as be at peace with him: he hath broken his covenant.
^21The words of his mouth were smoother than butter, but war was in his heart: his words were softer than oil, yet were they drawn swords.
^22Cast thy burden upon the Lord, and he shall sustain thee: he shall never suffer the righteous to be moved.
^23But thou, O God, shalt bring them down into the pit of destruction: bloody and deceitful men shall not live out half their days; but I will trust in thee.

Psalm 56

^1Be merciful unto me, O God: for man would swallow me up; he fighting daily oppresseth me.
^2Mine enemies would daily swallow me up: for they be many that fight against me, O thou most High.
^3What time I am afraid, I will trust in thee.
^4In God I will praise his word, in God I have put my trust; I will not fear what flesh can do unto me.
^5Every day they wrest my words: all their thoughts are against me for evil.
^6They gather themselves together, they hide themselves, they mark my steps, when they wait for my soul.
^7Shall they escape by iniquity? in thine anger cast down the people, O God.
^8Thou tellest my wanderings: put thou my tears into thy bottle: are they not in thy book?
^9When I cry unto thee, then shall mine enemies turn back: this I know; for God is for me.
^10In God will I praise his word: in the Lord will I praise his word.
^11In God have I put my trust: I will not be afraid what man can do unto me.
^12Thy vows are upon me, O God: I will render praises unto thee.
^13For thou hast delivered my soul from death: wilt not thou deliver my feet from falling, that I may walk before God in the light of the living?

Psalm 57

^1Be merciful unto me, O God, be merciful unto me: for my soul trusteth in thee: yea, in the shadow of thy wings will I make my refuge, until these calamities be overpast.
^2I will cry unto God most high; unto God that performeth all things for me.
^3He shall send from heaven, and save me from the reproach of him that would swallow me up. Selah. God shall send forth his mercy and his truth.
^4My soul is among lions: and I lie even among them that are set on fire, even the sons of men, whose teeth are spears and arrows, and their tongue a sharp sword.
^5Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens; let thy glory be above all the earth.
^6They have prepared a net for my steps; my soul is bowed down: they have digged a pit before me, into the midst whereof they are fallen themselves. Selah.
^7My heart is fixed, O God, my heart is fixed: I will sing and give praise.
^8Awake up, my glory; awake, psaltery and harp: I myself will awake early.
^9I will praise thee, O Lord, among the people: I will sing unto thee among the nations.
^10For thy mercy is great unto the heavens, and thy truth unto the clouds.
^11Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens: let thy glory be above all the earth.

Psalm 58

^1Do ye indeed speak righteousness, O congregation? do ye judge uprightly, O ye sons of men?
^2Yea, in heart ye work wickedness; ye weigh the violence of your hands in the earth.
^3The wicked are estranged from the womb: they go astray as soon as they be born, speaking lies.
^4Their poison is like the poison of a serpent: they are like the deaf adder that stoppeth her ear;
^5Which will not hearken to the voice of charmers, charming never so wisely.
^6Break their teeth, O God, in their mouth: break out the great teeth of the young lions, O Lord.
^7Let them melt away as waters which run continually: when he bendeth his bow to shoot his arrows, let them be as cut in pieces.
^8As a snail which melteth, let every one of them pass away: like the untimely birth of a woman, that they may not see the sun.
^9Before your pots can feel the thorns, he shall take them away as with a whirlwind, both living, and in his wrath.
^10The righteous shall rejoice when he seeth the vengeance: he shall wash his feet in the blood of the wicked.
^11So that a man shall say, Verily there is a reward for the righteous: verily he is a God that judgeth in the earth.

Psalm 59

^1Deliver me from mine enemies, O my God: defend me from them that rise up against me.
^2Deliver me from the workers of iniquity, and save me from bloody men.
^3For, lo, they lie in wait for my soul: the mighty are gathered against me; not for my transgression, nor for my sin, O Lord.
^4They run and prepare themselves without my fault: awake to help me, and behold.
^5Thou therefore, O Lord God of hosts, the God of Israel, awake to visit all the heathen: be not merciful to any wicked transgressors. Selah.
^6They return at evening: they make a noise like a dog, and go round about the city.
^7Behold, they belch out with their mouth: swords are in their lips: for who, say they, doth hear?
^8But thou, O Lord, shalt laugh at them; thou shalt have all the heathen in derision.
^9Because of his strength will I wait upon thee: for God is my defence.
^10The God of my mercy shall prevent me: God shall let me see my desire upon mine enemies.
^11Slay them not, lest my people forget: scatter them by thy power; and bring them down, O Lord our shield.
^12For the sin of their mouth and the words of their lips let them even be taken in their pride: and for cursing and lying which they speak.
^13Consume them in wrath, consume them, that they may not be: and let them know that God ruleth in Jacob unto the ends of the earth. Selah.
^14And at evening let them return; and let them make a noise like a dog, and go round about the city.
^15Let them wander up and down for meat, and grudge if they be not satisfied.
^16But I will sing of thy power; yea, I will sing aloud of thy mercy in the morning: for thou hast been my defence and refuge in the day of my trouble.
^17Unto thee, O my strength, will I sing: for God is my defence, and the God of my mercy.

Psalm 60

^1O God, thou hast cast us off, thou hast scattered us, thou hast been displeased; O turn thyself to us again.
^2Thou hast made the earth to tremble; thou hast broken it: heal the breaches thereof; for it shaketh.
^3Thou hast shewed thy people hard things: thou hast made us to drink the wine of astonishment.
^4Thou hast given a banner to them that fear thee, that it may be displayed because of the truth. Selah.
^5That thy beloved may be delivered; save with thy right hand, and hear me.
^6God hath spoken in his holiness; I will rejoice, I will divide Shechem, and mete out the valley of Succoth.
^7Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine; Ephraim also is the strength of mine head; Judah is my lawgiver;
^8Moab is my washpot; over Edom will I cast out my shoe: Philistia, triumph thou because of me.
^9Who will bring me into the strong city? who will lead me into Edom?
^10Wilt not thou, O God, which hadst cast us off? and thou, O God, which didst not go out with our armies?
^11Give us help from trouble: for vain is the help of man.
^12Through God we shall do valiantly: for he it is that shall tread down our enemies.

Psalm 61

^1Hear my cry, O God; attend unto my prayer.
^2From the end of the earth will I cry unto thee, when my heart is overwhelmed: lead me to the rock that is higher than I.
^3For thou hast been a shelter for me, and a strong tower from the enemy.
^4I will abide in thy tabernacle for ever: I will trust in the covert of thy wings. Selah.
^5For thou, O God, hast heard my vows: thou hast given me the heritage of those that fear thy name.
^6Thou wilt prolong the king’s life: and his years as many generations.
^7He shall abide before God for ever: O prepare mercy and truth, which may preserve him.
^8So will I sing praise unto thy name for ever, that I may daily perform my vows.

Psalm 62

^1Truly my soul waiteth upon God: from him cometh my salvation.
^2He only is my rock and my salvation; he is my defence; I shall not be greatly moved.
^3How long will ye imagine mischief against a man? ye shall be slain all of you: as a bowing wall shall ye be, and as a tottering fence.
^4They only consult to cast him down from his excellency: they delight in lies: they bless with their mouth, but they curse inwardly. Selah.
^5My soul, wait thou only upon God; for my expectation is from him.
^6He only is my rock and my salvation: he is my defence; I shall not be moved.
^7In God is my salvation and my glory: the rock of my strength, and my refuge, is in God.
^8Trust in him at all times; ye people, pour out your heart before him: God is a refuge for us. Selah.
^9Surely men of low degree are vanity, and men of high degree are a lie: to be laid in the balance, they are altogether lighter than vanity.
^10Trust not in oppression, and become not vain in robbery: if riches increase, set not your heart upon them.
^11God hath spoken once; twice have I heard this; that power belongeth unto God.
^12Also unto thee, O Lord, belongeth mercy: for thou renderest to every man according to his work.

Psalm 63

^1O God, thou art my God; early will I seek thee: my soul thirsteth for thee, my flesh longeth for thee in a dry and thirsty land, where no water is;
^2To see thy power and thy glory, so as I have seen thee in the sanctuary.
^3Because thy lovingkindness is better than life, my lips shall praise thee.
^4Thus will I bless thee while I live: I will lift up my hands in thy name.
^5My soul shall be satisfied as with marrow and fatness; and my mouth shall praise thee with joyful lips:
^6When I remember thee upon my bed, and meditate on thee in the night watches.
^7Because thou hast been my help, therefore in the shadow of thy wings will I rejoice.
^8My soul followeth hard after thee: thy right hand upholdeth me.
^9But those that seek my soul, to destroy it, shall go into the lower parts of the earth.
^10They shall fall by the sword: they shall be a portion for foxes.
^11But the king shall rejoice in God; every one that sweareth by him shall glory: but the mouth of them that speak lies shall be stopped.

Psalm 64

^1Hear my voice, O God, in my prayer: preserve my life from fear of the enemy.
^2Hide me from the secret counsel of the wicked; from the insurrection of the workers of iniquity:
^3Who whet their tongue like a sword, and bend their bows to shoot their arrows, even bitter words:
^4That they may shoot in secret at the perfect: suddenly do they shoot at him, and fear not.
^5They encourage themselves in an evil matter: they commune of laying snares privily; they say, Who shall see them?
^6They search out iniquities; they accomplish a diligent search: both the inward thought of every one of them, and the heart, is deep.
^7But God shall shoot at them with an arrow; suddenly shall they be wounded.
^8So they shall make their own tongue to fall upon themselves: all that see them shall flee away.
^9And all men shall fear, and shall declare the work of God; for they shall wisely consider of his doing.
^10The righteous shall be glad in the Lord, and shall trust in him; and all the upright in heart shall glory.

Psalm 65

^1Praise waiteth for thee, O God, in Sion: and unto thee shall the vow be performed.
^2O thou that hearest prayer, unto thee shall all flesh come.
^3Iniquities prevail against me: as for our transgressions, thou shalt purge them away.
^4Blessed is the man whom thou choosest, and causest to approach unto thee, that he may dwell in thy courts: we shall be satisfied with the goodness of thy house, even of thy holy temple.
^5By terrible things in righteousness wilt thou answer us, O God of our salvation; who art the confidence of all the ends of the earth, and of them that are afar off upon the sea:
^6Which by his strength setteth fast the mountains; being girded with power:
^7Which stilleth the noise of the seas, the noise of their waves, and the tumult of the people.
^8They also that dwell in the uttermost parts are afraid at thy tokens: thou makest the outgoings of the morning and evening to rejoice.
^9Thou visitest the earth, and waterest it: thou greatly enrichest it with the river of God, which is full of water: thou preparest them corn, when thou hast so provided for it.
^10Thou waterest the ridges thereof abundantly: thou settlest the furrows thereof: thou makest it soft with showers: thou blessest the springing thereof.
^11Thou crownest the year with thy goodness; and thy paths drop fatness.
^12They drop upon the pastures of the wilderness: and the little hills rejoice on every side.
^13The pastures are clothed with flocks; the valleys also are covered over with corn; they shout for joy, they also sing.

Psalm 66

^1Make a joyful noise unto God, all ye lands:
^2Sing forth the honour of his name: make his praise glorious.
^3Say unto God, How terrible art thou in thy works! through the greatness of thy power shall thine enemies submit themselves unto thee.
^4All the earth shall worship thee, and shall sing unto thee; they shall sing to thy name. Selah.
^5Come and see the works of God: he is terrible in his doing toward the children of men.
^6He turned the sea into dry land: they went through the flood on foot: there did we rejoice in him.
^7He ruleth by his power for ever; his eyes behold the nations: let not the rebellious exalt themselves. Selah.
^8O bless our God, ye people, and make the voice of his praise to be heard:
^9Which holdeth our soul in life, and suffereth not our feet to be moved.
^10For thou, O God, hast proved us: thou hast tried us, as silver is tried.
^11Thou broughtest us into the net; thou laidst affliction upon our loins.
^12Thou hast caused men to ride over our heads; we went through fire and through water: but thou broughtest us out into a wealthy place.
^13I will go into thy house with burnt offerings: I will pay thee my vows,
^14Which my lips have uttered, and my mouth hath spoken, when I was in trouble.
^15I will offer unto thee burnt sacrifices of fatlings, with the incense of rams; I will offer bullocks with goats. Selah.
^16Come and hear, all ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my soul.
^17I cried unto him with my mouth, and he was extolled with my tongue.
^18If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me:
^19But verily God hath heard me; he hath attended to the voice of my prayer.
^20Blessed be God, which hath not turned away my prayer, nor his mercy from me.

Psalm 67

^1God be merciful unto us, and bless us; and cause his face to shine upon us; Selah.
^2That thy way may be known upon earth, thy saving health among all nations.
^3Let the people praise thee, O God; let all the people praise thee.
^4O let the nations be glad and sing for joy: for thou shalt judge the people righteously, and govern the nations upon earth. Selah.
^5Let the people praise thee, O God; let all the people praise thee.
^6Then shall the earth yield her increase; and God, even our own God, shall bless us.
^7God shall bless us; and all the ends of the earth shall fear him.

Psalm 68

^1Let God arise, let his enemies be scattered: let them also that hate him flee before him.
^2As smoke is driven away, so drive them away: as wax melteth before the fire, so let the wicked perish at the presence of God.
^3But let the righteous be glad; let them rejoice before God: yea, let them exceedingly rejoice.
^4Sing unto God, sing praises to his name: extol him that rideth upon the heavens by his name Jah, and rejoice before him.
^5A father of the fatherless, and a judge of the widows, is God in his holy habitation.
^6God setteth the solitary in families: he bringeth out those which are bound with chains: but the rebellious dwell in a dry land.
^7O God, when thou wentest forth before thy people, when thou didst march through the wilderness; Selah:
^8The earth shook, the heavens also dropped at the presence of God: even Sinai itself was moved at the presence of God, the God of Israel.
^9Thou, O God, didst send a plentiful rain, whereby thou didst confirm thine inheritance, when it was weary.
^10Thy congregation hath dwelt therein: thou, O God, hast prepared of thy goodness for the poor.
^11The Lord gave the word: great was the company of those that published it.
^12Kings of armies did flee apace: and she that tarried at home divided the spoil.
^13Though ye have lien among the pots, yet shall ye be as the wings of a dove covered with silver, and her feathers with yellow gold.
^14When the Almighty scattered kings in it, it was white as snow in Salmon.
^15The hill of God is as the hill of Bashan; an high hill as the hill of Bashan.
^16Why leap ye, ye high hills? this is the hill which God desireth to dwell in; yea, the Lord will dwell in it for ever.
^17The chariots of God are twenty thousand, even thousands of angels: the Lord is among them, as in Sinai, in the holy place.
^18Thou hast ascended on high, thou hast led captivity captive: thou hast received gifts for men; yea, for the rebellious also, that the Lord God might dwell among them.
^19Blessed be the Lord, who daily loadeth us with benefits, even the God of our salvation. Selah.
^20He that is our God is the God of salvation; and unto God the Lord belong the issues from death.
^21But God shall wound the head of his enemies, and the hairy scalp of such an one as goeth on still in his trespasses.
^22The Lord said, I will bring again from Bashan, I will bring my people again from the depths of the sea:
^23That thy foot may be dipped in the blood of thine enemies, and the tongue of thy dogs in the same.
^24They have seen thy goings, O God; even the goings of my God, my King, in the sanctuary.
^25The singers went before, the players on instruments followed after; among them were the damsels playing with timbrels.
^26Bless ye God in the congregations, even the Lord, from the fountain of Israel.
^27There is little Benjamin with their ruler, the princes of Judah and their council, the princes of Zebulun, and the princes of Naphtali.
^28Thy God hath commanded thy strength: strengthen, O God, that which thou hast wrought for us.
^29Because of thy temple at Jerusalem shall kings bring presents unto thee.
^30Rebuke the company of spearmen, the multitude of the bulls, with the calves of the people, till every one submit himself with pieces of silver: scatter thou the people that delight in war.
^31Princes shall come out of Egypt; Ethiopia shall soon stretch out her hands unto God.
^32Sing unto God, ye kingdoms of the earth; O sing praises unto the Lord; Selah:
^33To him that rideth upon the heavens of heavens, which were of old; lo, he doth send out his voice, and that a mighty voice.
^34Ascribe ye strength unto God: his excellency is over Israel, and his strength is in the clouds.
^35O God, thou art terrible out of thy holy places: the God of Israel is he that giveth strength and power unto his people. Blessed be God.

Psalm 69

^1Save me, O God; for the waters are come in unto my soul.
^2I sink in deep mire, where there is no standing: I am come into deep waters, where the floods overflow me.
^3I am weary of my crying: my throat is dried: mine eyes fail while I wait for my God.
^4They that hate me without a cause are more than the hairs of mine head: they that would destroy me, being mine enemies wrongfully, are mighty: then I restored that which I took not away.
^5O God, thou knowest my foolishness; and my sins are not hid from thee.
^6Let not them that wait on thee, O Lord God of hosts, be ashamed for my sake: let not those that seek thee be confounded for my sake, O God of Israel.
^7Because for thy sake I have borne reproach; shame hath covered my face.
^8I am become a stranger unto my brethren, and an alien unto my mother’s children.
^9For the zeal of thine house hath eaten me up; and the reproaches of them that reproached thee are fallen upon me.
^10When I wept, and chastened my soul with fasting, that was to my reproach.
^11I made sackcloth also my garment; and I became a proverb to them.
^12They that sit in the gate speak against me; and I was the song of the drunkards.
^13But as for me, my prayer is unto thee, O Lord, in an acceptable time: O God, in the multitude of thy mercy hear me, in the truth of thy salvation.
^14Deliver me out of the mire, and let me not sink: let me be delivered from them that hate me, and out of the deep waters.
^15Let not the waterflood overflow me, neither let the deep swallow me up, and let not the pit shut her mouth upon me.
^16Hear me, O Lord; for thy lovingkindness is good: turn unto me according to the multitude of thy tender mercies.
^17And hide not thy face from thy servant; for I am in trouble: hear me speedily.
^18Draw nigh unto my soul, and redeem it: deliver me because of mine enemies.
^19Thou hast known my reproach, and my shame, and my dishonour: mine adversaries are all before thee.
^20Reproach hath broken my heart; and I am full of heaviness: and I looked for some to take pity, but there was none; and for comforters, but I found none.
^21They gave me also gall for my meat; and in my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink.
^22Let their table become a snare before them: and that which should have been for their welfare, let it become a trap.
^23Let their eyes be darkened, that they see not; and make their loins continually to shake.
^24Pour out thine indignation upon them, and let thy wrathful anger take hold of them.
^25Let their habitation be desolate; and let none dwell in their tents.
^26For they persecute him whom thou hast smitten; and they talk to the grief of those whom thou hast wounded.
^27Add iniquity unto their iniquity: and let them not come into thy righteousness.
^28Let them be blotted out of the book of the living, and not be written with the righteous.
^29But I am poor and sorrowful: let thy salvation, O God, set me up on high.
^30I will praise the name of God with a song, and will magnify him with thanksgiving.
^31This also shall please the Lord better than an ox or bullock that hath horns and hoofs.
^32The humble shall see this, and be glad: and your heart shall live that seek God.
^33For the Lord heareth the poor, and despiseth not his prisoners.
^34Let the heaven and earth praise him, the seas, and every thing that moveth therein.
^35For God will save Zion, and will build the cities of Judah: that they may dwell there, and have it in possession.
^36The seed also of his servants shall inherit it: and they that love his name shall dwell therein.

19:^1MAKE HASTE, O God, TO DELIVER ME; MAKE HASTE TO HELP ME, O Lord.

^2Let them be ashamed and confounded that seek after my soul: let them be turned backward, and put to confusion, that desire my hurt.
^3Let them be turned back for a reward of their shame that say, Aha, aha.
^4Let all those that seek thee rejoice and be glad in thee: and let such as love thy salvation say continually, Let God be magnified.
^5But I am poor and needy: make haste unto me, O God: thou art my help and my deliverer; O Lord, make no tarrying.

Psalm 71

^1In thee, O Lord, do I put my trust: let me never be put to confusion.
^2Deliver me in thy righteousness, and cause me to escape: incline thine ear unto me, and save me.
^3Be thou my strong habitation, whereunto I may continually resort: thou hast given commandment to save me; for thou art my rock and my fortress.
^4Deliver me, O my God, out of the hand of the wicked, out of the hand of the unrighteous and cruel man.
^5For thou art my hope, O Lord God: thou art my trust from my youth.
^6By thee have I been holden up from the womb: thou art he that took me out of my mother’s bowels: my praise shall be continually of thee.
^7I am as a wonder unto many; but thou art my strong refuge.
^8Let my mouth be filled with thy praise and with thy honour all the day.
^9Cast me not off in the time of old age; forsake me not when my strength faileth.
^10For mine enemies speak against me; and they that lay wait for my soul take counsel together,
^11Saying, God hath forsaken him: persecute and take him; for there is none to deliver him.
^12O God, be not far from me: O my God, make haste for my help.
^13Let them be confounded and consumed that are adversaries to my soul; let them be covered with reproach and dishonour that seek my hurt.
^14But I will hope continually, and will yet praise thee more and more.
^15My mouth shall shew forth thy righteousness and thy salvation all the day; for I know not the numbers thereof.
^16I will go in the strength of the Lord God: I will make mention of thy righteousness, even of thine only.
^17O God, thou hast taught me from my youth: and hitherto have I declared thy wondrous works.
^18Now also when I am old and greyheaded, O God, forsake me not; until I have shewed thy strength unto this generation, and thy power to every one that is to come.
^19Thy righteousness also, O God, is very high, who hast done great things: O God, who is like unto thee!
^20Thou, which hast shewed me great and sore troubles, shalt quicken me again, and shalt bring me up again from the depths of the earth.
^21Thou shalt increase my greatness, and comfort me on every side.
^22I will also praise thee with the psaltery, even thy truth, O my God: unto thee will I sing with the harp, O thou Holy One of Israel.
^23My lips shall greatly rejoice when I sing unto thee; and my soul, which thou hast redeemed.
^24My tongue also shall talk of thy righteousness all the day long: for they are confounded, for they are brought unto shame, that seek my hurt.

Psalm 72

^1Give the king thy judgments, O God, and thy righteousness unto the king’s son.
^2He shall judge thy people with righteousness, and thy poor with judgment.
^3The mountains shall bring peace to the people, and the little hills, by righteousness.
^4He shall judge the poor of the people, he shall save the children of the needy, and shall break in pieces the oppressor.
^5They shall fear thee as long as the sun and moon endure, throughout all generations.
^6He shall come down like rain upon the mown grass: as showers that water the earth.
^7In his days shall the righteous flourish; and abundance of peace so long as the moon endureth.
^8He shall have dominion also from sea to sea, and from the river unto the ends of the earth.
^9They that dwell in the wilderness shall bow before him; and his enemies shall lick the dust.
^10The kings of Tarshish and of the isles shall bring presents: the kings of Sheba and Seba shall offer gifts.
^11Yea, all kings shall fall down before him: all nations shall serve him.
^12For he shall deliver the needy when he crieth; the poor also, and him that hath no helper.
^13He shall spare the poor and needy, and shall save the souls of the needy.
^14He shall redeem their soul from deceit and violence: and precious shall their blood be in his sight.
^15And he shall live, and to him shall be given of the gold of Sheba: prayer also shall be made for him continually; and daily shall he be praised.
^16There shall be an handful of corn in the earth upon the top of the mountains; the fruit thereof shall shake like Lebanon: and they of the city shall flourish like grass of the earth.
^17His name shall endure for ever: his name shall be continued as long as the sun: and men shall be blessed in him: all nations shall call him blessed.
^18Blessed be the Lord God, the God of Israel, who only doeth wondrous things.
^19And blessed be his glorious name for ever: and let the whole earth be filled with his glory; Amen, and Amen.
^20The prayers of David the son of Jesse are ended.

Psalm 73

^1Truly God is good to Israel, even to such as are of a clean heart.
^2But as for me, my feet were almost gone; my steps had well nigh slipped.
^3For I was envious at the foolish, when I saw the prosperity of the wicked.
^4For there are no bands in their death: but their strength is firm.
^5They are not in trouble as other men; neither are they plagued like other men.
^6Therefore pride compasseth them about as a chain; violence covereth them as a garment.
^7Their eyes stand out with fatness: they have more than heart could wish.
^8They are corrupt, and speak wickedly concerning oppression: they speak loftily.
^9They set their mouth against the heavens, and their tongue walketh through the earth.
^10Therefore his people return hither: and waters of a full cup are wrung out to them.
^11And they say, How doth God know? and is there knowledge in the most High?
^12Behold, these are the ungodly, who prosper in the world; they increase in riches.
^13Verily I have cleansed my heart in vain, and washed my hands in innocency.
^14For all the day long have I been plagued, and chastened every morning.
^15If I say, I will speak thus; behold, I should offend against the generation of thy children.
^16When I thought to know this, it was too painful for me;
^17Until I went into the sanctuary of God; then understood I their end.
^18Surely thou didst set them in slippery places: thou castedst them down into destruction.
^19How are they brought into desolation, as in a moment! they are utterly consumed with terrors.
^20As a dream when one awaketh; so, O Lord, when thou awakest, thou shalt despise their image.
^21Thus my heart was grieved, and I was pricked in my reins.
^22So foolish was I, and ignorant: I was as a beast before thee.
^23Nevertheless I am continually with thee: thou hast holden me by my right hand.
^24Thou shalt guide me with thy counsel, and afterward receive me to glory.
^25Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I desire beside thee.
^26My flesh and my heart faileth: but God is the strength of my heart, and my portion for ever.
^27For, lo, they that are far from thee shall perish: thou hast destroyed all them that go a whoring from thee.
^28But it is good for me to draw near to God: I have put my trust in the Lord God, that I may declare all thy works.

Psalm 74

^1O God, why hast thou cast us off for ever? why doth thine anger smoke against the sheep of thy pasture?
^2Remember thy congregation, which thou hast purchased of old; the rod of thine inheritance, which thou hast redeemed; this mount Zion, wherein thou hast dwelt.
^3Lift up thy feet unto the perpetual desolations; even all that the enemy hath done wickedly in the sanctuary.
^4Thine enemies roar in the midst of thy congregations; they set up their ensigns for signs.
^5A man was famous according as he had lifted up axes upon the thick trees.
^6But now they break down the carved work thereof at once with axes and hammers.
^7They have cast fire into thy sanctuary, they have defiled by casting down the dwelling place of thy name to the ground.
^8They said in their hearts, Let us destroy them together: they have burned up all the synagogues of God in the land.
^9We see not our signs: there is no more any prophet: neither is there among us any that knoweth how long.
^10O God, how long shall the adversary reproach? shall the enemy blaspheme thy name for ever?
^11Why withdrawest thou thy hand, even thy right hand? pluck it out of thy bosom.
^12For God is my King of old, working salvation in the midst of the earth.
^13Thou didst divide the sea by thy strength: thou brakest the heads of the dragons in the waters.
^14Thou brakest the heads of leviathan in pieces, and gavest him to be meat to the people inhabiting the wilderness.
^15Thou didst cleave the fountain and the flood: thou driedst up mighty rivers.
^16The day is thine, the night also is thine: thou hast prepared the light and the sun.
^17Thou hast set all the borders of the earth: thou hast made summer and winter.
^18Remember this, that the enemy hath reproached, O Lord, and that the foolish people have blasphemed thy name.
^19O deliver not the soul of thy turtledove unto the multitude of the wicked: forget not the congregation of thy poor for ever.
^20Have respect unto the covenant: for the dark places of the earth are full of the habitations of cruelty.
^21O let not the oppressed return ashamed: let the poor and needy praise thy name.
^22Arise, O God, plead thine own cause: remember how the foolish man reproacheth thee daily.
^23Forget not the voice of thine enemies: the tumult of those that rise up against thee increaseth continually.

Psalm 75

^1Unto thee, O God, do we give thanks, unto thee do we give thanks: for that thy name is near thy wondrous works declare.
^2When I shall receive the congregation I will judge uprightly.
^3The earth and all the inhabitants thereof are dissolved: I bear up the pillars of it. Selah.
^4I said unto the fools, Deal not foolishly: and to the wicked, Lift not up the horn:
^5Lift not up your horn on high: speak not with a stiff neck.
^6For promotion cometh neither from the east, nor from the west, nor from the south.
^7But God is the judge: he putteth down one, and setteth up another.
^8For in the hand of the Lord there is a cup, and the wine is red; it is full of mixture; and he poureth out of the same: but the dregs thereof, all the wicked of the earth shall wring them out, and drink them.
^9But I will declare for ever; I will sing praises to the God of Jacob.
^10All the horns of the wicked also will I cut off; but the horns of the righteous shall be exalted.

Psalm 76

^1In Judah is God known: his name is great in Israel.
^2In Salem also is his tabernacle, and his dwelling place in Zion.
^3There brake he the arrows of the bow, the shield, and the sword, and the battle. Selah.
^4Thou art more glorious and excellent than the mountains of prey.
^5The stouthearted are spoiled, they have slept their sleep: and none of the men of might have found their hands.
^6At thy rebuke, O God of Jacob, both the chariot and horse are cast into a dead sleep.
^7Thou, even thou, art to be feared: and who may stand in thy sight when once thou art angry?
^8Thou didst cause judgment to be heard from heaven; the earth feared, and was still,
^9When God arose to judgment, to save all the meek of the earth. Selah.
^10Surely the wrath of man shall praise thee: the remainder of wrath shalt thou restrain.
^11Vow, and pay unto the Lord your God: let all that be round about him bring presents unto him that ought to be feared.
^12He shall cut off the spirit of princes: he is terrible to the kings of the earth.

Psalm 77

^1I cried unto God with my voice, even unto God with my voice; and he gave ear unto me.
^2In the day of my trouble I sought the Lord: my sore ran in the night, and ceased not: my soul refused to be comforted.
^3I remembered God, and was troubled: I complained, and my spirit was overwhelmed. Selah.
^4Thou holdest mine eyes waking: I am so troubled that I cannot speak.
^5I have considered the days of old, the years of ancient times.
^6I call to remembrance my song in the night: I commune with mine own heart: and my spirit made diligent search.
^7Will the Lord cast off for ever? and will he be favourable no more?
^8Is his mercy clean gone for ever? doth his promise fail for evermore?
^9Hath God forgotten to be gracious? hath he in anger shut up his tender mercies? Selah.
^10And I said, This is my infirmity: but I will remember the years of the right hand of the most High.
^11I will remember the works of the Lord: surely I will remember thy wonders of old.
^12I will meditate also of all thy work, and talk of thy doings.
^13Thy way, O God, is in the sanctuary: who is so great a God as our God?
^14Thou art the God that doest wonders: thou hast declared thy strength among the people.
^15Thou hast with thine arm redeemed thy people, the sons of Jacob and Joseph. Selah.
^16The waters saw thee, O God, the waters saw thee; they were afraid: the depths also were troubled.
^17The clouds poured out water: the skies sent out a sound: thine arrows also went abroad.
^18The voice of thy thunder was in the heaven: the lightnings lightened the world: the earth trembled and shook.
^19Thy way is in the sea, and thy path in the great waters, and thy footsteps are not known.
^20Thou leddest thy people like a flock by the hand of Moses and Aaron.

Psalm 78

^1Give ear, O my people, to my law: incline your ears to the words of my mouth.
^2I will open my mouth in a parable: I will utter dark sayings of old:
^3Which we have heard and known, and our fathers have told us.
^4We will not hide them from their children, shewing to the generation to come the praises of the Lord, and his strength, and his wonderful works that he hath done.
^5For he established a testimony in Jacob, and appointed a law in Israel, which he commanded our fathers, that they should make them known to their children:
^6That the generation to come might know them, even the children which should be born; who should arise and declare them to their children:
^7That they might set their hope in God, and not forget the works of God, but keep his commandments:
^8And might not be as their fathers, a stubborn and rebellious generation; a generation that set not their heart aright, and whose spirit was not stedfast with God.
^9The children of Ephraim, being armed, and carrying bows, turned back in the day of battle.
^10They kept not the covenant of God, and refused to walk in his law;
^11And forgat his works, and his wonders that he had shewed them.
^12Marvellous things did he in the sight of their fathers, in the land of Egypt, in the field of Zoan.
^13He divided the sea, and caused them to pass through; and he made the waters to stand as an heap.
^14In the daytime also he led them with a cloud, and all the night with a light of fire.
^15He clave the rocks in the wilderness, and gave them drink as out of the great depths.
^16He brought streams also out of the rock, and caused waters to run down like rivers.
^17And they sinned yet more against him by provoking the most High in the wilderness.
^18And they tempted God in their heart by asking meat for their lust.
^19Yea, they spake against God; they said, Can God furnish a table in the wilderness?
^20Behold, he smote the rock, that the waters gushed out, and the streams overflowed; can he give bread also? can he provide flesh for his people?
^21Therefore the Lord heard this, and was wroth: so a fire was kindled against Jacob, and anger also came up against Israel;
^22Because they believed not in God, and trusted not in his salvation:
^23Though he had commanded the clouds from above, and opened the doors of heaven,
^24And had rained down manna upon them to eat, and had given them of the corn of heaven.
^25Man did eat angels’ food: he sent them meat to the full.
^26He caused an east wind to blow in the heaven: and by his power he brought in the south wind.
^27He rained flesh also upon them as dust, and feathered fowls like as the sand of the sea:
^28And he let it fall in the midst of their camp, round about their habitations.
^29So they did eat, and were well filled: for he gave them their own desire;
^30They were not estranged from their lust. But while their meat was yet in their mouths,
^31The wrath of God came upon them, and slew the fattest of them, and smote down the chosen men of Israel.
^32For all this they sinned still, and believed not for his wondrous works.
^33Therefore their days did he consume in vanity, and their years in trouble.
^34When he slew them, then they sought him: and they returned and enquired early after God.
^35And they remembered that God was their rock, and the high God their redeemer.
^36Nevertheless they did flatter him with their mouth, and they lied unto him with their tongues.
^37For their heart was not right with him, neither were they stedfast in his covenant.
^38But he, being full of compassion, forgave their iniquity, and destroyed them not: yea, many a time turned he his anger away, and did not stir up all his wrath.
^39For he remembered that they were but flesh; a wind that passeth away, and cometh not again.
^40How oft did they provoke him in the wilderness, and grieve him in the desert!
^41Yea, they turned back and tempted God, and limited the Holy One of Israel.
^42They remembered not his hand, nor the day when he delivered them from the enemy.
^43How he had wrought his signs in Egypt, and his wonders in the field of Zoan.
^44And had turned their rivers into blood; and their floods, that they could not drink.
^45He sent divers sorts of flies among them, which devoured them; and frogs, which destroyed them.
^46He gave also their increase unto the caterpiller, and their labour unto the locust.
^47He destroyed their vines with hail, and their sycomore trees with frost.
^48He gave up their cattle also to the hail, and their flocks to hot thunderbolts.
^49He cast upon them the fierceness of his anger, wrath, and indignation, and trouble, by sending evil angels among them.
^50He made a way to his anger; he spared not their soul from death, but gave their life over to the pestilence;
^51And smote all the firstborn in Egypt; the chief of their strength in the tabernacles of Ham:
^52But made his own people to go forth like sheep, and guided them in the wilderness like a flock.
^53And he led them on safely, so that they feared not: but the sea overwhelmed their enemies.
^54And he brought them to the border of his sanctuary, even to this mountain, which his right hand had purchased.
^55He cast out the heathen also before them, and divided them an inheritance by line, and made the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tents.
^56Yet they tempted and provoked the most high God, and kept not his testimonies:
^57But turned back, and dealt unfaithfully like their fathers: they were turned aside like a deceitful bow.
^58For they provoked him to anger with their high places, and moved him to jealousy with their graven images.
^59When God heard this, he was wroth, and greatly abhorred Israel:
^60So that he forsook the tabernacle of Shiloh, the tent which he placed among men;
^61And delivered his strength into captivity, and his glory into the enemy’s hand.
^62He gave his people over also unto the sword; and was wroth with his inheritance.
^63The fire consumed their young men; and their maidens were not given to marriage.
^64Their priests fell by the sword; and their widows made no lamentation.
^65Then the Lord awaked as one out of sleep, and like a mighty man that shouteth by reason of wine.
^66And he smote his enemies in the hinder parts: he put them to a perpetual reproach.
^67Moreover he refused the tabernacle of Joseph, and chose not the tribe of Ephraim:
^68But chose the tribe of Judah, the mount Zion which he loved.
^69And he built his sanctuary like high palaces, like the earth which he hath established for ever.
^70He chose David also his servant, and took him from the sheepfolds:
^71From following the ewes great with young he brought him to feed Jacob his people, and Israel his inheritance.
^72So he fed them according to the integrity of his heart; and guided them by the skilfulness of his hands.

Psalm 79

^1O god, the heathen are come into thine inheritance; thy holy temple have they defiled; they have laid Jerusalem on heaps.
^2The dead bodies of thy servants have they given to be meat unto the fowls of the heaven, the flesh of thy saints unto the beasts of the earth.
^3Their blood have they shed like water round about Jerusalem; and there was none to bury them.
^4We are become a reproach to our neighbours, a scorn and derision to them that are round about us.
^5How long, Lord? wilt thou be angry for ever? shall thy jealousy burn like fire?
^6Pour out thy wrath upon the heathen that have not known thee, and upon the kingdoms that have not called upon thy name.
^7For they have devoured Jacob, and laid waste his dwelling place.
^8O remember not against us former iniquities: let thy tender mercies speedily prevent us: for we are brought very low.
^9Help us, O God of our salvation, for the glory of thy name: and deliver us, and purge away our sins, for thy name’s sake.
^10Wherefore should the heathen say, Where is their God? let him be known among the heathen in our sight by the revenging of the blood of thy servants which is shed.
^11Let the sighing of the prisoner come before thee; according to the greatness of thy power preserve thou those that are appointed to die;
^12And render unto our neighbours sevenfold into their bosom their reproach, wherewith they have reproached thee, O Lord.
^13So we thy people and sheep of thy pasture will give thee thanks for ever: we will shew forth thy praise to all generations.

Psalm 80

^1Give ear, O Shepherd of Israel, thou that leadest Joseph like a flock; thou that dwellest between the cherubims, shine forth.
^2Before Ephraim and Benjamin and Manasseh stir up thy strength, and come and save us.
^3Turn us again, O God, and cause thy face to shine; and we shall be saved.
^4O Lord God of hosts, how long wilt thou be angry against the prayer of thy people?
^5Thou feedest them with the bread of tears; and givest them tears to drink in great measure.
^6Thou makest us a strife unto our neighbours: and our enemies laugh among themselves.
^7Turn us again, O God of hosts, and cause thy face to shine; and we shall be saved.
^8Thou hast brought a vine out of Egypt: thou hast cast out the heathen, and planted it.
^9Thou preparedst room before it, and didst cause it to take deep root, and it filled the land.
^10The hills were covered with the shadow of it, and the boughs thereof were like the goodly cedars.
^11She sent out her boughs unto the sea, and her branches unto the river.
^12Why hast thou then broken down her hedges, so that all they which pass by the way do pluck her?
^13The boar out of the wood doth waste it, and the wild beast of the field doth devour it.
^14Return, we beseech thee, O God of hosts: look down from heaven, and behold, and visit this vine;
^15And the vineyard which thy right hand hath planted, and the branch that thou madest strong for thyself.
^16It is burned with fire, it is cut down: they perish at the rebuke of thy countenance.
^17Let thy hand be upon the man of thy right hand, upon the son of man whom thou madest strong for thyself.
^18So will not we go back from thee: quicken us, and we will call upon thy name.
^19Turn us again, O Lord God of hosts, cause thy face to shine; and we shall be saved.

Psalm 81

^1Sing aloud unto God our strength: make a joyful noise unto the God of Jacob.
^2Take a psalm, and bring hither the timbrel, the pleasant harp with the psaltery.
^3Blow up the trumpet in the new moon, in the time appointed, on our solemn feast day.
^4For this was a statute for Israel, and a law of the God of Jacob.
^5This he ordained in Joseph for a testimony, when he went out through the land of Egypt: where I heard a language that I understood not.
^6I removed his shoulder from the burden: his hands were delivered from the pots.
^7Thou calledst in trouble, and I delivered thee; I answered thee in the secret place of thunder: I proved thee at the waters of Meribah. Selah.
^8Hear, O my people, and I will testify unto thee: O Israel, if thou wilt hearken unto me;
^9There shall no strange god be in thee; neither shalt thou worship any strange god.
^10I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt: open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it.
^11But my people would not hearken to my voice; and Israel would none of me.
^12So I gave them up unto their own hearts’ lust: and they walked in their own counsels.
^13Oh that my people had hearkened unto me, and Israel had walked in my ways!
^14I should soon have subdued their enemies, and turned my hand against their adversaries.
^15The haters of the Lord should have submitted themselves unto him: but their time should have endured for ever.
^16He should have fed them also with the finest of the wheat: and with honey out of the rock should I have satisfied thee.

Psalm 82

^1God standeth in the congregation of the mighty; he judgeth among the gods.
^2How long will ye judge unjustly, and accept the persons of the wicked? Selah.
^3Defend the poor and fatherless: do justice to the afflicted and needy.
^4Deliver the poor and needy: rid them out of the hand of the wicked.
^5They know not, neither will they understand; they walk on in darkness: all the foundations of the earth are out of course.
^6I have said, Ye are gods; and all of you are children of the most High.
^7But ye shall die like men, and fall like one of the princes.
^8Arise, O God, judge the earth: for thou shalt inherit all nations.

Psalm 83

^1Keep not thou silence, O God: hold not thy peace, and be not still, O God.
^2For, lo, thine enemies make a tumult: and they that hate thee have lifted up the head.
^3They have taken crafty counsel against thy people, and consulted against thy hidden ones.
^4They have said, Come, and let us cut them off from being a nation; that the name of Israel may be no more in remembrance.
^5For they have consulted together with one consent: they are confederate against thee:
^6The tabernacles of Edom, and the Ishmaelites; of Moab, and the Hagarenes;
^7Gebal, and Ammon, and Amalek; the Philistines with the inhabitants of Tyre;
^8Assur also is joined with them: they have holpen the children of Lot. Selah.
^9Do unto them as unto the Midianites; as to Sisera, as to Jabin, at the brook of Kison:
^10Which perished at Endor: they became as dung for the earth.
^11Make their nobles like Oreb, and like Zeeb: yea, all their princes as Zebah, and as Zalmunna:
^12Who said, Let us take to ourselves the houses of God in possession.
^13O my God, make them like a wheel; as the stubble before the wind.
^14As the fire burneth a wood, and as the flame setteth the mountains on fire;
^15So persecute them with thy tempest, and make them afraid with thy storm.
^16Fill their faces with shame; that they may seek thy name, O Lord.
^17Let them be confounded and troubled for ever; yea, let them be put to shame, and perish:
^18That men may know that thou, whose name alone is Jehovah, art the most high over all the earth.

Psalm 84

^1How amiable are thy tabernacles, O Lord of hosts!
^2My soul longeth, yea, even fainteth for the courts of the Lord: my heart and my flesh crieth out for the living God.
^3Yea, the sparrow hath found an house, and the swallow a nest for herself, where she may lay her young, even thine altars, O Lord of hosts, my King, and my God.
^4Blessed are they that dwell in thy house: they will be still praising thee. Selah.
^5Blessed is the man whose strength is in thee; in whose heart are the ways of them.
^6Who passing through the valley of Baca make it a well; the rain also filleth the pools.
^7They go from strength to strength, every one of them in Zion appeareth before God.
^8O Lord God of hosts, hear my prayer: give ear, O God of Jacob. Selah.
^9Behold, O God our shield, and look upon the face of thine anointed.
^10For a day in thy courts is better than a thousand. I had rather be a doorkeeper in the house of my God, than to dwell in the tents of wickedness.
^11For the Lord God is a sun and shield: the Lord will give grace and glory: no good thing will he withhold from them that walk uprightly.
^12O Lord of hosts, blessed is the man that trusteth in thee.

Psalm 85

^1Lord, thou hast been favourable unto thy land: thou hast brought back the captivity of Jacob.
^2Thou hast forgiven the iniquity of thy people, thou hast covered all their sin. Selah.
^3Thou hast taken away all thy wrath: thou hast turned thyself from the fierceness of thine anger.
^4Turn us, O God of our salvation, and cause thine anger toward us to cease.
^5Wilt thou be angry with us for ever? wilt thou draw out thine anger to all generations?
^6Wilt thou not revive us again: that thy people may rejoice in thee?
^7Shew us thy mercy, O Lord, and grant us thy salvation.
^8I will hear what God the Lord will speak: for he will speak peace unto his people, and to his saints: but let them not turn again to folly.
^9Surely his salvation is nigh them that fear him; that glory may dwell in our land.
^10Mercy and truth are met together; righteousness and peace have kissed each other.
^11Truth shall spring out of the earth; and righteousness shall look down from heaven.
^12Yea, the Lord shall give that which is good; and our land shall yield her increase.
^13Righteousness shall go before him; and shall set us in the way of his steps.

Psalm 86

^1Bow down thine ear, O Lord, hear me: for I am poor and needy.
^2Preserve my soul; for I am holy: O thou my God, save thy servant that trusteth in thee.
^3Be merciful unto me, O Lord: for I cry unto thee daily.
^4Rejoice the soul of thy servant: for unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my soul.
^5For thou, Lord, art good, and ready to forgive; and plenteous in mercy unto all them that call upon thee.
^6Give ear, O Lord, unto my prayer; and attend to the voice of my supplications.
^7In the day of my trouble I will call upon thee: for thou wilt answer me.
^8Among the gods there is none like unto thee, O Lord; neither are there any works like unto thy works.
^9All nations whom thou hast made shall come and worship before thee, O Lord; and shall glorify thy name.
^10For thou art great, and doest wondrous things: thou art God alone.
^11Teach me thy way, O Lord; I will walk in thy truth: unite my heart to fear thy name.
^12I will praise thee, O Lord my God, with all my heart: and I will glorify thy name for evermore.
^13For great is thy mercy toward me: and thou hast delivered my soul from the lowest hell.
^14O God, the proud are risen against me, and the assemblies of violent men have sought after my soul; and have not set thee before them.
^15But thou, O Lord, art a God full of compassion, and gracious, longsuffering, and plenteous in mercy and truth.
^16O turn unto me, and have mercy upon me; give thy strength unto thy servant, and save the son of thine handmaid.
^17Shew me a token for good; that they which hate me may see it, and be ashamed: because thou, Lord, hast holpen me, and comforted me.

Psalm 87

^1His foundation is in the holy mountains.
^2The Lord loveth the gates of Zion more than all the dwellings of Jacob.
^3Glorious things are spoken of thee, O city of God. Selah.
^4I will make mention of Rahab and Babylon to them that know me: behold Philistia, and Tyre, with Ethiopia; this man was born there.
^5And of Zion it shall be said, This and that man was born in her: and the highest himself shall establish her.
^6The Lord shall count, when he writeth up the people, that this man was born there. Selah.
^7As well the singers as the players on instruments shall be there: all my springs are in thee.

Psalm 88

^1O lord God of my salvation, I have cried day and night before thee:
^2Let my prayer come before thee: incline thine ear unto my cry;
^3For my soul is full of troubles: and my life draweth nigh unto the grave.
^4I am counted with them that go down into the pit: I am as a man that hath no strength:
^5Free among the dead, like the slain that lie in the grave, whom thou rememberest no more: and they are cut off from thy hand.
^6Thou hast laid me in the lowest pit, in darkness, in the deeps.
^7Thy wrath lieth hard upon me, and thou hast afflicted me with all thy waves. Selah.
^8Thou hast put away mine acquaintance far from me; thou hast made me an abomination unto them: I am shut up, and I cannot come forth.
^9Mine eye mourneth by reason of affliction: Lord, I have called daily upon thee, I have stretched out my hands unto thee.
^10Wilt thou shew wonders to the dead? shall the dead arise and praise thee? Selah.
^11Shall thy lovingkindness be declared in the grave? or thy faithfulness in destruction?
^12Shall thy wonders be known in the dark? and thy righteousness in the land of forgetfulness?
^13But unto thee have I cried, O Lord; and in the morning shall my prayer prevent thee.
^14Lord, why castest thou off my soul? why hidest thou thy face from me?
^15I am afflicted and ready to die from my youth up: while I suffer thy terrors I am distracted.
^16Thy fierce wrath goeth over me; thy terrors have cut me off.
^17They came round about me daily like water; they compassed me about together.
^18Lover and friend hast thou put far from me, and mine acquaintance into darkness.

Psalm 89

^1I will sing of the mercies of the Lord for ever: with my mouth will I make known thy faithfulness to all generations.
^2For I have said, Mercy shall be built up for ever: thy faithfulness shalt thou establish in the very heavens.
^3I have made a covenant with my chosen, I have sworn unto David my servant,
^4Thy seed will I establish for ever, and build up thy throne to all generations. Selah.
^5And the heavens shall praise thy wonders, O Lord: thy faithfulness also in the congregation of the saints.
^6For who in the heaven can be compared unto the Lord? who among the sons of the mighty can be likened unto the Lord?
^7God is greatly to be feared in the assembly of the saints, and to be had in reverence of all them that are about him.
^8O Lord God of hosts, who is a strong Lord like unto thee? or to thy faithfulness round about thee?
^9Thou rulest the raging of the sea: when the waves thereof arise, thou stillest them.
^10Thou hast broken Rahab in pieces, as one that is slain; thou hast scattered thine enemies with thy strong arm.
^11The heavens are thine, the earth also is thine: as for the world and the fulness thereof, thou hast founded them.
^12The north and the south thou hast created them: Tabor and Hermon shall rejoice in thy name.
^13Thou hast a mighty arm: strong is thy hand, and high is thy right hand.
^14Justice and judgment are the habitation of thy throne: mercy and truth shall go before thy face.
^15Blessed is the people that know the joyful sound: they shall walk, O Lord, in the light of thy countenance.
^16In thy name shall they rejoice all the day: and in thy righteousness shall they be exalted.
^17For thou art the glory of their strength: and in thy favour our horn shall be exalted.
^18For the Lord is our defence; and the Holy One of Israel is our king.
^19Then thou spakest in vision to thy holy one, and saidst, I have laid help upon one that is mighty; I have exalted one chosen out of the people.
^20I have found David my servant; with my holy oil have I anointed him:
^21With whom my hand shall be established: mine arm also shall strengthen him.
^22The enemy shall not exact upon him; nor the son of wickedness afflict him.
^23And I will beat down his foes before his face, and plague them that hate him.
^24But my faithfulness and my mercy shall be with him: and in my name shall his horn be exalted.
^25I will set his hand also in the sea, and his right hand in the rivers.
^26He shall cry unto me, Thou art my father, my God, and the rock of my salvation.
^27Also I will make him my firstborn, higher than the kings of the earth.
^28My mercy will I keep for him for evermore, and my covenant shall stand fast with him.
^29His seed also will I make to endure for ever, and his throne as the days of heaven.
^30If his children forsake my law, and walk not in my judgments;
^31If they break my statutes, and keep not my commandments;
^32Then will I visit their transgression with the rod, and their iniquity with stripes.
^33Nevertheless my lovingkindness will I not utterly take from him, nor suffer my faithfulness to fail.
^34My covenant will I not break, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my lips.
^35Once have I sworn by my holiness that I will not lie unto David.
^36His seed shall endure for ever, and his throne as the sun before me.
^37It shall be established for ever as the moon, and as a faithful witness in heaven. Selah.
^38But thou hast cast off and abhorred, thou hast been wroth with thine anointed.
^39Thou hast made void the covenant of thy servant: thou hast profaned his crown by casting it to the ground.
^40Thou hast broken down all his hedges; thou hast brought his strong holds to ruin.
^41All that pass by the way spoil him: he is a reproach to his neighbours.
^42Thou hast set up the right hand of his adversaries; thou hast made all his enemies to rejoice.
^43Thou hast also turned the edge of his sword, and hast not made him to stand in the battle.
^44Thou hast made his glory to cease, and cast his throne down to the ground.
^45The days of his youth hast thou shortened: thou hast covered him with shame. Selah.
^46How long, Lord? wilt thou hide thyself for ever? shall thy wrath burn like fire?
^47Remember how short my time is: wherefore hast thou made all men in vain?
^48What man is he that liveth, and shall not see death? shall he deliver his soul from the hand of the grave? Selah.
^49Lord, where are thy former lovingkindnesses, which thou swarest unto David in thy truth?
^50Remember, Lord, the reproach of thy servants; how I do bear in my bosom the reproach of all the mighty people;
^51Wherewith thine enemies have reproached, O Lord; wherewith they have reproached the footsteps of thine anointed.
^52Blessed be the Lord for evermore. Amen, and Amen.

Psalm 90

^1Lord, thou hast been our dwelling place in all generations.
^2Before the mountains were brought forth, or ever thou hadst formed the earth and the world, even from everlasting to everlasting, thou art God.
^3Thou turnest man to destruction; and sayest, Return, ye children of men.
^4For a thousand years in thy sight are but as yesterday when it is past, and as a watch in the night.
^5Thou carriest them away as with a flood; they are as a sleep: in the morning they are like grass which groweth up.
^6In the morning it flourisheth, and groweth up; in the evening it is cut down, and withereth.
^7For we are consumed by thine anger, and by thy wrath are we troubled.
^8Thou hast set our iniquities before thee, our secret sins in the light of thy countenance.
^9For all our days are passed away in thy wrath: we spend our years as a tale that is told.
^10The days of our years are threescore years and ten; and if by reason of strength they be fourscore years, yet is their strength labour and sorrow; for it is soon cut off, and we fly away.
^11Who knoweth the power of thine anger? even according to thy fear, so is thy wrath.
^12So teach us to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.
^13Return, O Lord, how long? and let it repent thee concerning thy servants.
^14O satisfy us early with thy mercy; that we may rejoice and be glad all our days.
^15Make us glad according to the days wherein thou hast afflicted us, and the years wherein we have seen evil.
^16Let thy work appear unto thy servants, and thy glory unto their children.
^17And let the beauty of the Lord our God be upon us: and establish thou the work of our hands upon us; yea, the work of our hands establish thou it.

Psalm 91

^1He that dwelleth in the secret place of the most High shall abide under the shadow of the Almighty.
^2I will say of the Lord, He is my refuge and my fortress: my God; in him will I trust.
^3Surely he shall deliver thee from the snare of the fowler, and from the noisome pestilence.
^4He shall cover thee with his feathers, and under his wings shalt thou trust: his truth shall be thy shield and buckler.
^5Thou shalt not be afraid for the terror by night; nor for the arrow that flieth by day;
^6Nor for the pestilence that walketh in darkness; nor for the destruction that wasteth at noonday.
^7A thousand shall fall at thy side, and ten thousand at thy right hand; but it shall not come nigh thee.
^8Only with thine eyes shalt thou behold and see the reward of the wicked.
^9Because thou hast made the Lord, which is my refuge, even the most High, thy habitation;
^10There shall no evil befall thee, neither shall any plague come nigh thy dwelling.
^11For he shall give his angels charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy ways.
^12They shall bear thee up in their hands, lest thou dash thy foot against a stone.
^13Thou shalt tread upon the lion and adder: the young lion and the dragon shalt thou trample under feet.
^14Because he hath set his love upon me, therefore will I deliver him: I will set him on high, because he hath known my name.
^15He shall call upon me, and I will answer him: I will be with him in trouble; I will deliver him, and honour him.
^16With long life will I satisfy him, and shew him my salvation.

19:^1IT IS A GOOD THING TO GIVE THANKS UNTO THE Lord, AND TO SING PRAISES UNTO THY NAME, O MOST HIGH:

^2To shew forth thy lovingkindness in the morning, and thy faithfulness every night,
^3Upon an instrument of ten strings, and upon the psaltery; upon the harp with a solemn sound.
^4For thou, Lord, hast made me glad through thy work: I will triumph in the works of thy hands.
^5O Lord, how great are thy works! and thy thoughts are very deep.
^6A brutish man knoweth not; neither doth a fool understand this.
^7When the wicked spring as the grass, and when all the workers of iniquity do flourish; it is that they shall be destroyed for ever:
^8But thou, Lord, art most high for evermore.
^9For, lo, thine enemies, O Lord, for, lo, thine enemies shall perish; all the workers of iniquity shall be scattered.
^10But my horn shalt thou exalt like the horn of an unicorn: I shall be anointed with fresh oil.
^11Mine eye also shall see my desire on mine enemies, and mine ears shall hear my desire of the wicked that rise up against me.
^12The righteous shall flourish like the palm tree: he shall grow like a cedar in Lebanon.
^13Those that be planted in the house of the Lord shall flourish in the courts of our God.
^14They shall still bring forth fruit in old age; they shall be fat and flourishing;
^15To shew that the Lord is upright: he is my rock, and there is no unrighteousness in him.

Psalm 93

^1The Lord reigneth, he is clothed with majesty; the Lord is clothed with strength, wherewith he hath girded himself: the world also is stablished, that it cannot be moved.
^2Thy throne is established of old: thou art from everlasting.
^3The floods have lifted up, O Lord, the floods have lifted up their voice; the floods lift up their waves.
^4The Lord on high is mightier than the noise of many waters, yea, than the mighty waves of the sea.
^5Thy testimonies are very sure: holiness becometh thine house, O Lord, for ever.

Psalm 94

^1O Lord God, to whom vengeance belongeth; O God, to whom vengeance belongeth, shew thyself.
^2Lift up thyself, thou judge of the earth: render a reward to the proud.
^3Lord, how long shall the wicked, how long shall the wicked triumph?
^4How long shall they utter and speak hard things? and all the workers of iniquity boast themselves?
^5They break in pieces thy people, O Lord, and afflict thine heritage.
^6They slay the widow and the stranger, and murder the fatherless.
^7Yet they say, The Lord shall not see, neither shall the God of Jacob regard it.
^8Understand, ye brutish among the people: and ye fools, when will ye be wise?
^9He that planted the ear, shall he not hear? he that formed the eye, shall he not see?
^10He that chastiseth the heathen, shall not he correct? he that teacheth man knowledge, shall not he know?
^11The Lord knoweth the thoughts of man, that they are vanity.
^12Blessed is the man whom thou chastenest, O Lord, and teachest him out of thy law;
^13That thou mayest give him rest from the days of adversity, until the pit be digged for the wicked.
^14For the Lord will not cast off his people, neither will he forsake his inheritance.
^15But judgment shall return unto righteousness: and all the upright in heart shall follow it.
^16Who will rise up for me against the evildoers? or who will stand up for me against the workers of iniquity?
^17Unless the Lord had been my help, my soul had almost dwelt in silence.
^18When I said, My foot slippeth; thy mercy, O Lord, held me up.
^19In the multitude of my thoughts within me thy comforts delight my soul.
^20Shall the throne of iniquity have fellowship with thee, which frameth mischief by a law?
^21They gather themselves together against the soul of the righteous, and condemn the innocent blood.
^22But the Lord is my defence; and my God is the rock of my refuge.
^23And he shall bring upon them their own iniquity, and shall cut them off in their own wickedness; yea, the Lord our God shall cut them off.

Psalm 95

^1O come, let us sing unto the Lord: let us make a joyful noise to the rock of our salvation.
^2Let us come before his presence with thanksgiving, and make a joyful noise unto him with psalms.
^3For the Lord is a great God, and a great King above all gods.
^4In his hand are the deep places of the earth: the strength of the hills is his also.
^5The sea is his, and he made it: and his hands formed the dry land.
^6O come, let us worship and bow down: let us kneel before the Lord our maker.
^7For he is our God; and we are the people of his pasture, and the sheep of his hand. To day if ye will hear his voice,
^8Harden not your heart, as in the provocation, and as in the day of temptation in the wilderness:
^9When your fathers tempted me, proved me, and saw my work.
^10Forty years long was I grieved with this generation, and said, It is a people that do err in their heart, and they have not known my ways:
^11Unto whom I sware in my wrath that they should not enter into my rest.

Psalm 96

^1O sing unto the Lord a new song: sing unto the Lord, all the earth.
^2Sing unto the Lord, bless his name; shew forth his salvation from day to day.
^3Declare his glory among the heathen, his wonders among all people.
^4For the Lord is great, and greatly to be praised: he is to be feared above all gods.
^5For all the gods of the nations are idols: but the Lord made the heavens.
^6Honour and majesty are before him: strength and beauty are in his sanctuary.
^7Give unto the Lord, O ye kindreds of the people, give unto the Lord glory and strength.
^8Give unto the Lord the glory due unto his name: bring an offering, and come into his courts.
^9O worship the Lord in the beauty of holiness: fear before him, all the earth.
^10Say among the heathen that the Lord reigneth: the world also shall be established that it shall not be moved: he shall judge the people righteously.
^11Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth be glad; let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof.
^12Let the field be joyful, and all that is therein: then shall all the trees of the wood rejoice
^13Before the Lord: for he cometh, for he cometh to judge the earth: he shall judge the world with righteousness, and the people with his truth.

Psalm 97

^1The Lord reigneth; let the earth rejoice; let the multitude of isles be glad thereof.
^2Clouds and darkness are round about him: righteousness and judgment are the habitation of his throne.
^3A fire goeth before him, and burneth up his enemies round about.
^4His lightnings enlightened the world: the earth saw, and trembled.
^5The hills melted like wax at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the Lord of the whole earth.
^6The heavens declare his righteousness, and all the people see his glory.
^7Confounded be all they that serve graven images, that boast themselves of idols: worship him, all ye gods.
^8Zion heard, and was glad; and the daughters of Judah rejoiced because of thy judgments, O Lord.
^9For thou, Lord, art high above all the earth: thou art exalted far above all gods.
^10Ye that love the Lord, hate evil: he preserveth the souls of his saints; he delivereth them out of the hand of the wicked.
^11Light is sown for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in heart.
^12Rejoice in the Lord, ye righteous; and give thanks at the remembrance of his holiness.

Psalm 98

^1O sing unto the Lord a new song; for he hath done marvellous things: his right hand, and his holy arm, hath gotten him the victory.
^2The Lord hath made known his salvation: his righteousness hath he openly shewed in the sight of the heathen.
^3He hath remembered his mercy and his truth toward the house of Israel: all the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God.
^4Make a joyful noise unto the Lord, all the earth: make a loud noise, and rejoice, and sing praise.
^5Sing unto the Lord with the harp; with the harp, and the voice of a psalm.
^6With trumpets and sound of cornet make a joyful noise before the Lord, the King.
^7Let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof; the world, and they that dwell therein.
^8Let the floods clap their hands: let the hills be joyful together
^9Before the Lord; for he cometh to judge the earth: with righteousness shall he judge the world, and the people with equity.

Psalm 99

^1The Lord reigneth; let the people tremble: he sitteth between the cherubims; let the earth be moved.
^2The Lord is great in Zion; and he is high above all the people.
^3Let them praise thy great and terrible name; for it is holy.
^4The king’s strength also loveth judgment; thou dost establish equity, thou executest judgment and righteousness in Jacob.
^5Exalt ye the Lord our God, and worship at his footstool; for he is holy.
^6Moses and Aaron among his priests, and Samuel among them that call upon his name; they called upon the Lord, and he answered them.
^7He spake unto them in the cloudy pillar: they kept his testimonies, and the ordinance that he gave them.
^8Thou answeredst them, O Lord our God: thou wast a God that forgavest them, though thou tookest vengeance of their inventions.
^9Exalt the Lord our God, and worship at his holy hill; for the Lord our God is holy.

Psalm 100

^1Make a joyful noise unto the Lord, all ye lands.
^2Serve the Lord with gladness: come before his presence with singing.
^3Know ye that the Lord he is God: it is he that hath made us, and not we ourselves; we are his people, and the sheep of his pasture.
^4Enter into his gates with thanksgiving, and into his courts with praise: be thankful unto him, and bless his name.
^5For the Lord is good; his mercy is everlasting; and his truth endureth to all generations.

Psalm 101

^1I will sing of mercy and judgment: unto thee, O Lord, will I sing.
^2I will behave myself wisely in a perfect way. O when wilt thou come unto me? I will walk within my house with a perfect heart.
^3I will set no wicked thing before mine eyes: I hate the work of them that turn aside; it shall not cleave to me.
^4A froward heart shall depart from me: I will not know a wicked person.
^5Whoso privily slandereth his neighbour, him will I cut off: him that hath an high look and a proud heart will not I suffer.
^6Mine eyes shall be upon the faithful of the land, that they may dwell with me: he that walketh in a perfect way, he shall serve me.
^7He that worketh deceit shall not dwell within my house: he that telleth lies shall not tarry in my sight.
^8I will early destroy all the wicked of the land; that I may cut off all wicked doers from the city of the Lord.

Psalm 102

^1Hear my prayer, O Lord, and let my cry come unto thee.
^2Hide not thy face from me in the day when I am in trouble; incline thine ear unto me: in the day when I call answer me speedily.
^3For my days are consumed like smoke, and my bones are burned as an hearth.
^4My heart is smitten, and withered like grass; so that I forget to eat my bread.
^5By reason of the voice of my groaning my bones cleave to my skin.
^6I am like a pelican of the wilderness: I am like an owl of the desert.
^7I watch, and am as a sparrow alone upon the house top.
^8Mine enemies reproach me all the day; and they that are mad against me are sworn against me.
^9For I have eaten ashes like bread, and mingled my drink with weeping.
^10Because of thine indignation and thy wrath: for thou hast lifted me up, and cast me down.
^11My days are like a shadow that declineth; and I am withered like grass.
^12But thou, O Lord, shall endure for ever; and thy remembrance unto all generations.
^13Thou shalt arise, and have mercy upon Zion: for the time to favour her, yea, the set time, is come.
^14For thy servants take pleasure in her stones, and favour the dust thereof.
^15So the heathen shall fear the name of the Lord, and all the kings of the earth thy glory.
^16When the Lord shall build up Zion, he shall appear in his glory.
^17He will regard the prayer of the destitute, and not despise their prayer.
^18This shall be written for the generation to come: and the people which shall be created shall praise the Lord.
^19For he hath looked down from the height of his sanctuary; from heaven did the Lord behold the earth;
^20To hear the groaning of the prisoner; to loose those that are appointed to death;
^21To declare the name of the Lord in Zion, and his praise in Jerusalem;
^22When the people are gathered together, and the kingdoms, to serve the Lord.
^23He weakened my strength in the way; he shortened my days.
^24I said, O my God, take me not away in the midst of my days: thy years are throughout all generations.
^25Of old hast thou laid the foundation of the earth: and the heavens are the work of thy hands.
^26They shall perish, but thou shalt endure: yea, all of them shall wax old like a garment; as a vesture shalt thou change them, and they shall be changed:
^27But thou art the same, and thy years shall have no end.
^28The children of thy servants shall continue, and their seed shall be established before thee.

Psalm 103

^1Bless the Lord, O my soul: and all that is within me, bless his holy name.
^2Bless the Lord, O my soul, and forget not all his benefits:
^3Who forgiveth all thine iniquities; who healeth all thy diseases;
^4Who redeemeth thy life from destruction; who crowneth thee with lovingkindness and tender mercies;
^5Who satisfieth thy mouth with good things; so that thy youth is renewed like the eagle’s.
^6The Lord executeth righteousness and judgment for all that are oppressed.
^7He made known his ways unto Moses, his acts unto the children of Israel.
^8The Lord is merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and plenteous in mercy.
^9He will not always chide: neither will he keep his anger for ever.
^10He hath not dealt with us after our sins; nor rewarded us according to our iniquities.
^11For as the heaven is high above the earth, so great is his mercy toward them that fear him.
^12As far as the east is from the west, so far hath he removed our transgressions from us.
^13Like as a father pitieth his children, so the Lord pitieth them that fear him.
^14For he knoweth our frame; he remembereth that we are dust.
^15As for man, his days are as grass: as a flower of the field, so he flourisheth.
^16For the wind passeth over it, and it is gone; and the place thereof shall know it no more.
^17But the mercy of the Lord is from everlasting to everlasting upon them that fear him, and his righteousness unto children’s children;
^18To such as keep his covenant, and to those that remember his commandments to do them.
^19The Lord hath prepared his throne in the heavens; and his kingdom ruleth over all.
^20Bless the Lord, ye his angels, that excel in strength, that do his commandments, hearkening unto the voice of his word.
^21Bless ye the Lord, all ye his hosts; ye ministers of his, that do his pleasure.
^22Bless the Lord, all his works in all places of his dominion: bless the Lord, O my soul.

Psalm 104

^1Bless the Lord, O my soul. O Lord my God, thou art very great; thou art clothed with honour and majesty.
^2Who coverest thyself with light as with a garment: who stretchest out the heavens like a curtain:
^3Who layeth the beams of his chambers in the waters: who maketh the clouds his chariot: who walketh upon the wings of the wind:
^4Who maketh his angels spirits; his ministers a flaming fire:
^5Who laid the foundations of the earth, that it should not be removed for ever.
^6Thou coveredst it with the deep as with a garment: the waters stood above the mountains.
^7At thy rebuke they fled; at the voice of thy thunder they hasted away.
^8They go up by the mountains; they go down by the valleys unto the place which thou hast founded for them.
^9Thou hast set a bound that they may not pass over; that they turn not again to cover the earth.
^10He sendeth the springs into the valleys, which run among the hills.
^11They give drink to every beast of the field: the wild asses quench their thirst.
^12By them shall the fowls of the heaven have their habitation, which sing among the branches.
^13He watereth the hills from his chambers: the earth is satisfied with the fruit of thy works.
^14He causeth the grass to grow for the cattle, and herb for the service of man: that he may bring forth food out of the earth;
^15And wine that maketh glad the heart of man, and oil to make his face to shine, and bread which strengtheneth man’s heart.
^16The trees of the Lord are full of sap; the cedars of Lebanon, which he hath planted;
^17Where the birds make their nests: as for the stork, the fir trees are her house.
^18The high hills are a refuge for the wild goats; and the rocks for the conies.
^19He appointed the moon for seasons: the sun knoweth his going down.
^20Thou makest darkness, and it is night: wherein all the beasts of the forest do creep forth.
^21The young lions roar after their prey, and seek their meat from God.
^22The sun ariseth, they gather themselves together, and lay them down in their dens.
^23Man goeth forth unto his work and to his labour until the evening.
^24O Lord, how manifold are thy works! in wisdom hast thou made them all: the earth is full of thy riches.
^25So is this great and wide sea, wherein are things creeping innumerable, both small and great beasts.
^26There go the ships: there is that leviathan, whom thou hast made to play therein.
^27These wait all upon thee; that thou mayest give them their meat in due season.
^28That thou givest them they gather: thou openest thine hand, they are filled with good.
^29Thou hidest thy face, they are troubled: thou takest away their breath, they die, and return to their dust.
^30Thou sendest forth thy spirit, they are created: and thou renewest the face of the earth.
^31The glory of the Lord shall endure for ever: the Lord shall rejoice in his works.
^32He looketh on the earth, and it trembleth: he toucheth the hills, and they smoke.
^33I will sing unto the Lord as long as I live: I will sing praise to my God while I have my being.
^34My meditation of him shall be sweet: I will be glad in the Lord.
^35Let the sinners be consumed out of the earth, and let the wicked be no more. Bless thou the Lord, O my soul. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 105

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; call upon his name: make known his deeds among the people.
^2Sing unto him, sing psalms unto him: talk ye of all his wondrous works.
^3Glory ye in his holy name: let the heart of them rejoice that seek the Lord.
^4Seek the Lord, and his strength: seek his face evermore.
^5Remember his marvellous works that he hath done; his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth;
^6O ye seed of Abraham his servant, ye children of Jacob his chosen.
^7He is the Lord our God: his judgments are in all the earth.
^8He hath remembered his covenant for ever, the word which he commanded to a thousand generations.
^9Which covenant he made with Abraham, and his oath unto Isaac;
^10And confirmed the same unto Jacob for a law, and to Israel for an everlasting covenant:
^11Saying, Unto thee will I give the land of Canaan, the lot of your inheritance:
^12When they were but a few men in number; yea, very few, and strangers in it.
^13When they went from one nation to another, from one kingdom to another people;
^14He suffered no man to do them wrong: yea, he reproved kings for their sakes;
^15Saying, Touch not mine anointed, and do my prophets no harm.
^16Moreover he called for a famine upon the land: he brake the whole staff of bread.
^17He sent a man before them, even Joseph, who was sold for a servant:
^18Whose feet they hurt with fetters: he was laid in iron:
^19Until the time that his word came: the word of the Lord tried him.
^20The king sent and loosed him; even the ruler of the people, and let him go free.
^21He made him lord of his house, and ruler of all his substance:
^22To bind his princes at his pleasure; and teach his senators wisdom.
^23Israel also came into Egypt; and Jacob sojourned in the land of Ham.
^24And he increased his people greatly; and made them stronger than their enemies.
^25He turned their heart to hate his people, to deal subtilly with his servants.
^26He sent Moses his servant; and Aaron whom he had chosen.
^27They shewed his signs among them, and wonders in the land of Ham.
^28He sent darkness, and made it dark; and they rebelled not against his word.
^29He turned their waters into blood, and slew their fish.
^30Their land brought forth frogs in abundance, in the chambers of their kings.
^31He spake, and there came divers sorts of flies, and lice in all their coasts.
^32He gave them hail for rain, and flaming fire in their land.
^33He smote their vines also and their fig trees; and brake the trees of their coasts.
^34He spake, and the locusts came, and caterpillers, and that without number,
^35And did eat up all the herbs in their land, and devoured the fruit of their ground.
^36He smote also all the firstborn in their land, the chief of all their strength.
^37He brought them forth also with silver and gold: and there was not one feeble person among their tribes.
^38Egypt was glad when they departed: for the fear of them fell upon them.
^39He spread a cloud for a covering; and fire to give light in the night.
^40The people asked, and he brought quails, and satisfied them with the bread of heaven.
^41He opened the rock, and the waters gushed out; they ran in the dry places like a river.
^42For he remembered his holy promise, and Abraham his servant.
^43And he brought forth his people with joy, and his chosen with gladness:
^44And gave them the lands of the heathen: and they inherited the labour of the people;
^45That they might observe his statutes, and keep his laws. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 106

^1Praise ye the Lord. O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Who can utter the mighty acts of the Lord? who can shew forth all his praise?
^3Blessed are they that keep judgment, and he that doeth righteousness at all times.
^4Remember me, O Lord, with the favour that thou bearest unto thy people: O visit me with thy salvation;
^5That I may see the good of thy chosen, that I may rejoice in the gladness of thy nation, that I may glory with thine inheritance.
^6We have sinned with our fathers, we have committed iniquity, we have done wickedly.
^7Our fathers understood not thy wonders in Egypt; they remembered not the multitude of thy mercies; but provoked him at the sea, even at the Red sea.
^8Nevertheless he saved them for his name’s sake, that he might make his mighty power to be known.
^9He rebuked the Red sea also, and it was dried up: so he led them through the depths, as through the wilderness.
^10And he saved them from the hand of him that hated them, and redeemed them from the hand of the enemy.
^11And the waters covered their enemies: there was not one of them left.
^12Then believed they his words; they sang his praise.
^13They soon forgat his works; they waited not for his counsel:
^14But lusted exceedingly in the wilderness, and tempted God in the desert.
^15And he gave them their request; but sent leanness into their soul.
^16They envied Moses also in the camp, and Aaron the saint of the Lord.
^17The earth opened and swallowed up Dathan and covered the company of Abiram.
^18And a fire was kindled in their company; the flame burned up the wicked.
^19They made a calf in Horeb, and worshipped the molten image.
^20Thus they changed their glory into the similitude of an ox that eateth grass.
^21They forgat God their saviour, which had done great things in Egypt;
^22Wondrous works in the land of Ham, and terrible things by the Red sea.
^23Therefore he said that he would destroy them, had not Moses his chosen stood before him in the breach, to turn away his wrath, lest he should destroy them.
^24Yea, they despised the pleasant land, they believed not his word:
^25But murmured in their tents, and hearkened not unto the voice of the Lord.
^26Therefore he lifted up his hand against them, to overthrow them in the wilderness:
^27To overthrow their seed also among the nations, and to scatter them in the lands.
^28They joined themselves also unto Baalpeor, and ate the sacrifices of the dead.
^29Thus they provoked him to anger with their inventions: and the plague brake in upon them.
^30Then stood up Phinehas, and executed judgment: and so the plague was stayed.
^31And that was counted unto him for righteousness unto all generations for evermore.
^32They angered him also at the waters of strife, so that it went ill with Moses for their sakes:
^33Because they provoked his spirit, so that he spake unadvisedly with his lips.
^34They did not destroy the nations, concerning whom the Lord commanded them:
^35But were mingled among the heathen, and learned their works.
^36And they served their idols: which were a snare unto them.
^37Yea, they sacrificed their sons and their daughters unto devils,
^38And shed innocent blood, even the blood of their sons and of their daughters, whom they sacrificed unto the idols of Canaan: and the land was polluted with blood.
^39Thus were they defiled with their own works, and went a whoring with their own inventions.
^40Therefore was the wrath of the Lord kindled against his people, insomuch that he abhorred his own inheritance.
^41And he gave them into the hand of the heathen; and they that hated them ruled over them.
^42Their enemies also oppressed them, and they were brought into subjection under their hand.
^43Many times did he deliver them; but they provoked him with their counsel, and were brought low for their iniquity.
^44Nevertheless he regarded their affliction, when he heard their cry:
^45And he remembered for them his covenant, and repented according to the multitude of his mercies.
^46He made them also to be pitied of all those that carried them captives.
^47Save us, O Lord our God, and gather us from among the heathen, to give thanks unto thy holy name, and to triumph in thy praise.
^48Blessed be the Lord God of Israel from everlasting to everlasting: and let all the people say, Amen. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 107

^1O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Let the redeemed of the Lord say so, whom he hath redeemed from the hand of the enemy;
^3And gathered them out of the lands, from the east, and from the west, from the north, and from the south.
^4They wandered in the wilderness in a solitary way; they found no city to dwell in.
^5Hungry and thirsty, their soul fainted in them.
^6Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and he delivered them out of their distresses.
^7And he led them forth by the right way, that they might go to a city of habitation.
^8Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^9For he satisfieth the longing soul, and filleth the hungry soul with goodness.
^10Such as sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, being bound in affliction and iron;
^11Because they rebelled against the words of God, and contemned the counsel of the most High:
^12Therefore he brought down their heart with labour; they fell down, and there was none to help.
^13Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and he saved them out of their distresses.
^14He brought them out of darkness and the shadow of death, and brake their bands in sunder.
^15Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^16For he hath broken the gates of brass, and cut the bars of iron in sunder.
^17Fools because of their transgression, and because of their iniquities, are afflicted.
^18Their soul abhorreth all manner of meat; and they draw near unto the gates of death.
^19Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he saveth them out of their distresses.
^20He sent his word, and healed them, and delivered them from their destructions.
^21Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^22And let them sacrifice the sacrifices of thanksgiving, and declare his works with rejoicing.
^23They that go down to the sea in ships, that do business in great waters;
^24These see the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep.
^25For he commandeth, and raiseth the stormy wind, which lifteth up the waves thereof.
^26They mount up to the heaven, they go down again to the depths: their soul is melted because of trouble.
^27They reel to and fro, and stagger like a drunken man, and are at their wit’s end.
^28Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he bringeth them out of their distresses.
^29He maketh the storm a calm, so that the waves thereof are still.
^30Then are they glad because they be quiet; so he bringeth them unto their desired haven.
^31Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^32Let them exalt him also in the congregation of the people, and praise him in the assembly of the elders.
^33He turneth rivers into a wilderness, and the watersprings into dry ground;
^34A fruitful land into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell therein.
^35He turneth the wilderness into a standing water, and dry ground into watersprings.
^36And there he maketh the hungry to dwell, that they may prepare a city for habitation;
^37And sow the fields, and plant vineyards, which may yield fruits of increase.
^38He blesseth them also, so that they are multiplied greatly; and suffereth not their cattle to decrease.
^39Again, they are minished and brought low through oppression, affliction, and sorrow.
^40He poureth contempt upon princes, and causeth them to wander in the wilderness, where there is no way.
^41Yet setteth he the poor on high from affliction, and maketh him families like a flock.
^42The righteous shall see it, and rejoice: and all iniquity shall stop her mouth.
^43Whoso is wise, and will observe these things, even they shall understand the lovingkindness of the Lord.

Psalm 108

^1O god, my heart is fixed; I will sing and give praise, even with my glory.
^2Awake, psaltery and harp: I myself will awake early.
^3I will praise thee, O Lord, among the people: and I will sing praises unto thee among the nations.
^4For thy mercy is great above the heavens: and thy truth reacheth unto the clouds.
^5Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens: and thy glory above all the earth;
^6That thy beloved may be delivered: save with thy right hand, and answer me.
^7God hath spoken in his holiness; I will rejoice, I will divide Shechem, and mete out the valley of Succoth.
^8Gilead is mine; Manasseh is mine; Ephraim also is the strength of mine head; Judah is my lawgiver;
^9Moab is my washpot; over Edom will I cast out my shoe; over Philistia will I triumph.
^10Who will bring me into the strong city? who will lead me into Edom?
^11Wilt not thou, O God, who hast cast us off? and wilt not thou, O God, go forth with our hosts?
^12Give us help from trouble: for vain is the help of man.
^13Through God we shall do valiantly: for he it is that shall tread down our enemies.

Psalm 109

^1Hold not thy peace, O God of my praise;
^2For the mouth of the wicked and the mouth of the deceitful are opened against me: they have spoken against me with a lying tongue.
^3They compassed me about also with words of hatred; and fought against me without a cause.
^4For my love they are my adversaries: but I give myself unto prayer.
^5And they have rewarded me evil for good, and hatred for my love.
^6Set thou a wicked man over him: and let Satan stand at his right hand.
^7When he shall be judged, let him be condemned: and let his prayer become sin.
^8Let his days be few; and let another take his office.
^9Let his children be fatherless, and his wife a widow.
^10Let his children be continually vagabonds, and beg: let them seek their bread also out of their desolate places.
^11Let the extortioner catch all that he hath; and let the strangers spoil his labour.
^12Let there be none to extend mercy unto him: neither let there be any to favour his fatherless children.
^13Let his posterity be cut off; and in the generation following let their name be blotted out.
^14Let the iniquity of his fathers be remembered with the Lord; and let not the sin of his mother be blotted out.
^15Let them be before the Lord continually, that he may cut off the memory of them from the earth.
^16Because that he remembered not to shew mercy, but persecuted the poor and needy man, that he might even slay the broken in heart.
^17As he loved cursing, so let it come unto him: as he delighted not in blessing, so let it be far from him.
^18As he clothed himself with cursing like as with his garment, so let it come into his bowels like water, and like oil into his bones.
^19Let it be unto him as the garment which covereth him, and for a girdle wherewith he is girded continually.
^20Let this be the reward of mine adversaries from the Lord, and of them that speak evil against my soul.
^21But do thou for me, O God the Lord, for thy name’s sake: because thy mercy is good, deliver thou me.
^22For I am poor and needy, and my heart is wounded within me.
^23I am gone like the shadow when it declineth: I am tossed up and down as the locust.
^24My knees are weak through fasting; and my flesh faileth of fatness.
^25I became also a reproach unto them: when they looked upon me they shaked their heads.
^26Help me, O Lord my God: O save me according to thy mercy:
^27That they may know that this is thy hand; that thou, Lord, hast done it.
^28Let them curse, but bless thou: when they arise, let them be ashamed; but let thy servant rejoice.
^29Let mine adversaries be clothed with shame, and let them cover themselves with their own confusion, as with a mantle.
^30I will greatly praise the Lord with my mouth; yea, I will praise him among the multitude.
^31For he shall stand at the right hand of the poor, to save him from those that condemn his soul.

Psalm 110

^1The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footstool.
^2The Lord shall send the rod of thy strength out of Zion: rule thou in the midst of thine enemies.
^3Thy people shall be willing in the day of thy power, in the beauties of holiness from the womb of the morning: thou hast the dew of thy youth.
^4The Lord hath sworn, and will not repent, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchizedek.
^5The Lord at thy right hand shall strike through kings in the day of his wrath.
^6He shall judge among the heathen, he shall fill the places with the dead bodies; he shall wound the heads over many countries.
^7He shall drink of the brook in the way: therefore shall he lift up the head.

Psalm 111

^1Praise ye the Lord. I will praise the Lord with my whole heart, in the assembly of the upright, and in the congregation.
^2The works of the Lord are great, sought out of all them that have pleasure therein.
^3His work is honourable and glorious: and his righteousness endureth for ever.
^4He hath made his wonderful works to be remembered: the Lord is gracious and full of compassion.
^5He hath given meat unto them that fear him: he will ever be mindful of his covenant.
^6He hath shewed his people the power of his works, that he may give them the heritage of the heathen.
^7The works of his hands are verity and judgment; all his commandments are sure.
^8They stand fast for ever and ever, and are done in truth and uprightness.
^9He sent redemption unto his people: he hath commanded his covenant for ever: holy and reverend is his name.
^10The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom: a good understanding have all they that do his commandments: his praise endureth for ever.

Psalm 112

^1Praise ye the Lord. Blessed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his commandments.
^2His seed shall be mighty upon earth: the generation of the upright shall be blessed.
^3Wealth and riches shall be in his house: and his righteousness endureth for ever.
^4Unto the upright there ariseth light in the darkness: he is gracious, and full of compassion, and righteous.
^5A good man sheweth favour, and lendeth: he will guide his affairs with discretion.
^6Surely he shall not be moved for ever: the righteous shall be in everlasting remembrance.
^7He shall not be afraid of evil tidings: his heart is fixed, trusting in the Lord.
^8His heart is established, he shall not be afraid, until he see his desire upon his enemies.
^9He hath dispersed, he hath given to the poor; his righteousness endureth for ever; his horn shall be exalted with honour.
^10The wicked shall see it, and be grieved; he shall gnash with his teeth, and melt away: the desire of the wicked shall perish.

Psalm 113

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise, O ye servants of the Lord, praise the name of the Lord.
^2Blessed be the name of the Lord from this time forth and for evermore.
^3From the rising of the sun unto the going down of the same the Lord’s name is to be praised.
^4The Lord is high above all nations, and his glory above the heavens.
^5Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwelleth on high,
^6Who humbleth himself to behold the things that are in heaven, and in the earth!
^7He raiseth up the poor out of the dust, and lifteth the needy out of the dunghill;
^8That he may set him with princes, even with the princes of his people.
^9He maketh the barren woman to keep house, and to be a joyful mother of children. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 114

^1When Israel went out of Egypt, the house of Jacob from a people of strange language;
^2Judah was his sanctuary, and Israel his dominion.
^3The sea saw it, and fled: Jordan was driven back.
^4The mountains skipped like rams, and the little hills like lambs.
^5What ailed thee, O thou sea, that thou fleddest? thou Jordan, that thou wast driven back?
^6Ye mountains, that ye skipped like rams; and ye little hills, like lambs?
^7Tremble, thou earth, at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the God of Jacob;
^8Which turned the rock into a standing water, the flint into a fountain of waters.

Psalm 115

^1Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name give glory, for thy mercy, and for thy truth’s sake.
^2Wherefore should the heathen say, Where is now their God?
^3But our God is in the heavens: he hath done whatsoever he hath pleased.
^4Their idols are silver and gold, the work of men’s hands.
^5They have mouths, but they speak not: eyes have they, but they see not:
^6They have ears, but they hear not: noses have they, but they smell not:
^7They have hands, but they handle not: feet have they, but they walk not: neither speak they through their throat.
^8They that make them are like unto them; so is every one that trusteth in them.
^9O Israel, trust thou in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^10O house of Aaron, trust in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^11Ye that fear the Lord, trust in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^12The Lord hath been mindful of us: he will bless us; he will bless the house of Israel; he will bless the house of Aaron.
^13He will bless them that fear the Lord, both small and great.
^14The Lord shall increase you more and more, you and your children.
^15Ye are blessed of the Lord which made heaven and earth.
^16The heaven, even the heavens, are the Lord’s: but the earth hath he given to the children of men.
^17The dead praise not the Lord, neither any that go down into silence.
^18But we will bless the Lord from this time forth and for evermore. Praise the Lord.

Psalm 116

^1I love the Lord, because he hath heard my voice and my supplications.
^2Because he hath inclined his ear unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live.
^3The sorrows of death compassed me, and the pains of hell gat hold upon me: I found trouble and sorrow.
^4Then called I upon the name of the Lord; O Lord, I beseech thee, deliver my soul.
^5Gracious is the Lord, and righteous; yea, our God is merciful.
^6The Lord preserveth the simple: I was brought low, and he helped me.
^7Return unto thy rest, O my soul; for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.
^8For thou hast delivered my soul from death, mine eyes from tears, and my feet from falling.
^9I will walk before the Lord in the land of the living.
^10I believed, therefore have I spoken: I was greatly afflicted:
^11I said in my haste, All men are liars.
^12What shall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits toward me?
^13I will take the cup of salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord.
^14I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all his people.
^15Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his saints.
^16O Lord, truly I am thy servant; I am thy servant, and the son of thine handmaid: thou hast loosed my bonds.
^17I will offer to thee the sacrifice of thanksgiving, and will call upon the name of the Lord.
^18I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all his people.
^19In the courts of the Lord’s house, in the midst of thee, O Jerusalem. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 117

^1O praise the Lord, all ye nations: praise him, all ye people.
^2For his merciful kindness is great toward us: and the truth of the Lord endureth for ever. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 118

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: because his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Let Israel now say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^3Let the house of Aaron now say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^4Let them now that fear the Lord say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^5I called upon the Lord in distress: the Lord answered me, and set me in a large place.
^6The Lord is on my side; I will not fear: what can man do unto me?
^7The Lord taketh my part with them that help me: therefore shall I see my desire upon them that hate me.
^8It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in man.
^9It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in princes.
^10All nations compassed me about: but in the name of the Lord will I destroy them.
^11They compassed me about; yea, they compassed me about: but in the name of the Lord I will destroy them.
^12They compassed me about like bees: they are quenched as the fire of thorns: for in the name of the Lord I will destroy them.
^13Thou hast thrust sore at me that I might fall: but the Lord helped me.
^14The Lord is my strength and song, and is become my salvation.
^15The voice of rejoicing and salvation is in the tabernacles of the righteous: the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
^16The right hand of the Lord is exalted: the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
^17I shall not die, but live, and declare the works of the Lord.
^18The Lord hath chastened me sore: but he hath not given me over unto death.
^19Open to me the gates of righteousness: I will go into them, and I will praise the Lord:
^20This gate of the Lord, into which the righteous shall enter.
^21I will praise thee: for thou hast heard me, and art become my salvation.
^22The stone which the builders refused is become the head stone of the corner.
^23This is the Lord’s doing; it is marvellous in our eyes.
^24This is the day which the Lord hath made; we will rejoice and be glad in it.
^25Save now, I beseech thee, O Lord: O Lord, I beseech thee, send now prosperity.
^26Blessed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord: we have blessed you out of the house of the Lord.
^27God is the Lord, which hath shewed us light: bind the sacrifice with cords, even unto the horns of the altar.
^28Thou art my God, and I will praise thee: thou art my God, I will exalt thee.
^29O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.

Psalm 119

^1Blessed are the undefiled in the way, who walk in the law of the Lord.
^2Blessed are they that keep his testimonies, and that seek him with the whole heart.
^3They also do no iniquity: they walk in his ways.
^4Thou hast commanded us to keep thy precepts diligently.
^5O that my ways were directed to keep thy statutes!
^6Then shall I not be ashamed, when I have respect unto all thy commandments.
^7I will praise thee with uprightness of heart, when I shall have learned thy righteous judgments.
^8I will keep thy statutes: O forsake me not utterly.
^9Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way? by taking heed thereto according to thy word.
^10With my whole heart have I sought thee: O let me not wander from thy commandments.
^11Thy word have I hid in mine heart, that I might not sin against thee.
^12Blessed art thou, O Lord: teach me thy statutes.
^13With my lips have I declared all the judgments of thy mouth.
^14I have rejoiced in the way of thy testimonies, as much as in all riches.
^15I will meditate in thy precepts, and have respect unto thy ways.
^16I will delight myself in thy statutes: I will not forget thy word.
^17Deal bountifully with thy servant, that I may live, and keep thy word.
^18Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.
^19I am a stranger in the earth: hide not thy commandments from me.
^20My soul breaketh for the longing that it hath unto thy judgments at all times.
^21Thou hast rebuked the proud that are cursed, which do err from thy commandments.
^22Remove from me reproach and contempt; for I have kept thy testimonies.
^23Princes also did sit and speak against me: but thy servant did meditate in thy statutes.
^24Thy testimonies also are my delight and my counsellors.
^25My soul cleaveth unto the dust: quicken thou me according to thy word.
^26I have declared my ways, and thou heardest me: teach me thy statutes.
^27Make me to understand the way of thy precepts: so shall I talk of thy wondrous works.
^28My soul melteth for heaviness: strengthen thou me according unto thy word.
^29Remove from me the way of lying: and grant me thy law graciously.
^30I have chosen the way of truth: thy judgments have I laid before me.
^31I have stuck unto thy testimonies: O Lord, put me not to shame.
^32I will run the way of thy commandments, when thou shalt enlarge my heart.
^33Teach me, O Lord, the way of thy statutes; and I shall keep it unto the end.
^34Give me understanding, and I shall keep thy law; yea, I shall observe it with my whole heart.
^35Make me to go in the path of thy commandments; for therein do I delight.
^36Incline my heart unto thy testimonies, and not to covetousness.
^37Turn away mine eyes from beholding vanity; and quicken thou me in thy way.
^38Stablish thy word unto thy servant, who is devoted to thy fear.
^39Turn away my reproach which I fear: for thy judgments are good.
^40Behold, I have longed after thy precepts: quicken me in thy righteousness.
^41Let thy mercies come also unto me, O Lord, even thy salvation, according to thy word.
^42So shall I have wherewith to answer him that reproacheth me: for I trust in thy word.
^43And take not the word of truth utterly out of my mouth; for I have hoped in thy judgments.
^44So shall I keep thy law continually for ever and ever.
^45And I will walk at liberty: for I seek thy precepts.
^46I will speak of thy testimonies also before kings, and will not be ashamed.
^47And I will delight myself in thy commandments, which I have loved.
^48My hands also will I lift up unto thy commandments, which I have loved; and I will meditate in thy statutes.
^49Remember the word unto thy servant, upon which thou hast caused me to hope.
^50This is my comfort in my affliction: for thy word hath quickened me.
^51The proud have had me greatly in derision: yet have I not declined from thy law.
^52I remembered thy judgments of old, O Lord; and have comforted myself.
^53Horror hath taken hold upon me because of the wicked that forsake thy law.
^54Thy statutes have been my songs in the house of my pilgrimage.
^55I have remembered thy name, O Lord, in the night, and have kept thy law.
^56This I had, because I kept thy precepts.
^57Thou art my portion, O Lord: I have said that I would keep thy words.
^58I intreated thy favour with my whole heart: be merciful unto me according to thy word.
^59I thought on my ways, and turned my feet unto thy testimonies.
^60I made haste, and delayed not to keep thy commandments.
^61The bands of the wicked have robbed me: but I have not forgotten thy law.
^62At midnight I will rise to give thanks unto thee because of thy righteous judgments.
^63I am a companion of all them that fear thee, and of them that keep thy precepts.
^64The earth, O Lord, is full of thy mercy: teach me thy statutes.
^65Thou hast dealt well with thy servant, O Lord, according unto thy word.
^66Teach me good judgment and knowledge: for I have believed thy commandments.
^67Before I was afflicted I went astray: but now have I kept thy word.
^68Thou art good, and doest good; teach me thy statutes.
^69The proud have forged a lie against me: but I will keep thy precepts with my whole heart.
^70Their heart is as fat as grease; but I delight in thy law.
^71It is good for me that I have been afflicted; that I might learn thy statutes.
^72The law of thy mouth is better unto me than thousands of gold and silver.
^73Thy hands have made me and fashioned me: give me understanding, that I may learn thy commandments.
^74They that fear thee will be glad when they see me; because I have hoped in thy word.
^75I know, O Lord, that thy judgments are right, and that thou in faithfulness hast afflicted me.
^76Let, I pray thee, thy merciful kindness be for my comfort, according to thy word unto thy servant.
^77Let thy tender mercies come unto me, that I may live: for thy law is my delight.
^78Let the proud be ashamed; for they dealt perversely with me without a cause: but I will meditate in thy precepts.
^79Let those that fear thee turn unto me, and those that have known thy testimonies.
^80Let my heart be sound in thy statutes; that I be not ashamed.
^81My soul fainteth for thy salvation: but I hope in thy word.
^82Mine eyes fail for thy word, saying, When wilt thou comfort me?
^83For I am become like a bottle in the smoke; yet do I not forget thy statutes.
^84How many are the days of thy servant? when wilt thou execute judgment on them that persecute me?
^85The proud have digged pits for me, which are not after thy law.
^86All thy commandments are faithful: they persecute me wrongfully; help thou me.
^87They had almost consumed me upon earth; but I forsook not thy precepts.
^88Quicken me after thy lovingkindness; so shall I keep the testimony of thy mouth.
^89For ever, O Lord, thy word is settled in heaven.
^90Thy faithfulness is unto all generations: thou hast established the earth, and it abideth.
^91They continue this day according to thine ordinances: for all are thy servants.
^92Unless thy law had been my delights, I should then have perished in mine affliction.
^93I will never forget thy precepts: for with them thou hast quickened me.
^94I am thine, save me: for I have sought thy precepts.
^95The wicked have waited for me to destroy me: but I will consider thy testimonies.
^96I have seen an end of all perfection: but thy commandment is exceeding broad.
^97O how I love thy law! it is my meditation all the day.
^98Thou through thy commandments hast made me wiser than mine enemies: for they are ever with me.
^99I have more understanding than all my teachers: for thy testimonies are my meditation.
^100I understand more than the ancients, because I keep thy precepts.
^101I have refrained my feet from every evil way, that I might keep thy word.
^102I have not departed from thy judgments: for thou hast taught me.
^103How sweet are thy words unto my taste! yea, sweeter than honey to my mouth!
^104Through thy precepts I get understanding: therefore I hate every false way.
^105Thy word is a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path.
^106I have sworn, and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous judgments.
^107I am afflicted very much: quicken me, O Lord, according unto thy word.
^108Accept, I beseech thee, the freewill offerings of my mouth, O Lord, and teach me thy judgments.
^109My soul is continually in my hand: yet do I not forget thy law.
^110The wicked have laid a snare for me: yet I erred not from thy precepts.
^111Thy testimonies have I taken as an heritage for ever: for they are the rejoicing of my heart.
^112I have inclined mine heart to perform thy statutes alway, even unto the end.
^113I hate vain thoughts: but thy law do I love.
^114Thou art my hiding place and my shield: I hope in thy word.
^115Depart from me, ye evildoers: for I will keep the commandments of my God.
^116Uphold me according unto thy word, that I may live: and let me not be ashamed of my hope.
^117Hold thou me up, and I shall be safe: and I will have respect unto thy statutes continually.
^118Thou hast trodden down all them that err from thy statutes: for their deceit is falsehood.
^119Thou puttest away all the wicked of the earth like dross: therefore I love thy testimonies.
^120My flesh trembleth for fear of thee; and I am afraid of thy judgments.
^121I have done judgment and justice: leave me not to mine oppressors.
^122Be surety for thy servant for good: let not the proud oppress me.
^123Mine eyes fail for thy salvation, and for the word of thy righteousness.
^124Deal with thy servant according unto thy mercy, and teach me thy statutes.
^125I am thy servant; give me understanding, that I may know thy testimonies.
^126It is time for thee, Lord, to work: for they have made void thy law.
^127Therefore I love thy commandments above gold; yea, above fine gold.
^128Therefore I esteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right; and I hate every false way.
^129Thy testimonies are wonderful: therefore doth my soul keep them.
^130The entrance of thy words giveth light; it giveth understanding unto the simple.
^131I opened my mouth, and panted: for I longed for thy commandments.
^132Look thou upon me, and be merciful unto me, as thou usest to do unto those that love thy name.
^133Order my steps in thy word: and let not any iniquity have dominion over me.
^134Deliver me from the oppression of man: so will I keep thy precepts.
^135Make thy face to shine upon thy servant; and teach me thy statutes.
^136Rivers of waters run down mine eyes, because they keep not thy law.
^137Righteous art thou, O Lord, and upright are thy judgments.
^138Thy testimonies that thou hast commanded are righteous and very faithful.
^139My zeal hath consumed me, because mine enemies have forgotten thy words.
^140Thy word is very pure: therefore thy servant loveth it.
^141I am small and despised: yet do not I forget thy precepts.
^142Thy righteousness is an everlasting righteousness, and thy law is the truth.
^143Trouble and anguish have taken hold on me: yet thy commandments are my delights.
^144The righteousness of thy testimonies is everlasting: give me understanding, and I shall live.
^145I cried with my whole heart; hear me, O Lord: I will keep thy statutes.
^146I cried unto thee; save me, and I shall keep thy testimonies.
^147I prevented the dawning of the morning, and cried: I hoped in thy word.
^148Mine eyes prevent the night watches, that I might meditate in thy word.
^149Hear my voice according unto thy lovingkindness: O Lord, quicken me according to thy judgment.
^150They draw nigh that follow after mischief: they are far from thy law.
^151Thou art near, O Lord; and all thy commandments are truth.
^152Concerning thy testimonies, I have known of old that thou hast founded them for ever.
^153Consider mine affliction, and deliver me: for I do not forget thy law.
^154Plead my cause, and deliver me: quicken me according to thy word.
^155Salvation is far from the wicked: for they seek not thy statutes.
^156Great are thy tender mercies, O Lord: quicken me according to thy judgments.
^157Many are my persecutors and mine enemies; yet do I not decline from thy testimonies.
^158I beheld the transgressors, and was grieved; because they kept not thy word.
^159Consider how I love thy precepts: quicken me, O Lord, according to thy lovingkindness.
^160Thy word is true from the beginning: and every one of thy righteous judgments endureth for ever.
^161Princes have persecuted me without a cause: but my heart standeth in awe of thy word.
^162I rejoice at thy word, as one that findeth great spoil.
^163I hate and abhor lying: but thy law do I love.
^164Seven times a day do I praise thee because of thy righteous judgments.
^165Great peace have they which love thy law: and nothing shall offend them.
^166Lord, I have hoped for thy salvation, and done thy commandments.
^167My soul hath kept thy testimonies; and I love them exceedingly.
^168I have kept thy precepts and thy testimonies: for all my ways are before thee.
^169Let my cry come near before thee, O Lord: give me understanding according to thy word.
^170Let my supplication come before thee: deliver me according to thy word.
^171My lips shall utter praise, when thou hast taught me thy statutes.
^172My tongue shall speak of thy word: for all thy commandments are righteousness.
^173Let thine hand help me; for I have chosen thy precepts.
^174I have longed for thy salvation, O Lord; and thy law is my delight.
^175Let my soul live, and it shall praise thee; and let thy judgments help me.
^176I have gone astray like a lost sheep; seek thy servant; for I do not forget thy commandments.

Psalm 120

^1In my distress I cried unto the Lord, and he heard me.
^2Deliver my soul, O Lord, from lying lips, and from a deceitful tongue.
^3What shall be given unto thee? or what shall be done unto thee, thou false tongue?
^4Sharp arrows of the mighty, with coals of juniper.
^5Woe is me, that I sojourn in Mesech, that I dwell in the tents of Kedar!
^6My soul hath long dwelt with him that hateth peace.
^7I am for peace: but when I speak, they are for war.

Psalm 121

^1I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills, from whence cometh my help.
^2My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
^3He will not suffer thy foot to be moved: he that keepeth thee will not slumber.
^4Behold, he that keepeth Israel shall neither slumber nor sleep.
^5The Lord is thy keeper: the Lord is thy shade upon thy right hand.
^6The sun shall not smite thee by day, nor the moon by night.
^7The Lord shall preserve thee from all evil: he shall preserve thy soul.
^8The Lord shall preserve thy going out and thy coming in from this time forth, and even for evermore.

Psalm 122

^1I was glad when they said unto me, Let us go into the house of the Lord.
^2Our feet shall stand within thy gates, O Jerusalem.
^3Jerusalem is builded as a city that is compact together:
^4Whither the tribes go up, the tribes of the Lord, unto the testimony of Israel, to give thanks unto the name of the Lord.
^5For there are set thrones of judgment, the thrones of the house of David.
^6Pray for the peace of Jerusalem: they shall prosper that love thee.
^7Peace be within thy walls, and prosperity within thy palaces.
^8For my brethren and companions’ sakes, I will now say, Peace be within thee.
^9Because of the house of the Lord our God I will seek thy good.

Psalm 123

^1Unto thee lift I up mine eyes, O thou that dwellest in the heavens.
^2Behold, as the eyes of servants look unto the hand of their masters, and as the eyes of a maiden unto the hand of her mistress; so our eyes wait upon the Lord our God, until that he have mercy upon us.
^3Have mercy upon us, O Lord, have mercy upon us: for we are exceedingly filled with contempt.
^4Our soul is exceedingly filled with the scorning of those that are at ease, and with the contempt of the proud.

Psalm 124

^1If it had not been the Lord who was on our side, now may Israel say;
^2If it had not been the Lord who was on our side, when men rose up against us:
^3Then they had swallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled against us:
^4Then the waters had overwhelmed us, the stream had gone over our soul:
^5Then the proud waters had gone over our soul.
^6Blessed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a prey to their teeth.
^7Our soul is escaped as a bird out of the snare of the fowlers: the snare is broken, and we are escaped.
^8Our help is in the name of the Lord, who made heaven and earth.

Psalm 125

^1They that trust in the Lord shall be as mount Zion, which cannot be removed, but abideth for ever.
^2As the mountains are round about Jerusalem, so the Lord is round about his people from henceforth even for ever.
^3For the rod of the wicked shall not rest upon the lot of the righteous; lest the righteous put forth their hands unto iniquity.
^4Do good, O Lord, unto those that be good, and to them that are upright in their hearts.
^5As for such as turn aside unto their crooked ways, the Lord shall lead them forth with the workers of iniquity: but peace shall be upon Israel.

Psalm 126

^1When the Lord turned again the captivity of Zion, we were like them that dream.
^2Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with singing: then said they among the heathen, The Lord hath done great things for them.
^3The Lord hath done great things for us; whereof we are glad.
^4Turn again our captivity, O Lord, as the streams in the south.
^5They that sow in tears shall reap in joy.
^6He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious seed, shall doubtless come again with rejoicing, bringing his sheaves with him.

Psalm 127

^1Except the Lord build the house, they labour in vain that build it: except the Lord keep the city, the watchman waketh but in vain.
^2It is vain for you to rise up early, to sit up late, to eat the bread of sorrows: for so he giveth his beloved sleep.
^3Lo, children are an heritage of the Lord: and the fruit of the womb is his reward.
^4As arrows are in the hand of a mighty man; so are children of the youth.
^5Happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them: they shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the enemies in the gate.

Psalm 128

^1Blessed is every one that feareth the Lord; that walketh in his ways.
^2For thou shalt eat the labour of thine hands: happy shalt thou be, and it shall be well with thee.
^3Thy wife shall be as a fruitful vine by the sides of thine house: thy children like olive plants round about thy table.
^4Behold, that thus shall the man be blessed that feareth the Lord.
^5The Lord shall bless thee out of Zion: and thou shalt see the good of Jerusalem all the days of thy life.
^6Yea, thou shalt see thy children’s children, and peace upon Israel.

Psalm 129

^1Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth, may Israel now say:
^2Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth: yet they have not prevailed against me.
^3The plowers plowed upon my back: they made long their furrows.
^4The Lord is righteous: he hath cut asunder the cords of the wicked.
^5Let them all be confounded and turned back that hate Zion.
^6Let them be as the grass upon the housetops, which withereth afore it groweth up:
^7Wherewith the mower filleth not his hand; nor he that bindeth sheaves his bosom.
^8Neither do they which go by say, The blessing of the Lord be upon you: we bless you in the name of the Lord.

Psalm 130

^1Out of the depths have I cried unto thee, O Lord.
^2Lord, hear my voice: let thine ears be attentive to the voice of my supplications.
^3If thou, Lord, shouldest mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand?
^4But there is forgiveness with thee, that thou mayest be feared.
^5I wait for the Lord, my soul doth wait, and in his word do I hope.
^6My soul waiteth for the Lord more than they that watch for the morning: I say, more than they that watch for the morning.
^7Let Israel hope in the Lord: for with the Lord there is mercy, and with him is plenteous redemption.
^8And he shall redeem Israel from all his iniquities.

Psalm 131

^1Lord, my heart is not haughty, nor mine eyes lofty: neither do I exercise myself in great matters, or in things too high for me.
^2Surely I have behaved and quieted myself, as a child that is weaned of his mother: my soul is even as a weaned child.
^3Let Israel hope in the Lord from henceforth and for ever.

Psalm 132

^1Lord, remember David, and all his afflictions:
^2How he sware unto the Lord, and vowed unto the mighty God of Jacob;
^3Surely I will not come into the tabernacle of my house, nor go up into my bed;
^4I will not give sleep to mine eyes, or slumber to mine eyelids,
^5Until I find out a place for the Lord, an habitation for the mighty God of Jacob.
^6Lo, we heard of it at Ephratah: we found it in the fields of the wood.
^7We will go into his tabernacles: we will worship at his footstool.
^8Arise, O Lord, into thy rest; thou, and the ark of thy strength.
^9Let thy priests be clothed with righteousness; and let thy saints shout for joy.
^10For thy servant David’s sake turn not away the face of thine anointed.
^11The Lord hath sworn in truth unto David; he will not turn from it; Of the fruit of thy body will I set upon thy throne.
^12If thy children will keep my covenant and my testimony that I shall teach them, their children shall also sit upon thy throne for evermore.
^13For the Lord hath chosen Zion; he hath desired it for his habitation.
^14This is my rest for ever: here will I dwell; for I have desired it.
^15I will abundantly bless her provision: I will satisfy her poor with bread.
^16I will also clothe her priests with salvation: and her saints shall shout aloud for joy.
^17There will I make the horn of David to bud: I have ordained a lamp for mine anointed.
^18His enemies will I clothe with shame: but upon himself shall his crown flourish.

Psalm 133

^1Behold, how good and how pleasant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity!
^2It is like the precious ointment upon the head, that ran down upon the beard, even Aaron’s beard: that went down to the skirts of his garments;
^3As the dew of Hermon, and as the dew that descended upon the mountains of Zion: for there the Lord commanded the blessing, even life for evermore.

Psalm 134

^1Behold, bless ye the Lord, all ye servants of the Lord, which by night stand in the house of the Lord.
^2Lift up your hands in the sanctuary, and bless the Lord.
^3The Lord that made heaven and earth bless thee out of Zion.

Psalm 135

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise ye the name of the Lord; praise him, O ye servants of the Lord.
^2Ye that stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God.
^3Praise the Lord; for the Lord is good: sing praises unto his name; for it is pleasant.
^4For the Lord hath chosen Jacob unto himself, and Israel for his peculiar treasure.
^5For I know that the Lord is great, and that our Lord is above all gods.
^6Whatsoever the Lord pleased, that did he in heaven, and in earth, in the seas, and all deep places.
^7He causeth the vapours to ascend from the ends of the earth; he maketh lightnings for the rain; he bringeth the wind out of his treasuries.
^8Who smote the firstborn of Egypt, both of man and beast.
^9Who sent tokens and wonders into the midst of thee, O Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his servants.
^10Who smote great nations, and slew mighty kings;
^11Sihon king of the Amorites, and Og king of Bashan, and all the kingdoms of Canaan:
^12And gave their land for an heritage, an heritage unto Israel his people.
^13Thy name, O Lord, endureth for ever; and thy memorial, O Lord, throughout all generations.
^14For the Lord will judge his people, and he will repent himself concerning his servants.
^15The idols of the heathen are silver and gold, the work of men’s hands.
^16They have mouths, but they speak not; eyes have they, but they see not;
^17They have ears, but they hear not; neither is there any breath in their mouths.
^18They that make them are like unto them: so is every one that trusteth in them.
^19Bless the Lord, O house of Israel: bless the Lord, O house of Aaron:
^20Bless the Lord, O house of Levi: ye that fear the Lord, bless the Lord.
^21Blessed be the Lord out of Zion, which dwelleth at Jerusalem. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 136

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2O give thanks unto the God of gods: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^3O give thanks to the Lord of lords: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^4To him who alone doeth great wonders: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^5To him that by wisdom made the heavens: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^6To him that stretched out the earth above the waters: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^7To him that made great lights: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^8The sun to rule by day: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^9The moon and stars to rule by night: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^10To him that smote Egypt in their firstborn: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^11And brought out Israel from among them: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^12With a strong hand, and with a stretched out arm: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^13To him which divided the Red sea into parts: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^14And made Israel to pass through the midst of it: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^15But overthrew Pharaoh and his host in the Red sea: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^16To him which led his people through the wilderness: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^17To him which smote great kings: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^18And slew famous kings: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^19Sihon king of the Amorites: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^20And Og the king of Bashan: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^21And gave their land for an heritage: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^22Even an heritage unto Israel his servant: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^23Who remembered us in our low estate: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^24And hath redeemed us from our enemies: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^25Who giveth food to all flesh: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^26O give thanks unto the God of heaven: for his mercy endureth for ever.

Psalm 137

^1By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down, yea, we wept, when we remembered Zion.
^2We hanged our harps upon the willows in the midst thereof.
^3For there they that carried us away captive required of us a song; and they that wasted us required of us mirth, saying, Sing us one of the songs of Zion.
^4How shall we sing the Lord’s song in a strange land?
^5If I forget thee, O Jerusalem, let my right hand forget her cunning.
^6If I do not remember thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth; if I prefer not Jerusalem above my chief joy.
^7Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem; who said, Rase it, rase it, even to the foundation thereof.
^8O daughter of Babylon, who art to be destroyed; happy shall he be, that rewardeth thee as thou hast served us.
^9Happy shall he be, that taketh and dasheth thy little ones against the stones.

Psalm 138

^1I will praise thee with my whole heart: before the gods will I sing praise unto thee.
^2I will worship toward thy holy temple, and praise thy name for thy lovingkindness and for thy truth: for thou hast magnified thy word above all thy name.
^3In the day when I cried thou answeredst me, and strengthenedst me with strength in my soul.
^4All the kings of the earth shall praise thee, O Lord, when they hear the words of thy mouth.
^5Yea, they shall sing in the ways of the Lord: for great is the glory of the Lord.
^6Though the Lord be high, yet hath he respect unto the lowly: but the proud he knoweth afar off.
^7Though I walk in the midst of trouble, thou wilt revive me: thou shalt stretch forth thine hand against the wrath of mine enemies, and thy right hand shall save me.
^8The Lord will perfect that which concerneth me: thy mercy, O Lord, endureth for ever: forsake not the works of thine own hands.

Psalm 139

^1O lord, thou hast searched me, and known me.
^2Thou knowest my downsitting and mine uprising, thou understandest my thought afar off.
^3Thou compassest my path and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways.
^4For there is not a word in my tongue, but, lo, O Lord, thou knowest it altogether.
^5Thou hast beset me behind and before, and laid thine hand upon me.
^6Such knowledge is too wonderful for me; it is high, I cannot attain unto it.
^7Whither shall I go from thy spirit? or whither shall I flee from thy presence?
^8If I ascend up into heaven, thou art there: if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou art there.
^9If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea;
^10Even there shall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand shall hold me.
^11If I say, Surely the darkness shall cover me; even the night shall be light about me.
^12Yea, the darkness hideth not from thee; but the night shineth as the day: the darkness and the light are both alike to thee.
^13For thou hast possessed my reins: thou hast covered me in my mother’s womb.
^14I will praise thee; for I am fearfully and wonderfully made: marvellous are thy works; and that my soul knoweth right well.
^15My substance was not hid from thee, when I was made in secret, and curiously wrought in the lowest parts of the earth.
^16Thine eyes did see my substance, yet being unperfect; and in thy book all my members were written, which in continuance were fashioned, when as yet there was none of them.
^17How precious also are thy thoughts unto me, O God! how great is the sum of them!
^18If I should count them, they are more in number than the sand: when I awake, I am still with thee.
^19Surely thou wilt slay the wicked, O God: depart from me therefore, ye bloody men.
^20For they speak against thee wickedly, and thine enemies take thy name in vain.
^21Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? and am not I grieved with those that rise up against thee?
^22I hate them with perfect hatred: I count them mine enemies.
^23Search me, O God, and know my heart: try me, and know my thoughts:
^24And see if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting.

Psalm 140

^1Deliver me, O Lord, from the evil man: preserve me from the violent man;
^2Which imagine mischiefs in their heart; continually are they gathered together for war.
^3They have sharpened their tongues like a serpent; adders’ poison is under their lips. Selah.
^4Keep me, O Lord, from the hands of the wicked; preserve me from the violent man; who have purposed to overthrow my goings.
^5The proud have hid a snare for me, and cords; they have spread a net by the wayside; they have set gins for me. Selah.
^6I said unto the Lord, Thou art my God: hear the voice of my supplications, O Lord.
^7O God the Lord, the strength of my salvation, thou hast covered my head in the day of battle.
^8Grant not, O Lord, the desires of the wicked: further not his wicked device; lest they exalt themselves. Selah.
^9As for the head of those that compass me about, let the mischief of their own lips cover them.
^10Let burning coals fall upon them: let them be cast into the fire; into deep pits, that they rise not up again.
^11Let not an evil speaker be established in the earth: evil shall hunt the violent man to overthrow him.
^12I know that the Lord will maintain the cause of the afflicted, and the right of the poor.
^13Surely the righteous shall give thanks unto thy name: the upright shall dwell in thy presence.

Psalm 141

^1Lord, I cry unto thee: make haste unto me; give ear unto my voice, when I cry unto thee.
^2Let my prayer be set forth before thee as incense; and the lifting up of my hands as the evening sacrifice.
^3Set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth; keep the door of my lips.
^4Incline not my heart to any evil thing, to practise wicked works with men that work iniquity: and let me not eat of their dainties.
^5Let the righteous smite me; it shall be a kindness: and let him reprove me; it shall be an excellent oil, which shall not break my head: for yet my prayer also shall be in their calamities.
^6When their judges are overthrown in stony places, they shall hear my words; for they are sweet.
^7Our bones are scattered at the grave’s mouth, as when one cutteth and cleaveth wood upon the earth.
^8But mine eyes are unto thee, O God the Lord: in thee is my trust; leave not my soul destitute.
^9Keep me from the snares which they have laid for me, and the gins of the workers of iniquity.
^10Let the wicked fall into their own nets, whilst that I withal escape.

Psalm 142

^1I cried unto the Lord with my voice; with my voice unto the Lord did I make my supplication.
^2I poured out my complaint before him; I shewed before him my trouble.
^3When my spirit was overwhelmed within me, then thou knewest my path. In the way wherein I walked have they privily laid a snare for me.
^4I looked on my right hand, and beheld, but there was no man that would know me: refuge failed me; no man cared for my soul.
^5I cried unto thee, O Lord: I said, Thou art my refuge and my portion in the land of the living.
^6Attend unto my cry; for I am brought very low: deliver me from my persecutors; for they are stronger than I.
^7Bring my soul out of prison, that I may praise thy name: the righteous shall compass me about; for thou shalt deal bountifully with me.

Psalm 143

^1Hear my prayer, O Lord, give ear to my supplications: in thy faithfulness answer me, and in thy righteousness.
^2And enter not into judgment with thy servant: for in thy sight shall no man living be justified.
^3For the enemy hath persecuted my soul; he hath smitten my life down to the ground; he hath made me to dwell in darkness, as those that have been long dead.
^4Therefore is my spirit overwhelmed within me; my heart within me is desolate.
^5I remember the days of old; I meditate on all thy works; I muse on the work of thy hands.
^6I stretch forth my hands unto thee: my soul thirsteth after thee, as a thirsty land. Selah.
^7Hear me speedily, O Lord: my spirit faileth: hide not thy face from me, lest I be like unto them that go down into the pit.
^8Cause me to hear thy lovingkindness in the morning; for in thee do I trust: cause me to know the way wherein I should walk; for I lift up my soul unto thee.
^9Deliver me, O Lord, from mine enemies: I flee unto thee to hide me.
^10Teach me to do thy will; for thou art my God: thy spirit is good; lead me into the land of uprightness.
^11Quicken me, O Lord, for thy name’s sake: for thy righteousness’ sake bring my soul out of trouble.
^12And of thy mercy cut off mine enemies, and destroy all them that afflict my soul: for I am thy servant.

Psalm 144

^1Blessed be the Lord my strength which teacheth my hands to war, and my fingers to fight:
^2My goodness, and my fortress; my high tower, and my deliverer; my shield, and he in whom I trust; who subdueth my people under me.
^3Lord, what is man, that thou takest knowledge of him! or the son of man, that thou makest account of him!
^4Man is like to vanity: his days are as a shadow that passeth away.
^5Bow thy heavens, O Lord, and come down: touch the mountains, and they shall smoke.
^6Cast forth lightning, and scatter them: shoot out thine arrows, and destroy them.
^7Send thine hand from above; rid me, and deliver me out of great waters, from the hand of strange children;
^8Whose mouth speaketh vanity, and their right hand is a right hand of falsehood.
^9I will sing a new song unto thee, O God: upon a psaltery and an instrument of ten strings will I sing praises unto thee.
^10It is he that giveth salvation unto kings: who delivereth David his servant from the hurtful sword.
^11Rid me, and deliver me from the hand of strange children, whose mouth speaketh vanity, and their right hand is a right hand of falsehood:
^12That our sons may be as plants grown up in their youth; that our daughters may be as corner stones, polished after the similitude of a palace:
^13That our garners may be full, affording all manner of store: that our sheep may bring forth thousands and ten thousands in our streets:
^14That our oxen may be strong to labour; that there be no breaking in, nor going out; that there be no complaining in our streets.
^15Happy is that people, that is in such a case: yea, happy is that people, whose God is the Lord.

Psalm 145

^1I will extol thee, my God, O king; and I will bless thy name for ever and ever.
^2Every day will I bless thee; and I will praise thy name for ever and ever.
^3Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised; and his greatness is unsearchable.
^4One generation shall praise thy works to another, and shall declare thy mighty acts.
^5I will speak of the glorious honour of thy majesty, and of thy wondrous works.
^6And men shall speak of the might of thy terrible acts: and I will declare thy greatness.
^7They shall abundantly utter the memory of thy great goodness, and shall sing of thy righteousness.
^8The Lord is gracious, and full of compassion; slow to anger, and of great mercy.
^9The Lord is good to all: and his tender mercies are over all his works.
^10All thy works shall praise thee, O Lord; and thy saints shall bless thee.
^11They shall speak of the glory of thy kingdom, and talk of thy power;
^12To make known to the sons of men his mighty acts, and the glorious majesty of his kingdom.
^13Thy kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and thy dominion endureth throughout all generations.
^14The Lord upholdeth all that fall, and raiseth up all those that be bowed down.
^15The eyes of all wait upon thee; and thou givest them their meat in due season.
^16Thou openest thine hand, and satisfiest the desire of every living thing.
^17The Lord is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works.
^18The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him, to all that call upon him in truth.
^19He will fulfil the desire of them that fear him: he also will hear their cry, and will save them.
^20The Lord preserveth all them that love him: but all the wicked will he destroy.
^21My mouth shall speak the praise of the Lord: and let all flesh bless his holy name for ever and ever.

Psalm 146

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise the Lord, O my soul.
^2While I live will I praise the Lord: I will sing praises unto my God while I have any being.
^3Put not your trust in princes, nor in the son of man, in whom there is no help.
^4His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth; in that very day his thoughts perish.
^5Happy is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whose hope is in the Lord his God:
^6Which made heaven, and earth, the sea, and all that therein is: which keepeth truth for ever:
^7Which executeth judgment for the oppressed: which giveth food to the hungry. The Lord looseth the prisoners:
^8The Lord openeth the eyes of the blind: the Lord raiseth them that are bowed down: the Lord loveth the righteous:
^9The Lord preserveth the strangers; he relieveth the fatherless and widow: but the way of the wicked he turneth upside down.
^10The Lord shall reign for ever, even thy God, O Zion, unto all generations. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 147

^1Praise ye the Lord: for it is good to sing praises unto our God; for it is pleasant; and praise is comely.
^2The Lord doth build up Jerusalem: he gathereth together the outcasts of Israel.
^3He healeth the broken in heart, and bindeth up their wounds.
^4He telleth the number of the stars; he calleth them all by their names.
^5Great is our Lord, and of great power: his understanding is infinite.
^6The Lord lifteth up the meek: he casteth the wicked down to the ground.
^7Sing unto the Lord with thanksgiving; sing praise upon the harp unto our God:
^8Who covereth the heaven with clouds, who prepareth rain for the earth, who maketh grass to grow upon the mountains.
^9He giveth to the beast his food, and to the young ravens which cry.
^10He delighteth not in the strength of the horse: he taketh not pleasure in the legs of a man.
^11The Lord taketh pleasure in them that fear him, in those that hope in his mercy.
^12Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem; praise thy God, O Zion.
^13For he hath strengthened the bars of thy gates; he hath blessed thy children within thee.
^14He maketh peace in thy borders, and filleth thee with the finest of the wheat.
^15He sendeth forth his commandment upon earth: his word runneth very swiftly.
^16He giveth snow like wool: he scattereth the hoarfrost like ashes.
^17He casteth forth his ice like morsels: who can stand before his cold?
^18He sendeth out his word, and melteth them: he causeth his wind to blow, and the waters flow.
^19He sheweth his word unto Jacob, his statutes and his judgments unto Israel.
^20He hath not dealt so with any nation: and as for his judgments, they have not known them. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 148

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise ye the Lord from the heavens: praise him in the heights.
^2Praise ye him, all his angels: praise ye him, all his hosts.
^3Praise ye him, sun and moon: praise him, all ye stars of light.
^4Praise him, ye heavens of heavens, and ye waters that be above the heavens.
^5Let them praise the name of the Lord: for he commanded, and they were created.
^6He hath also stablished them for ever and ever: he hath made a decree which shall not pass.
^7Praise the Lord from the earth, ye dragons, and all deeps:
^8Fire, and hail; snow, and vapours; stormy wind fulfilling his word:
^9Mountains, and all hills; fruitful trees, and all cedars:
^10Beasts, and all cattle; creeping things, and flying fowl:
^11Kings of the earth, and all people; princes, and all judges of the earth:
^12Both young men, and maidens; old men, and children:
^13Let them praise the name of the Lord: for his name alone is excellent; his glory is above the earth and heaven.
^14He also exalteth the horn of his people, the praise of all his saints; even of the children of Israel, a people near unto him. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 149

^1Praise ye the Lord. Sing unto the Lord a new song, and his praise in the congregation of saints.
^2Let Israel rejoice in him that made him: let the children of Zion be joyful in their King.
^3Let them praise his name in the dance: let them sing praises unto him with the timbrel and harp.
^4For the Lord taketh pleasure in his people: he will beautify the meek with salvation.
^5Let the saints be joyful in glory: let them sing aloud upon their beds.
^6Let the high praises of God be in their mouth, and a two-edged sword in their hand;
^7To execute vengeance upon the heathen, and punishments upon the people;
^8To bind their kings with chains, and their nobles with fetters of iron;
^9To execute upon them the judgment written: this honour have all his saints. Praise ye the Lord.

Psalm 150

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise God in his sanctuary: praise him in the firmament of his power.
^2Praise him for his mighty acts: praise him according to his excellent greatness.
^3Praise him with the sound of the trumpet: praise him with the psaltery and harp.
^4Praise him with the timbrel and dance: praise him with stringed instruments and organs.
^5Praise him upon the loud cymbals: praise him upon the high sounding cymbals.
^6Let every thing that hath breath praise the Lord. Praise ye the Lord.

The Fourth Book of

Psalms

XC

^1Lord, thou hast been our dwelling place in all generations.
^2Before the mountains were brought forth, or ever thou hadst formed the earth and the world, even from everlasting to everlasting, thou art God.
^3Thou turnest man to destruction; and sayest, Return, ye children of men.
^4For a thousand years in thy sight are but as yesterday when it is past, and as a watch in the night.
^5Thou carriest them away as with a flood; they are as a sleep: in the morning they are like grass which groweth up.
^6In the morning it flourisheth, and groweth up; in the evening it is cut down, and withereth.
^7For we are consumed by thine anger, and by thy wrath are we troubled.
^8Thou hast set our iniquities before thee, our secret sins in the light of thy countenance.
^9For all our days are passed away in thy wrath: we spend our years as a tale that is told.
^10The days of our years are threescore years and ten; and if by reason of strength they be fourscore years, yet is their strength labour and sorrow; for it is soon cut off, and we fly away.
^11Who knoweth the power of thine anger? even according to thy fear, so is thy wrath.
^12So teach us to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.
^13Return, O Lord, how long? and let it repent thee concerning thy servants.
^14O satisfy us early with thy mercy; that we may rejoice and be glad all our days.
^15Make us glad according to the days wherein thou hast afflicted us, and the years wherein we have seen evil.
^16Let thy work appear unto thy servants, and thy glory unto their children.
^17And let the beauty of the Lord our God be upon us: and establish thou the work of our hands upon us; yea, the work of our hands establish thou it.

XCI

^1He that dwelleth in the secret place of the most High shall abide under the shadow of the Almighty.
^2I will say of the Lord, He is my refuge and my fortress: my God; in him will I trust.
^3Surely he shall deliver thee from the snare of the fowler, and from the noisome pestilence.
^4He shall cover thee with his feathers, and under his wings shalt thou trust: his truth shall be thy shield and buckler.
^5Thou shalt not be afraid for the terror by night; nor for the arrow that flieth by day;
^6Nor for the pestilence that walketh in darkness; nor for the destruction that wasteth at noonday.
^7A thousand shall fall at thy side, and ten thousand at thy right hand; but it shall not come nigh thee.
^8Only with thine eyes shalt thou behold and see the reward of the wicked.
^9Because thou hast made the Lord, which is my refuge, even the most High, thy habitation;
^10There shall no evil befall thee, neither shall any plague come nigh thy dwelling.
^11For he shall give his angels charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy ways.
^12They shall bear thee up in their hands, lest thou dash thy foot against a stone.
^13Thou shalt tread upon the lion and adder: the young lion and the dragon shalt thou trample under feet.
^14Because he hath set his love upon me, therefore will I deliver him: I will set him on high, because he hath known my name.
^15He shall call upon me, and I will answer him: I will be with him in trouble; I will deliver him, and honour him.
^16With long life will I satisfy him, and shew him my salvation.

XCII

^1It is a good thing to gives thanks unto the Lord, and to sing praises unto thy name, O most High:
^2To shew forth thy lovingkindness in the morning, and thy faithfulness every night,
^3Upon an instrument of ten strings, and upon the psaltery; upon the harp with a solemn sound.
^4For thou, Lord, hast made me glad through thy work: I will triumph in the works of thy hands.
^5O Lord, how great are thy works! and thy thoughts are very deep.
^6A brutish man knoweth not; neither doth a fool understand this.
^7When the wicked spring as the grass, and when all the workers of iniquity do flourish; it is that they shall be destroyed for ever:
^8But thou, Lord, art most high for evermore.
^9For, lo, thine enemies, O Lord, for, lo, thine enemies shall perish; all the workers of iniquity shall be scattered.
^10But my horn shalt thou exalt like the horn of an unicorn: I shall be anointed with fresh oil.
^11Mine eye also shall see my desire on mine enemies, and mine ears shall hear my desire of the wicked that rise up against me.
^12The righteous shall flourish like the palm tree: he shall grow like a cedar in Lebanon.
^13Those that be planted in the house of the Lord shall flourish in the courts of our God.
^14They shall still bring forth fruit in old age; they shall be fat and flourishing;
^15To shew that the Lord is upright: he is my rock, and there is no unrighteousness in him.

XCIII

^1The Lord reigneth, he is clothed with majesty; the Lord is clothed with strength, wherewith he hath girded himself: the world also is stablished, that it cannot be moved.
^2Thy throne is established of old: thou art from everlasting.
^3The floods have lifted up, O Lord, the floods have lifted up their voice; the floods lift up their waves.
^4The Lord on high is mightier than the noise of many waters, yea, than the mighty waves of the sea.
^5Thy testimonies are very sure: holiness becometh thine house, O Lord, for ever.

XCIV

^1O Lord God, to whom vengeance belongeth; O God, to whom vengeance belongeth, shew thyself.
^2Lift up thyself, thou judge of the earth: render a reward to the proud.
^3Lord, how long shall the wicked, how long shall the wicked triumph?
^4How long shall they utter and speak hard things? and all the workers of iniquity boast themselves?
^5They break in pieces thy people, O Lord, and afflict thine heritage.
^6They slay the widow and the stranger, and murder the fatherless.
^7Yet they say, The Lord shall not see, neither shall the God of Jacob regard it.
^8Understand, ye brutish among the people: and ye fools, when will ye be wise?
^9He that planted the ear, shall he not hear? he that formed the eye, shall he not see?
^10He that chastiseth the heathen, shall not he correct? he that teacheth man knowledge, shall not he know?
^11The Lord knoweth the thoughts of man, that they are vanity.
^12Blessed is the man whom thou chastenest, O Lord, and teachest him out of thy law;
^13That thou mayest give him rest from the days of adversity, until the pit be digged for the wicked.
^14For the Lord will not cast off his people, neither will he forsake his inheritance.
^15But judgment shall return unto righteousness: and all the upright in heart shall follow it.
^16Who will rise up for me against the evildoers? or who will stand up for me against the workers of iniquity?
^17Unless the Lord had been my help, my soul had almost dwelt in silence.
^18When I said, My foot slippeth; thy mercy, O Lord, held me up.
^19In the multitude of my thoughts within me thy comforts delight my soul.
^20Shall the throne of iniquity have fellowship with thee, which frameth mischief by a law?
^21They gather themselves together against the soul of the righteous, and condemn the innocent blood.
^22But the Lord is my defence; and my God is the rock of my refuge.
^23And he shall bring upon them their own iniquity, and shall cut them off in their own wickedness; yea, the Lord our God shall cut them off.

XCV

^1O come, let us sing unto the Lord: let us make a joyful noise to the rock of our salvation.
^2Let us come before his presence with thanksgiving, and make a joyful noise unto him with psalms.
^3For the Lord is a great God, and a great King above all gods.
^4In his hand are the deep places of the earth: the strength of the hills is his also.
^5The sea is his, and he made it: and his hands formed the dry land.
^6O come, let us worship and bow down: let us kneel before the Lord our maker.
^7For he is our God; and we are the people of his pasture, and the sheep of his hand. To day if ye will hear his voice,
^8Harden not your heart, as in the provocation, and as in the day of temptation in the wilderness:
^9When your fathers tempted me, proved me, and saw my work.
^10Forty years long was I grieved with this generation, and said, It is a people that do err in their heart, and they have not known my ways:
^11Unto whom I sware in my wrath that they should not enter into my rest.

XCVI

^1O sing unto the Lord a new song: sing unto the Lord, all the earth.
^2Sing unto the Lord, bless his name; shew forth his salvation from day to day.
^3Declare his glory among the heathen, his wonders among all people.
^4For the Lord is great, and greatly to be praised: he is to be feared above all gods.
^5For all the gods of the nations are idols: but the Lord made the heavens.
^6Honour and majesty are before him: strength and beauty are in his sanctuary.
^7Give unto the Lord, O ye kindreds of the people, give unto the Lord glory and strength.
^8Give unto the Lord the glory due unto his name: bring an offering, and come into his courts.
^9O worship the Lord in the beauty of holiness: fear before him, all the earth.
^10Say among the heathen that the Lord reigneth: the world also shall be established that it shall not be moved: he shall judge the people righteously.
^11Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth be glad; let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof.
^12Let the field be joyful, and all that is therein: then shall all the trees of the wood rejoice
^13Before the Lord: for he cometh, for he cometh to judge the earth: he shall judge the world with righteousness, and the people with his truth.

XCVII

^1The Lord reigneth; let the earth rejoice; let the multitude of isles be glad thereof.
^2Clouds and darkness are round about him: righteousness and judgment are the habitation of his throne.
^3A fire goeth before him, and burneth up his enemies round about.
^4His lightnings enlightened the world: the earth saw, and trembled.
^5The hills melted like wax at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the Lord of the whole earth.
^6The heavens declare his righteousness, and all the people see his glory.
^7Confounded be all they that serve graven images, that boast themselves of idols: worship him, all ye gods.
^8Zion heard, and was glad; and the daughters of Judah rejoiced because of thy judgments, O Lord.
^9For thou, Lord, art high above all the earth: thou art exalted far above all gods.
^10Ye that love the Lord, hate evil: he preserveth the souls of his saints; he delivereth them out of the hand of the wicked.
^11Light is sown for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in heart.
^12Rejoice in the Lord, ye righteous; and give thanks at the remembrance of his holiness.

XCVIII

^1O sing unto the Lord a new song; for he hath done marvellous things: his right hand, and his holy arm, hath gotten him the victory.
^2The Lord hath made known his salvation: his righteousness hath he openly shewed in the sight of the heathen.
^3He hath remembered his mercy and his truth toward the house of Israel: all the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God.
^4Make a joyful noise unto the Lord, all the earth: make a loud noise, and rejoice, and sing praise.
^5Sing unto the Lord with the harp; with the harp, and the voice of a psalm.
^6With trumpets and sound of cornet make a joyful noise before the Lord, the King.
^7Let the sea roar, and the fulness thereof; the world, and they that dwell therein.
^8Let the floods clap their hands: let the hills be joyful together
^9Before the Lord; for he cometh to judge the earth: with righteousness shall he judge the world, and the people with equity.

XCIX

^1The Lord reigneth; let the people tremble: he sitteth between the cherubims; let the earth be moved.
^2The Lord is great in Zion; and he is high above all the people.
^3Let them praise thy great and terrible name; for it is holy.
^4The king’s strength also loveth judgment; thou dost establish equity, thou executest judgment and righteousness in Jacob.
^5Exalt ye the Lord our God, and worship at his footstool; for he is holy.
^6Moses and Aaron among his priests, and Samuel among them that call upon his name; they called upon the Lord, and he answered them.
^7He spake unto them in the cloudy pillar: they kept his testimonies, and the ordinance that he gave them.
^8Thou answeredst them, O Lord our God: thou wast a God that forgavest them, though thou tookest vengeance of their inventions.
^9Exalt the Lord our God, and worship at his holy hill; for the Lord our God is holy.

C

^1Make a joyful noise unto the Lord, all ye lands.
^2Serve the Lord with gladness: come before his presence with singing.
^3Know ye that the Lord he is God: it is he that hath made us, and not we ourselves; we are his people, and the sheep of his pasture.
^4Enter into his gates with thanksgiving, and into his courts with praise: be thankful unto him, and bless his name.
^5For the Lord is good; his mercy is everlasting; and his truth endureth to all generations.

CI

^1I will sing of mercy and judgment: unto thee, O Lord, will I sing.
^2I will behave myself wisely in a perfect way. O when wilt thou come unto me? I will walk within my house with a perfect heart.
^3I will set no wicked thing before mine eyes: I hate the work of them that turn aside; it shall not cleave to me.
^4A froward heart shall depart from me: I will not know a wicked person.
^5Whoso privily slandereth his neighbour, him will I cut off: him that hath an high look and a proud heart will not I suffer.
^6Mine eyes shall be upon the faithful of the land, that they may dwell with me: he that walketh in a perfect way, he shall serve me.
^7He that worketh deceit shall not dwell within my house: he that telleth lies shall not tarry in my sight.
^8I will early destroy all the wicked of the land; that I may cut off all wicked doers from the city of the Lord.

CII

^1Hear my prayer, O Lord, and let my cry come unto thee.
^2Hide not thy face from me in the day when I am in trouble; incline thine ear unto me: in the day when I call answer me speedily.
^3For my days are consumed like smoke, and my bones are burned as an hearth.
^4My heart is smitten, and withered like grass; so that I forget to eat my bread.
^5By reason of the voice of my groaning my bones cleave to my skin.
^6I am like a pelican of the wilderness: I am like an owl of the desert.
^7I watch, and am as a sparrow alone upon the house top.
^8Mine enemies reproach me all the day; and they that are mad against me are sworn against me.
^9For I have eaten ashes like bread, and mingled my drink with weeping.
^10Because of thine indignation and thy wrath: for thou hast lifted me up, and cast me down.
^11My days are like a shadow that declineth; and I am withered like grass.
^12But thou, O Lord, shall endure for ever; and thy remembrance unto all generations.
^13Thou shalt arise, and have mercy upon Zion: for the time to favour her, yea, the set time, is come.
^14For thy servants take pleasure in her stones, and favour the dust thereof.
^15So the heathen shall fear the name of the Lord, and all the kings of the earth thy glory.
^16When the Lord shall build up Zion, he shall appear in his glory.
^17He will regard the prayer of the destitute, and not despise their prayer.
^18This shall be written for the generation to come: and the people which shall be created shall praise the Lord.
^19For he hath looked down from the height of his sanctuary; from heaven did the Lord behold the earth;
^20To hear the groaning of the prisoner; to loose those that are appointed to death;
^21To declare the name of the Lord in Zion, and his praise in Jerusalem;
^22When the people are gathered together, and the kingdoms, to serve the Lord.
^23He weakened my strength in the way; he shortened my days.
^24I said, O my God, take me not away in the midst of my days: thy years are throughout all generations.
^25Of old hast thou laid the foundation of the earth: and the heavens are the work of thy hands.
^26They shall perish, but thou shalt endure: yea, all of them shall wax old like a garment; as a vesture shalt thou change them, and they shall be changed:
^27But thou art the same, and thy years shall have no end.
^28The children of thy servants shall continue, and their seed shall be established before thee.

CIII

^1Bless the Lord, O my soul: and all that is within me, bless his holy name.
^2Bless the Lord, O my soul, and forget not all his benefits:
^3Who forgiveth all thine iniquities; who healeth all thy diseases;
^4Who redeemeth thy life from destruction; who crowneth thee with lovingkindness and tender mercies;
^5Who satisfieth thy mouth with good things; so that thy youth is renewed like the eagle’s.
^6The Lord executeth righteousness and judgment for all that are oppressed.
^7He made known his ways unto Moses, his acts unto the children of Israel.
^8The Lord is merciful and gracious, slow to anger, and plenteous in mercy.
^9He will not always chide: neither will he keep his anger for ever.
^10He hath not dealt with us after our sins; nor rewarded us according to our iniquities.
^11For as the heaven is high above the earth, so great is his mercy toward them that fear him.
^12As far as the east is from the west, so far hath he removed our transgressions from us.
^13Like as a father pitieth his children, so the Lord pitieth them that fear him.
^14For he knoweth our frame; he remembereth that we are dust.
^15As for man, his days are as grass: as a flower of the field, so he flourisheth.
^16For the wind passeth over it, and it is gone; and the place thereof shall know it no more.
^17But the mercy of the Lord is from everlasting to everlasting upon them that fear him, and his righteousness unto children’s children;
^18To such as keep his covenant, and to those that remember his commandments to do them.
^19The Lord hath prepared his throne in the heavens; and his kingdom ruleth over all.
^20Bless the Lord, ye his angels, that excel in strength, that do his commandments, hearkening unto the voice of his word.
^21Bless ye the Lord, all ye his hosts; ye ministers of his, that do his pleasure.
^22Bless the Lord, all his works in all places of his dominion: bless the Lord, O my soul.

CIV

^1Bless the Lord, O my soul. O Lord my God, thou art very great; thou art clothed with honour and majesty.
^2Who coverest thyself with light as with a garment: who stretchest out the heavens like a curtain:
^3Who layeth the beams of his chambers in the waters: who maketh the clouds his chariot: who walketh upon the wings of the wind:
^4Who maketh his angels spirits; his ministers a flaming fire:
^5Who laid the foundations of the earth, that it should not be removed for ever.
^6Thou coveredst it with the deep as with a garment: the waters stood above the mountains.
^7At thy rebuke they fled; at the voice of thy thunder they hasted away.
^8They go up by the mountains; they go down by the valleys unto the place which thou hast founded for them.
^9Thou hast set a bound that they may not pass over; that they turn not again to cover the earth.
^10He sendeth the springs into the valleys, which run among the hills.
^11They give drink to every beast of the field: the wild asses quench their thirst.
^12By them shall the fowls of the heaven have their habitation, which sing among the branches.
^13He watereth the hills from his chambers: the earth is satisfied with the fruit of thy works.
^14He causeth the grass to grow for the cattle, and herb for the service of man: that he may bring forth food out of the earth;
^15And wine that maketh glad the heart of man, and oil to make his face to shine, and bread which strengtheneth man’s heart.
^16The trees of the Lord are full of sap; the cedars of Lebanon, which he hath planted;
^17Where the birds make their nests: as for the stork, the fir trees are her house.
^18The high hills are a refuge for the wild goats; and the rocks for the conies.
^19He appointed the moon for seasons: the sun knoweth his going down.
^20Thou makest darkness, and it is night: wherein all the beasts of the forest do creep forth.
^21The young lions roar after their prey, and seek their meat from God.
^22The sun ariseth, they gather themselves together, and lay them down in their dens.
^23Man goeth forth unto his work and to his labour until the evening.
^24O Lord, how manifold are thy works! in wisdom hast thou made them all: the earth is full of thy riches.
^25So is this great and wide sea, wherein are things creeping innumerable, both small and great beasts.
^26There go the ships: there is that leviathan, whom thou hast made to play therein.
^27These wait all upon thee; that thou mayest give them their meat in due season.
^28That thou givest them they gather: thou openest thine hand, they are filled with good.
^29Thou hidest thy face, they are troubled: thou takest away their breath, they die, and return to their dust.
^30Thou sendest forth thy spirit, they are created: and thou renewest the face of the earth.
^31The glory of the Lord shall endure for ever: the Lord shall rejoice in his works.
^32He looketh on the earth, and it trembleth: he toucheth the hills, and they smoke.
^33I will sing unto the Lord as long as I live: I will sing praise to my God while I have my being.
^34My meditation of him shall be sweet: I will be glad in the Lord.
^35Let the sinners be consumed out of the earth, and let the wicked be no more. Bless thou the Lord, O my soul. Praise ye the Lord.

CV

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; call upon his name: make known his deeds among the people.
^2Sing unto him, sing psalms unto him: talk ye of all his wondrous works.
^3Glory ye in his holy name: let the heart of them rejoice that seek the Lord.
^4Seek the Lord, and his strength: seek his face evermore.
^5Remember his marvellous works that he hath done; his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth;
^6O ye seed of Abraham his servant, ye children of Jacob his chosen.
^7He is the Lord our God: his judgments are in all the earth.
^8He hath remembered his covenant for ever, the word which he commanded to a thousand generations.
^9Which covenant he made with Abraham, and his oath unto Isaac;
^10And confirmed the same unto Jacob for a law, and to Israel for an everlasting covenant:
^11Saying, Unto thee will I give the land of Canaan, the lot of your inheritance:
^12When they were but a few men in number; yea, very few, and strangers in it.
^13When they went from one nation to another, from one kingdom to another people;
^14He suffered no man to do them wrong: yea, he reproved kings for their sakes;
^15Saying, Touch not mine anointed, and do my prophets no harm.
^16Moreover he called for a famine upon the land: he brake the whole staff of bread.
^17He sent a man before them, even Joseph, who was sold for a servant:
^18Whose feet they hurt with fetters: he was laid in iron:
^19Until the time that his word came: the word of the Lord tried him.
^20The king sent and loosed him; even the ruler of the people, and let him go free.
^21He made him lord of his house, and ruler of all his substance:
^22To bind his princes at his pleasure; and teach his senators wisdom.
^23Israel also came into Egypt; and Jacob sojourned in the land of Ham.
^24And he increased his people greatly; and made them stronger than their enemies.
^25He turned their heart to hate his people, to deal subtilly with his servants.
^26He sent Moses his servant; and Aaron whom he had chosen.
^27They shewed his signs among them, and wonders in the land of Ham.
^28He sent darkness, and made it dark; and they rebelled not against his word.
^29He turned their waters into blood, and slew their fish.
^30Their land brought forth frogs in abundance, in the chambers of their kings.
^31He spake, and there came divers sorts of flies, and lice in all their coasts.
^32He gave them hail for rain, and flaming fire in their land.
^33He smote their vines also and their fig trees; and brake the trees of their coasts.
^34He spake, and the locusts came, and caterpillers, and that without number,
^35And did eat up all the herbs in their land, and devoured the fruit of their ground.
^36He smote also all the firstborn in their land, the chief of all their strength.
^37He brought them forth also with silver and gold: and there was not one feeble person among their tribes.
^38Egypt was glad when they departed: for the fear of them fell upon them.
^39He spread a cloud for a covering; and fire to give light in the night.
^40The people asked, and he brought quails, and satisfied them with the bread of heaven.
^41He opened the rock, and the waters gushed out; they ran in the dry places like a river.
^42For he remembered his holy promise, and Abraham his servant.
^43And he brought forth his people with joy, and his chosen with gladness:
^44And gave them the lands of the heathen: and they inherited the labour of the people;
^45That they might observe his statutes, and keep his laws. Praise ye the Lord.

CVI

^1Praise ye the Lord. O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Who can utter the mighty acts of the Lord? who can shew forth all his praise?
^3Blessed are they that keep judgment, and he that doeth righteousness at all times.
^4Remember me, O Lord, with the favour that thou bearest unto thy people: O visit me with thy salvation;
^5That I may see the good of thy chosen, that I may rejoice in the gladness of thy nation, that I may glory with thine inheritance.
^6We have sinned with our fathers, we have committed iniquity, we have done wickedly.
^7Our fathers understood not thy wonders in Egypt; they remembered not the multitude of thy mercies; but provoked him at the sea, even at the Red sea.
^8Nevertheless he saved them for his name’s sake, that he might make his mighty power to be known.
^9He rebuked the Red sea also, and it was dried up: so he led them through the depths, as through the wilderness.
^10And he saved them from the hand of him that hated them, and redeemed them from the hand of the enemy.
^11And the waters covered their enemies: there was not one of them left.
^12Then believed they his words; they sang his praise.
^13They soon forgat his works; they waited not for his counsel:
^14But lusted exceedingly in the wilderness, and tempted God in the desert.
^15And he gave them their request; but sent leanness into their soul.
^16They envied Moses also in the camp, and Aaron the saint of the Lord.
^17The earth opened and swallowed up Dathan and covered the company of Abiram.
^18And a fire was kindled in their company; the flame burned up the wicked.
^19They made a calf in Horeb, and worshipped the molten image.
^20Thus they changed their glory into the similitude of an ox that eateth grass.
^21They forgat God their saviour, which had done great things in Egypt;
^22Wondrous works in the land of Ham, and terrible things by the Red sea.
^23Therefore he said that he would destroy them, had not Moses his chosen stood before him in the breach, to turn away his wrath, lest he should destroy them.
^24Yea, they despised the pleasant land, they believed not his word:
^25But murmured in their tents, and hearkened not unto the voice of the Lord.
^26Therefore he lifted up his hand against them, to overthrow them in the wilderness:
^27To overthrow their seed also among the nations, and to scatter them in the lands.
^28They joined themselves also unto Baalpeor, and ate the sacrifices of the dead.
^29Thus they provoked him to anger with their inventions: and the plague brake in upon them.
^30Then stood up Phinehas, and executed judgment: and so the plague was stayed.
^31And that was counted unto him for righteousness unto all generations for evermore.
^32They angered him also at the waters of strife, so that it went ill with Moses for their sakes:
^33Because they provoked his spirit, so that he spake unadvisedly with his lips.
^34They did not destroy the nations, concerning whom the Lord commanded them:
^35But were mingled among the heathen, and learned their works.
^36And they served their idols: which were a snare unto them.
^37Yea, they sacrificed their sons and their daughters unto devils,
^38And shed innocent blood, even the blood of their sons and of their daughters, whom they sacrificed unto the idols of Canaan: and the land was polluted with blood.
^39Thus were they defiled with their own works, and went a whoring with their own inventions.
^40Therefore was the wrath of the Lord kindled against his people, insomuch that he abhorred his own inheritance.
^41And he gave them into the hand of the heathen; and they that hated them ruled over them.
^42Their enemies also oppressed them, and they were brought into subjection under their hand.
^43Many times did he deliver them; but they provoked him with their counsel, and were brought low for their iniquity.
^44Nevertheless he regarded their affliction, when he heard their cry:
^45And he remembered for them his covenant, and repented according to the multitude of his mercies.
^46He made them also to be pitied of all those that carried them captives.
^47Save us, O Lord our God, and gather us from among the heathen, to give thanks unto thy holy name, and to triumph in thy praise.
^48Blessed be the Lord God of Israel from everlasting to everlasting: and let all the people say, Amen. Praise ye the Lord.

The Fifth Book of

Psalms

CVII

^1O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Let the redeemed of the Lord say so, whom he hath redeemed from the hand of the enemy;
^3And gathered them out of the lands, from the east, and from the west, from the north, and from the south.
^4They wandered in the wilderness in a solitary way; they found no city to dwell in.
^5Hungry and thirsty, their soul fainted in them.
^6Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and he delivered them out of their distresses.
^7And he led them forth by the right way, that they might go to a city of habitation.
^8Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^9For he satisfieth the longing soul, and filleth the hungry soul with goodness.
^10Such as sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, being bound in affliction and iron;
^11Because they rebelled against the words of God, and contemned the counsel of the most High:
^12Therefore he brought down their heart with labour; they fell down, and there was none to help.
^13Then they cried unto the Lord in their trouble, and he saved them out of their distresses.
^14He brought them out of darkness and the shadow of death, and brake their bands in sunder.
^15Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^16For he hath broken the gates of brass, and cut the bars of iron in sunder.
^17Fools because of their transgression, and because of their iniquities, are afflicted.
^18Their soul abhorreth all manner of meat; and they draw near unto the gates of death.
^19Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he saveth them out of their distresses.
^20He sent his word, and healed them, and delivered them from their destructions.
^21Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^22And let them sacrifice the sacrifices of thanksgiving, and declare his works with rejoicing.
^23They that go down to the sea in ships, that do business in great waters;
^24These see the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep.
^25For he commandeth, and raiseth the stormy wind, which lifteth up the waves thereof.
^26They mount up to the heaven, they go down again to the depths: their soul is melted because of trouble.
^27They reel to and fro, and stagger like a drunken man, and are at their wit’s end.
^28Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he bringeth them out of their distresses.
^29He maketh the storm a calm, so that the waves thereof are still.
^30Then are they glad because they be quiet; so he bringeth them unto their desired haven.
^31Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for his wonderful works to the children of men!
^32Let them exalt him also in the congregation of the people, and praise him in the assembly of the elders.
^33He turneth rivers into a wilderness, and the watersprings into dry ground;
^34A fruitful land into barrenness, for the wickedness of them that dwell therein.
^35He turneth the wilderness into a standing water, and dry ground into watersprings.
^36And there he maketh the hungry to dwell, that they may prepare a city for habitation;
^37And sow the fields, and plant vineyards, which may yield fruits of increase.
^38He blesseth them also, so that they are multiplied greatly; and suffereth not their cattle to decrease.
^39Again, they are minished and brought low through oppression, affliction, and sorrow.
^40He poureth contempt upon princes, and causeth them to wander in the wilderness, where there is no way.
^41Yet setteth he the poor on high from affliction, and maketh him families like a flock.
^42The righteous shall see it, and rejoice: and all iniquity shall stop her mouth.
^43Whoso is wise, and will observe these things, even they shall understand the lovingkindness of the Lord.

CVIII

^1O god, my heart is fixed; I will sing and give praise, even with my glory.
^2Awake, psaltery and harp: I myself will awake early.
^3I will praise thee, O Lord, among the people: and I will sing praises unto thee among the nations.
^4For thy mercy is great above the heavens: and thy truth reacheth unto the clouds.
^5Be thou exalted, O God, above the heavens: and thy glory above all the earth;
^6That thy beloved may be delivered: save with thy right hand, and answer me.
^7God hath spoken in his holiness; I will rejoice, I will divide Shechem, and mete out the valley of Succoth.
^8Gilead is mine; Manasseh is mine; Ephraim also is the strength of mine head; Judah is my lawgiver;
^9Moab is my washpot; over Edom will I cast out my shoe; over Philistia will I triumph.
^10Who will bring me into the strong city? who will lead me into Edom?
^11Wilt not thou, O God, who hast cast us off? and wilt not thou, O God, go forth with our hosts?
^12Give us help from trouble: for vain is the help of man.
^13Through God we shall do valiantly: for he it is that shall tread down our enemies.

CIX

^1Hold not thy peace, O God of my praise;
^2For the mouth of the wicked and the mouth of the deceitful are opened against me: they have spoken against me with a lying tongue.
^3They compassed me about also with words of hatred; and fought against me without a cause.
^4For my love they are my adversaries: but I give myself unto prayer.
^5And they have rewarded me evil for good, and hatred for my love.
^6Set thou a wicked man over him: and let Satan stand at his right hand.
^7When he shall be judged, let him be condemned: and let his prayer become sin.
^8Let his days be few; and let another take his office.
^9Let his children be fatherless, and his wife a widow.
^10Let his children be continually vagabonds, and beg: let them seek their bread also out of their desolate places.
^11Let the extortioner catch all that he hath; and let the strangers spoil his labour.
^12Let there be none to extend mercy unto him: neither let there be any to favour his fatherless children.
^13Let his posterity be cut off; and in the generation following let their name be blotted out.
^14Let the iniquity of his fathers be remembered with the Lord; and let not the sin of his mother be blotted out.
^15Let them be before the Lord continually, that he may cut off the memory of them from the earth.
^16Because that he remembered not to shew mercy, but persecuted the poor and needy man, that he might even slay the broken in heart.
^17As he loved cursing, so let it come unto him: as he delighted not in blessing, so let it be far from him.
^18As he clothed himself with cursing like as with his garment, so let it come into his bowels like water, and like oil into his bones.
^19Let it be unto him as the garment which covereth him, and for a girdle wherewith he is girded continually.
^20Let this be the reward of mine adversaries from the Lord, and of them that speak evil against my soul.
^21But do thou for me, O God the Lord, for thy name’s sake: because thy mercy is good, deliver thou me.
^22For I am poor and needy, and my heart is wounded within me.
^23I am gone like the shadow when it declineth: I am tossed up and down as the locust.
^24My knees are weak through fasting; and my flesh faileth of fatness.
^25I became also a reproach unto them: when they looked upon me they shaked their heads.
^26Help me, O Lord my God: O save me according to thy mercy:
^27That they may know that this is thy hand; that thou, Lord, hast done it.
^28Let them curse, but bless thou: when they arise, let them be ashamed; but let thy servant rejoice.
^29Let mine adversaries be clothed with shame, and let them cover themselves with their own confusion, as with a mantle.
^30I will greatly praise the Lord with my mouth; yea, I will praise him among the multitude.
^31For he shall stand at the right hand of the poor, to save him from those that condemn his soul.

CX

^1The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footstool.
^2The Lord shall send the rod of thy strength out of Zion: rule thou in the midst of thine enemies.
^3Thy people shall be willing in the day of thy power, in the beauties of holiness from the womb of the morning: thou hast the dew of thy youth.
^4The Lord hath sworn, and will not repent, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchizedek.
^5The Lord at thy right hand shall strike through kings in the day of his wrath.
^6He shall judge among the heathen, he shall fill the places with the dead bodies; he shall wound the heads over many countries.
^7He shall drink of the brook in the way: therefore shall he lift up the head.

CXI

^1Praise ye the Lord. I will praise the Lord with my whole heart, in the assembly of the upright, and in the congregation.
^2The works of the Lord are great, sought out of all them that have pleasure therein.
^3His work is honourable and glorious: and his righteousness endureth for ever.
^4He hath made his wonderful works to be remembered: the Lord is gracious and full of compassion.
^5He hath given meat unto them that fear him: he will ever be mindful of his covenant.
^6He hath shewed his people the power of his works, that he may give them the heritage of the heathen.
^7The works of his hands are verity and judgment; all his commandments are sure.
^8They stand fast for ever and ever, and are done in truth and uprightness.
^9He sent redemption unto his people: he hath commanded his covenant for ever: holy and reverend is his name.
^10The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom: a good understanding have all they that do his commandments: his praise endureth for ever.

CXII

^1Praise ye the Lord. Blessed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his commandments.
^2His seed shall be mighty upon earth: the generation of the upright shall be blessed.
^3Wealth and riches shall be in his house: and his righteousness endureth for ever.
^4Unto the upright there ariseth light in the darkness: he is gracious, and full of compassion, and righteous.
^5A good man sheweth favour, and lendeth: he will guide his affairs with discretion.
^6Surely he shall not be moved for ever: the righteous shall be in everlasting remembrance.
^7He shall not be afraid of evil tidings: his heart is fixed, trusting in the Lord.
^8His heart is established, he shall not be afraid, until he see his desire upon his enemies.
^9He hath dispersed, he hath given to the poor; his righteousness endureth for ever; his horn shall be exalted with honour.
^10The wicked shall see it, and be grieved; he shall gnash with his teeth, and melt away: the desire of the wicked shall perish.

CXIII

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise, O ye servants of the Lord, praise the name of the Lord.
^2Blessed be the name of the Lord from this time forth and for evermore.
^3From the rising of the sun unto the going down of the same the Lord’s name is to be praised.
^4The Lord is high above all nations, and his glory above the heavens.
^5Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwelleth on high,
^6Who humbleth himself to behold the things that are in heaven, and in the earth!
^7He raiseth up the poor out of the dust, and lifteth the needy out of the dunghill;
^8That he may set him with princes, even with the princes of his people.
^9He maketh the barren woman to keep house, and to be a joyful mother of children. Praise ye the Lord.

CXIV

^1When Israel went out of Egypt, the house of Jacob from a people of strange language;
^2Judah was his sanctuary, and Israel his dominion.
^3The sea saw it, and fled: Jordan was driven back.
^4The mountains skipped like rams, and the little hills like lambs.
^5What ailed thee, O thou sea, that thou fleddest? thou Jordan, that thou wast driven back?
^6Ye mountains, that ye skipped like rams; and ye little hills, like lambs?
^7Tremble, thou earth, at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the God of Jacob;
^8Which turned the rock into a standing water, the flint into a fountain of waters.

CXV

^1Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name give glory, for thy mercy, and for thy truth’s sake.
^2Wherefore should the heathen say, Where is now their God?
^3But our God is in the heavens: he hath done whatsoever he hath pleased.
^4Their idols are silver and gold, the work of men’s hands.
^5They have mouths, but they speak not: eyes have they, but they see not:
^6They have ears, but they hear not: noses have they, but they smell not:
^7They have hands, but they handle not: feet have they, but they walk not: neither speak they through their throat.
^8They that make them are like unto them; so is every one that trusteth in them.
^9O Israel, trust thou in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^10O house of Aaron, trust in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^11Ye that fear the Lord, trust in the Lord: he is their help and their shield.
^12The Lord hath been mindful of us: he will bless us; he will bless the house of Israel; he will bless the house of Aaron.
^13He will bless them that fear the Lord, both small and great.
^14The Lord shall increase you more and more, you and your children.
^15Ye are blessed of the Lord which made heaven and earth.
^16The heaven, even the heavens, are the Lord’s: but the earth hath he given to the children of men.
^17The dead praise not the Lord, neither any that go down into silence.
^18But we will bless the Lord from this time forth and for evermore. Praise the Lord.

CXVI

^1I love the Lord, because he hath heard my voice and my supplications.
^2Because he hath inclined his ear unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live.
^3The sorrows of death compassed me, and the pains of hell gat hold upon me: I found trouble and sorrow.
^4Then called I upon the name of the Lord; O Lord, I beseech thee, deliver my soul.
^5Gracious is the Lord, and righteous; yea, our God is merciful.
^6The Lord preserveth the simple: I was brought low, and he helped me.
^7Return unto thy rest, O my soul; for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.
^8For thou hast delivered my soul from death, mine eyes from tears, and my feet from falling.
^9I will walk before the Lord in the land of the living.
^10I believed, therefore have I spoken: I was greatly afflicted:
^11I said in my haste, All men are liars.
^12What shall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits toward me?
^13I will take the cup of salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord.
^14I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all his people.
^15Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of his saints.
^16O Lord, truly I am thy servant; I am thy servant, and the son of thine handmaid: thou hast loosed my bonds.
^17I will offer to thee the sacrifice of thanksgiving, and will call upon the name of the Lord.
^18I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the presence of all his people.
^19In the courts of the Lord’s house, in the midst of thee, O Jerusalem. Praise ye the Lord.

CXVII

^1O praise the Lord, all ye nations: praise him, all ye people.
^2For his merciful kindness is great toward us: and the truth of the Lord endureth for ever. Praise ye the Lord.

CXVIII

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: because his mercy endureth for ever.
^2Let Israel now say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^3Let the house of Aaron now say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^4Let them now that fear the Lord say, that his mercy endureth for ever.
^5I called upon the Lord in distress: the Lord answered me, and set me in a large place.
^6The Lord is on my side; I will not fear: what can man do unto me?
^7The Lord taketh my part with them that help me: therefore shall I see my desire upon them that hate me.
^8It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in man.
^9It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in princes.
^10All nations compassed me about: but in the name of the Lord will I destroy them.
^11They compassed me about; yea, they compassed me about: but in the name of the Lord I will destroy them.
^12They compassed me about like bees: they are quenched as the fire of thorns: for in the name of the Lord I will destroy them.
^13Thou hast thrust sore at me that I might fall: but the Lord helped me.
^14The Lord is my strength and song, and is become my salvation.
^15The voice of rejoicing and salvation is in the tabernacles of the righteous: the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
^16The right hand of the Lord is exalted: the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly.
^17I shall not die, but live, and declare the works of the Lord.
^18The Lord hath chastened me sore: but he hath not given me over unto death.
^19Open to me the gates of righteousness: I will go into them, and I will praise the Lord:
^20This gate of the Lord, into which the righteous shall enter.
^21I will praise thee: for thou hast heard me, and art become my salvation.
^22The stone which the builders refused is become the head stone of the corner.
^23This is the Lord’s doing; it is marvellous in our eyes.
^24This is the day which the Lord hath made; we will rejoice and be glad in it.
^25Save now, I beseech thee, O Lord: O Lord, I beseech thee, send now prosperity.
^26Blessed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord: we have blessed you out of the house of the Lord.
^27God is the Lord, which hath shewed us light: bind the sacrifice with cords, even unto the horns of the altar.
^28Thou art my God, and I will praise thee: thou art my God, I will exalt thee.
^29O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.

CXIX

^1Blessed are the undefiled in the way, who walk in the law of the Lord.
^2Blessed are they that keep his testimonies, and that seek him with the whole heart.
^3They also do no iniquity: they walk in his ways.
^4Thou hast commanded us to keep thy precepts diligently.
^5O that my ways were directed to keep thy statutes!
^6Then shall I not be ashamed, when I have respect unto all thy commandments.
^7I will praise thee with uprightness of heart, when I shall have learned thy righteous judgments.
^8I will keep thy statutes: O forsake me not utterly.
^9Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way? by taking heed thereto according to thy word.
^10With my whole heart have I sought thee: O let me not wander from thy commandments.
^11Thy word have I hid in mine heart, that I might not sin against thee.
^12Blessed art thou, O Lord: teach me thy statutes.
^13With my lips have I declared all the judgments of thy mouth.
^14I have rejoiced in the way of thy testimonies, as much as in all riches.
^15I will meditate in thy precepts, and have respect unto thy ways.
^16I will delight myself in thy statutes: I will not forget thy word.
^17Deal bountifully with thy servant, that I may live, and keep thy word.
^18Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wondrous things out of thy law.
^19I am a stranger in the earth: hide not thy commandments from me.
^20My soul breaketh for the longing that it hath unto thy judgments at all times.
^21Thou hast rebuked the proud that are cursed, which do err from thy commandments.
^22Remove from me reproach and contempt; for I have kept thy testimonies.
^23Princes also did sit and speak against me: but thy servant did meditate in thy statutes.
^24Thy testimonies also are my delight and my counsellors.
^25My soul cleaveth unto the dust: quicken thou me according to thy word.
^26I have declared my ways, and thou heardest me: teach me thy statutes.
^27Make me to understand the way of thy precepts: so shall I talk of thy wondrous works.
^28My soul melteth for heaviness: strengthen thou me according unto thy word.
^29Remove from me the way of lying: and grant me thy law graciously.
^30I have chosen the way of truth: thy judgments have I laid before me.
^31I have stuck unto thy testimonies: O Lord, put me not to shame.
^32I will run the way of thy commandments, when thou shalt enlarge my heart.
^33Teach me, O Lord, the way of thy statutes; and I shall keep it unto the end.
^34Give me understanding, and I shall keep thy law; yea, I shall observe it with my whole heart.
^35Make me to go in the path of thy commandments; for therein do I delight.
^36Incline my heart unto thy testimonies, and not to covetousness.
^37Turn away mine eyes from beholding vanity; and quicken thou me in thy way.
^38Stablish thy word unto thy servant, who is devoted to thy fear.
^39Turn away my reproach which I fear: for thy judgments are good.
^40Behold, I have longed after thy precepts: quicken me in thy righteousness.
^41Let thy mercies come also unto me, O Lord, even thy salvation, according to thy word.
^42So shall I have wherewith to answer him that reproacheth me: for I trust in thy word.
^43And take not the word of truth utterly out of my mouth; for I have hoped in thy judgments.
^44So shall I keep thy law continually for ever and ever.
^45And I will walk at liberty: for I seek thy precepts.
^46I will speak of thy testimonies also before kings, and will not be ashamed.
^47And I will delight myself in thy commandments, which I have loved.
^48My hands also will I lift up unto thy commandments, which I have loved; and I will meditate in thy statutes.
^49Remember the word unto thy servant, upon which thou hast caused me to hope.
^50This is my comfort in my affliction: for thy word hath quickened me.
^51The proud have had me greatly in derision: yet have I not declined from thy law.
^52I remembered thy judgments of old, O Lord; and have comforted myself.
^53Horror hath taken hold upon me because of the wicked that forsake thy law.
^54Thy statutes have been my songs in the house of my pilgrimage.
^55I have remembered thy name, O Lord, in the night, and have kept thy law.
^56This I had, because I kept thy precepts.
^57Thou art my portion, O Lord: I have said that I would keep thy words.
^58I intreated thy favour with my whole heart: be merciful unto me according to thy word.
^59I thought on my ways, and turned my feet unto thy testimonies.
^60I made haste, and delayed not to keep thy commandments.
^61The bands of the wicked have robbed me: but I have not forgotten thy law.
^62At midnight I will rise to give thanks unto thee because of thy righteous judgments.
^63I am a companion of all them that fear thee, and of them that keep thy precepts.
^64The earth, O Lord, is full of thy mercy: teach me thy statutes.
^65Thou hast dealt well with thy servant, O Lord, according unto thy word.
^66Teach me good judgment and knowledge: for I have believed thy commandments.
^67Before I was afflicted I went astray: but now have I kept thy word.
^68Thou art good, and doest good; teach me thy statutes.
^69The proud have forged a lie against me: but I will keep thy precepts with my whole heart.
^70Their heart is as fat as grease; but I delight in thy law.
^71It is good for me that I have been afflicted; that I might learn thy statutes.
^72The law of thy mouth is better unto me than thousands of gold and silver.
^73Thy hands have made me and fashioned me: give me understanding, that I may learn thy commandments.
^74They that fear thee will be glad when they see me; because I have hoped in thy word.
^75I know, O Lord, that thy judgments are right, and that thou in faithfulness hast afflicted me.
^76Let, I pray thee, thy merciful kindness be for my comfort, according to thy word unto thy servant.
^77Let thy tender mercies come unto me, that I may live: for thy law is my delight.
^78Let the proud be ashamed; for they dealt perversely with me without a cause: but I will meditate in thy precepts.
^79Let those that fear thee turn unto me, and those that have known thy testimonies.
^80Let my heart be sound in thy statutes; that I be not ashamed.
^81My soul fainteth for thy salvation: but I hope in thy word.
^82Mine eyes fail for thy word, saying, When wilt thou comfort me?
^83For I am become like a bottle in the smoke; yet do I not forget thy statutes.
^84How many are the days of thy servant? when wilt thou execute judgment on them that persecute me?
^85The proud have digged pits for me, which are not after thy law.
^86All thy commandments are faithful: they persecute me wrongfully; help thou me.
^87They had almost consumed me upon earth; but I forsook not thy precepts.
^88Quicken me after thy lovingkindness; so shall I keep the testimony of thy mouth.
^89For ever, O Lord, thy word is settled in heaven.
^90Thy faithfulness is unto all generations: thou hast established the earth, and it abideth.
^91They continue this day according to thine ordinances: for all are thy servants.
^92Unless thy law had been my delights, I should then have perished in mine affliction.
^93I will never forget thy precepts: for with them thou hast quickened me.
^94I am thine, save me: for I have sought thy precepts.
^95The wicked have waited for me to destroy me: but I will consider thy testimonies.
^96I have seen an end of all perfection: but thy commandment is exceeding broad.
^97O how I love thy law! it is my meditation all the day.
^98Thou through thy commandments hast made me wiser than mine enemies: for they are ever with me.
^99I have more understanding than all my teachers: for thy testimonies are my meditation.
^100I understand more than the ancients, because I keep thy precepts.
^101I have refrained my feet from every evil way, that I might keep thy word.
^102I have not departed from thy judgments: for thou hast taught me.
^103How sweet are thy words unto my taste! yea, sweeter than honey to my mouth!
^104Through thy precepts I get understanding: therefore I hate every false way.
^105Thy word is a lamp unto my feet, and a light unto my path.
^106I have sworn, and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous judgments.
^107I am afflicted very much: quicken me, O Lord, according unto thy word.
^108Accept, I beseech thee, the freewill offerings of my mouth, O Lord, and teach me thy judgments.
^109My soul is continually in my hand: yet do I not forget thy law.
^110The wicked have laid a snare for me: yet I erred not from thy precepts.
^111Thy testimonies have I taken as an heritage for ever: for they are the rejoicing of my heart.
^112I have inclined mine heart to perform thy statutes alway, even unto the end.
^113I hate vain thoughts: but thy law do I love.
^114Thou art my hiding place and my shield: I hope in thy word.
^115Depart from me, ye evildoers: for I will keep the commandments of my God.
^116Uphold me according unto thy word, that I may live: and let me not be ashamed of my hope.
^117Hold thou me up, and I shall be safe: and I will have respect unto thy statutes continually.
^118Thou hast trodden down all them that err from thy statutes: for their deceit is falsehood.
^119Thou puttest away all the wicked of the earth like dross: therefore I love thy testimonies.
^120My flesh trembleth for fear of thee; and I am afraid of thy judgments.
^121I have done judgment and justice: leave me not to mine oppressors.
^122Be surety for thy servant for good: let not the proud oppress me.
^123Mine eyes fail for thy salvation, and for the word of thy righteousness.
^124Deal with thy servant according unto thy mercy, and teach me thy statutes.
^125I am thy servant; give me understanding, that I may know thy testimonies.
^126It is time for thee, Lord, to work: for they have made void thy law.
^127Therefore I love thy commandments above gold; yea, above fine gold.
^128Therefore I esteem all thy precepts concerning all things to be right; and I hate every false way.
^129Thy testimonies are wonderful: therefore doth my soul keep them.
^130The entrance of thy words giveth light; it giveth understanding unto the simple.
^131I opened my mouth, and panted: for I longed for thy commandments.
^132Look thou upon me, and be merciful unto me, as thou usest to do unto those that love thy name.
^133Order my steps in thy word: and let not any iniquity have dominion over me.
^134Deliver me from the oppression of man: so will I keep thy precepts.
^135Make thy face to shine upon thy servant; and teach me thy statutes.
^136Rivers of waters run down mine eyes, because they keep not thy law.
^137Righteous art thou, O Lord, and upright are thy judgments.
^138Thy testimonies that thou hast commanded are righteous and very faithful.
^139My zeal hath consumed me, because mine enemies have forgotten thy words.
^140Thy word is very pure: therefore thy servant loveth it.
^141I am small and despised: yet do not I forget thy precepts.
^142Thy righteousness is an everlasting righteousness, and thy law is the truth.
^143Trouble and anguish have taken hold on me: yet thy commandments are my delights.
^144The righteousness of thy testimonies is everlasting: give me understanding, and I shall live.
^145I cried with my whole heart; hear me, O Lord: I will keep thy statutes.
^146I cried unto thee; save me, and I shall keep thy testimonies.
^147I prevented the dawning of the morning, and cried: I hoped in thy word.
^148Mine eyes prevent the night watches, that I might meditate in thy word.
^149Hear my voice according unto thy lovingkindness: O Lord, quicken me according to thy judgment.
^150They draw nigh that follow after mischief: they are far from thy law.
^151Thou art near, O Lord; and all thy commandments are truth.
^152Concerning thy testimonies, I have known of old that thou hast founded them for ever.
^153Consider mine affliction, and deliver me: for I do not forget thy law.
^154Plead my cause, and deliver me: quicken me according to thy word.
^155Salvation is far from the wicked: for they seek not thy statutes.
^156Great are thy tender mercies, O Lord: quicken me according to thy judgments.
^157Many are my persecutors and mine enemies; yet do I not decline from thy testimonies.
^158I beheld the transgressors, and was grieved; because they kept not thy word.
^159Consider how I love thy precepts: quicken me, O Lord, according to thy lovingkindness.
^160Thy word is true from the beginning: and every one of thy righteous judgments endureth for ever.
^161Princes have persecuted me without a cause: but my heart standeth in awe of thy word.
^162I rejoice at thy word, as one that findeth great spoil.
^163I hate and abhor lying: but thy law do I love.
^164Seven times a day do I praise thee because of thy righteous judgments.
^165Great peace have they which love thy law: and nothing shall offend them.
^166Lord, I have hoped for thy salvation, and done thy commandments.
^167My soul hath kept thy testimonies; and I love them exceedingly.
^168I have kept thy precepts and thy testimonies: for all my ways are before thee.
^169Let my cry come near before thee, O Lord: give me understanding according to thy word.
^170Let my supplication come before thee: deliver me according to thy word.
^171My lips shall utter praise, when thou hast taught me thy statutes.
^172My tongue shall speak of thy word: for all thy commandments are righteousness.
^173Let thine hand help me; for I have chosen thy precepts.
^174I have longed for thy salvation, O Lord; and thy law is my delight.
^175Let my soul live, and it shall praise thee; and let thy judgments help me.
^176I have gone astray like a lost sheep; seek thy servant; for I do not forget thy commandments.

CXX

^1In my distress I cried unto the Lord, and he heard me.
^2Deliver my soul, O Lord, from lying lips, and from a deceitful tongue.
^3What shall be given unto thee? or what shall be done unto thee, thou false tongue?
^4Sharp arrows of the mighty, with coals of juniper.
^5Woe is me, that I sojourn in Mesech, that I dwell in the tents of Kedar!
^6My soul hath long dwelt with him that hateth peace.
^7I am for peace: but when I speak, they are for war.

CXXI

^1I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills, from whence cometh my help.
^2My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth.
^3He will not suffer thy foot to be moved: he that keepeth thee will not slumber.
^4Behold, he that keepeth Israel shall neither slumber nor sleep.
^5The Lord is thy keeper: the Lord is thy shade upon thy right hand.
^6The sun shall not smite thee by day, nor the moon by night.
^7The Lord shall preserve thee from all evil: he shall preserve thy soul.
^8The Lord shall preserve thy going out and thy coming in from this time forth, and even for evermore.

CXXII

^1I was glad when they said unto me, Let us go into the house of the Lord.
^2Our feet shall stand within thy gates, O Jerusalem.
^3Jerusalem is builded as a city that is compact together:
^4Whither the tribes go up, the tribes of the Lord, unto the testimony of Israel, to give thanks unto the name of the Lord.
^5For there are set thrones of judgment, the thrones of the house of David.
^6Pray for the peace of Jerusalem: they shall prosper that love thee.
^7Peace be within thy walls, and prosperity within thy palaces.
^8For my brethren and companions’ sakes, I will now say, Peace be within thee.
^9Because of the house of the Lord our God I will seek thy good.

CXXIII

^1Unto thee lift I up mine eyes, O thou that dwellest in the heavens.
^2Behold, as the eyes of servants look unto the hand of their masters, and as the eyes of a maiden unto the hand of her mistress; so our eyes wait upon the Lord our God, until that he have mercy upon us.
^3Have mercy upon us, O Lord, have mercy upon us: for we are exceedingly filled with contempt.
^4Our soul is exceedingly filled with the scorning of those that are at ease, and with the contempt of the proud.

CXXIV

^1If it had not been the Lord who was on our side, now may Israel say;
^2If it had not been the Lord who was on our side, when men rose up against us:
^3Then they had swallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled against us:
^4Then the waters had overwhelmed us, the stream had gone over our soul:
^5Then the proud waters had gone over our soul.
^6Blessed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a prey to their teeth.
^7Our soul is escaped as a bird out of the snare of the fowlers: the snare is broken, and we are escaped.
^8Our help is in the name of the Lord, who made heaven and earth.

CXXV

^1They that trust in the Lord shall be as mount Zion, which cannot be removed, but abideth for ever.
^2As the mountains are round about Jerusalem, so the Lord is round about his people from henceforth even for ever.
^3For the rod of the wicked shall not rest upon the lot of the righteous; lest the righteous put forth their hands unto iniquity.
^4Do good, O Lord, unto those that be good, and to them that are upright in their hearts.
^5As for such as turn aside unto their crooked ways, the Lord shall lead them forth with the workers of iniquity: but peace shall be upon Israel.

CXXVI

^1When the Lord turned again the captivity of Zion, we were like them that dream.
^2Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with singing: then said they among the heathen, The Lord hath done great things for them.
^3The Lord hath done great things for us; whereof we are glad.
^4Turn again our captivity, O Lord, as the streams in the south.
^5They that sow in tears shall reap in joy.
^6He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious seed, shall doubtless come again with rejoicing, bringing his sheaves with him.

CXXVII

^1Except the Lord build the house, they labour in vain that build it: except the Lord keep the city, the watchman waketh but in vain.
^2It is vain for you to rise up early, to sit up late, to eat the bread of sorrows: for so he giveth his beloved sleep.
^3Lo, children are an heritage of the Lord: and the fruit of the womb is his reward.
^4As arrows are in the hand of a mighty man; so are children of the youth.
^5Happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them: they shall not be ashamed, but they shall speak with the enemies in the gate.

CXXVIII

^1Blessed is every one that feareth the Lord; that walketh in his ways.
^2For thou shalt eat the labour of thine hands: happy shalt thou be, and it shall be well with thee.
^3Thy wife shall be as a fruitful vine by the sides of thine house: thy children like olive plants round about thy table.
^4Behold, that thus shall the man be blessed that feareth the Lord.
^5The Lord shall bless thee out of Zion: and thou shalt see the good of Jerusalem all the days of thy life.
^6Yea, thou shalt see thy children’s children, and peace upon Israel.

CXXIX

^1Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth, may Israel now say:
^2Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth: yet they have not prevailed against me.
^3The plowers plowed upon my back: they made long their furrows.
^4The Lord is righteous: he hath cut asunder the cords of the wicked.
^5Let them all be confounded and turned back that hate Zion.
^6Let them be as the grass upon the housetops, which withereth afore it groweth up:
^7Wherewith the mower filleth not his hand; nor he that bindeth sheaves his bosom.
^8Neither do they which go by say, The blessing of the Lord be upon you: we bless you in the name of the Lord.

CXXX

^1Out of the depths have I cried unto thee, O Lord.
^2Lord, hear my voice: let thine ears be attentive to the voice of my supplications.
^3If thou, Lord, shouldest mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand?
^4But there is forgiveness with thee, that thou mayest be feared.
^5I wait for the Lord, my soul doth wait, and in his word do I hope.
^6My soul waiteth for the Lord more than they that watch for the morning: I say, more than they that watch for the morning.
^7Let Israel hope in the Lord: for with the Lord there is mercy, and with him is plenteous redemption.
^8And he shall redeem Israel from all his iniquities.

CXXXI

^1Lord, my heart is not haughty, nor mine eyes lofty: neither do I exercise myself in great matters, or in things too high for me.
^2Surely I have behaved and quieted myself, as a child that is weaned of his mother: my soul is even as a weaned child.
^3Let Israel hope in the Lord from henceforth and for ever.

CXXXII

^1Lord, remember David, and all his afflictions:
^2How he sware unto the Lord, and vowed unto the mighty God of Jacob;
^3Surely I will not come into the tabernacle of my house, nor go up into my bed;
^4I will not give sleep to mine eyes, or slumber to mine eyelids,
^5Until I find out a place for the Lord, an habitation for the mighty God of Jacob.
^6Lo, we heard of it at Ephratah: we found it in the fields of the wood.
^7We will go into his tabernacles: we will worship at his footstool.
^8Arise, O Lord, into thy rest; thou, and the ark of thy strength.
^9Let thy priests be clothed with righteousness; and let thy saints shout for joy.
^10For thy servant David’s sake turn not away the face of thine anointed.
^11The Lord hath sworn in truth unto David; he will not turn from it; Of the fruit of thy body will I set upon thy throne.
^12If thy children will keep my covenant and my testimony that I shall teach them, their children shall also sit upon thy throne for evermore.
^13For the Lord hath chosen Zion; he hath desired it for his habitation.
^14This is my rest for ever: here will I dwell; for I have desired it.
^15I will abundantly bless her provision: I will satisfy her poor with bread.
^16I will also clothe her priests with salvation: and her saints shall shout aloud for joy.
^17There will I make the horn of David to bud: I have ordained a lamp for mine anointed.
^18His enemies will I clothe with shame: but upon himself shall his crown flourish.

CXXXIII

^1Behold, how good and how pleasant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity!
^2It is like the precious ointment upon the head, that ran down upon the beard, even Aaron’s beard: that went down to the skirts of his garments;
^3As the dew of Hermon, and as the dew that descended upon the mountains of Zion: for there the Lord commanded the blessing, even life for evermore.

CXXXIV

^1Behold, bless ye the Lord, all ye servants of the Lord, which by night stand in the house of the Lord.
^2Lift up your hands in the sanctuary, and bless the Lord.
^3The Lord that made heaven and earth bless thee out of Zion.

CXXXV

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise ye the name of the Lord; praise him, O ye servants of the Lord.
^2Ye that stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God.
^3Praise the Lord; for the Lord is good: sing praises unto his name; for it is pleasant.
^4For the Lord hath chosen Jacob unto himself, and Israel for his peculiar treasure.
^5For I know that the Lord is great, and that our Lord is above all gods.
^6Whatsoever the Lord pleased, that did he in heaven, and in earth, in the seas, and all deep places.
^7He causeth the vapours to ascend from the ends of the earth; he maketh lightnings for the rain; he bringeth the wind out of his treasuries.
^8Who smote the firstborn of Egypt, both of man and beast.
^9Who sent tokens and wonders into the midst of thee, O Egypt, upon Pharaoh, and upon all his servants.
^10Who smote great nations, and slew mighty kings;
^11Sihon king of the Amorites, and Og king of Bashan, and all the kingdoms of Canaan:
^12And gave their land for an heritage, an heritage unto Israel his people.
^13Thy name, O Lord, endureth for ever; and thy memorial, O Lord, throughout all generations.
^14For the Lord will judge his people, and he will repent himself concerning his servants.
^15The idols of the heathen are silver and gold, the work of men’s hands.
^16They have mouths, but they speak not; eyes have they, but they see not;
^17They have ears, but they hear not; neither is there any breath in their mouths.
^18They that make them are like unto them: so is every one that trusteth in them.
^19Bless the Lord, O house of Israel: bless the Lord, O house of Aaron:
^20Bless the Lord, O house of Levi: ye that fear the Lord, bless the Lord.
^21Blessed be the Lord out of Zion, which dwelleth at Jerusalem. Praise ye the Lord.

CXXXVI

^1O give thanks unto the Lord; for he is good: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^2O give thanks unto the God of gods: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^3O give thanks to the Lord of lords: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^4To him who alone doeth great wonders: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^5To him that by wisdom made the heavens: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^6To him that stretched out the earth above the waters: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^7To him that made great lights: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^8The sun to rule by day: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^9The moon and stars to rule by night: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^10To him that smote Egypt in their firstborn: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^11And brought out Israel from among them: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^12With a strong hand, and with a stretched out arm: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^13To him which divided the Red sea into parts: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^14And made Israel to pass through the midst of it: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^15But overthrew Pharaoh and his host in the Red sea: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^16To him which led his people through the wilderness: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^17To him which smote great kings: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^18And slew famous kings: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^19Sihon king of the Amorites: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^20And Og the king of Bashan: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^21And gave their land for an heritage: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^22Even an heritage unto Israel his servant: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^23Who remembered us in our low estate: for his mercy endureth for ever:
^24And hath redeemed us from our enemies: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^25Who giveth food to all flesh: for his mercy endureth for ever.
^26O give thanks unto the God of heaven: for his mercy endureth for ever.

CXXXVII

^1By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat down, yea, we wept, when we remembered Zion.
^2We hanged our harps upon the willows in the midst thereof.
^3For there they that carried us away captive required of us a song; and they that wasted us required of us mirth, saying, Sing us one of the songs of Zion.
^4How shall we sing the Lord’s song in a strange land?
^5If I forget thee, O Jerusalem, let my right hand forget her cunning.
^6If I do not remember thee, let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth; if I prefer not Jerusalem above my chief joy.
^7Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem; who said, Rase it, rase it, even to the foundation thereof.
^8O daughter of Babylon, who art to be destroyed; happy shall he be, that rewardeth thee as thou hast served us.
^9Happy shall he be, that taketh and dasheth thy little ones against the stones.

CXXXVIII

^1I will praise thee with my whole heart: before the gods will I sing praise unto thee.
^2I will worship toward thy holy temple, and praise thy name for thy lovingkindness and for thy truth: for thou hast magnified thy word above all thy name.
^3In the day when I cried thou answeredst me, and strengthenedst me with strength in my soul.
^4All the kings of the earth shall praise thee, O Lord, when they hear the words of thy mouth.
^5Yea, they shall sing in the ways of the Lord: for great is the glory of the Lord.
^6Though the Lord be high, yet hath he respect unto the lowly: but the proud he knoweth afar off.
^7Though I walk in the midst of trouble, thou wilt revive me: thou shalt stretch forth thine hand against the wrath of mine enemies, and thy right hand shall save me.
^8The Lord will perfect that which concerneth me: thy mercy, O Lord, endureth for ever: forsake not the works of thine own hands.

CXXXIX

^1O lord, thou hast searched me, and known me.
^2Thou knowest my downsitting and mine uprising, thou understandest my thought afar off.
^3Thou compassest my path and my lying down, and art acquainted with all my ways.
^4For there is not a word in my tongue, but, lo, O Lord, thou knowest it altogether.
^5Thou hast beset me behind and before, and laid thine hand upon me.
^6Such knowledge is too wonderful for me; it is high, I cannot attain unto it.
^7Whither shall I go from thy spirit? or whither shall I flee from thy presence?
^8If I ascend up into heaven, thou art there: if I make my bed in hell, behold, thou art there.
^9If I take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermost parts of the sea;
^10Even there shall thy hand lead me, and thy right hand shall hold me.
^11If I say, Surely the darkness shall cover me; even the night shall be light about me.
^12Yea, the darkness hideth not from thee; but the night shineth as the day: the darkness and the light are both alike to thee.
^13For thou hast possessed my reins: thou hast covered me in my mother’s womb.
^14I will praise thee; for I am fearfully and wonderfully made: marvellous are thy works; and that my soul knoweth right well.
^15My substance was not hid from thee, when I was made in secret, and curiously wrought in the lowest parts of the earth.
^16Thine eyes did see my substance, yet being unperfect; and in thy book all my members were written, which in continuance were fashioned, when as yet there was none of them.
^17How precious also are thy thoughts unto me, O God! how great is the sum of them!
^18If I should count them, they are more in number than the sand: when I awake, I am still with thee.
^19Surely thou wilt slay the wicked, O God: depart from me therefore, ye bloody men.
^20For they speak against thee wickedly, and thine enemies take thy name in vain.
^21Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? and am not I grieved with those that rise up against thee?
^22I hate them with perfect hatred: I count them mine enemies.
^23Search me, O God, and know my heart: try me, and know my thoughts:
^24And see if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlasting.

CXL

^1Deliver me, O Lord, from the evil man: preserve me from the violent man;
^2Which imagine mischiefs in their heart; continually are they gathered together for war.
^3They have sharpened their tongues like a serpent; adders’ poison is under their lips.
Selah.
^4Keep me, O Lord, from the hands of the wicked; preserve me from the violent man; who have purposed to overthrow my goings.
^5The proud have hid a snare for me, and cords; they have spread a net by the wayside; they have set gins for me.
Selah.
^6I said unto the Lord, Thou art my God: hear the voice of my supplications, O Lord.
^7O God the Lord, the strength of my salvation, thou hast covered my head in the day of battle.
^8Grant not, O Lord, the desires of the wicked: further not his wicked device; lest they exalt themselves.
Selah.
^9As for the head of those that compass me about, let the mischief of their own lips cover them.
^10Let burning coals fall upon them: let them be cast into the fire; into deep pits, that they rise not up again.
^11Let not an evil speaker be established in the earth: evil shall hunt the violent man to overthrow him.
^12I know that the Lord will maintain the cause of the afflicted, and the right of the poor.
^13Surely the righteous shall give thanks unto thy name: the upright shall dwell in thy presence.

CXLI

^1Lord, I cry unto thee: make haste unto me; give ear unto my voice, when I cry unto thee.
^2Let my prayer be set forth before thee as incense; and the lifting up of my hands as the evening sacrifice.
^3Set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth; keep the door of my lips.
^4Incline not my heart to any evil thing, to practise wicked works with men that work iniquity: and let me not eat of their dainties.
^5Let the righteous smite me; it shall be a kindness: and let him reprove me; it shall be an excellent oil, which shall not break my head: for yet my prayer also shall be in their calamities.
^6When their judges are overthrown in stony places, they shall hear my words; for they are sweet.
^7Our bones are scattered at the grave’s mouth, as when one cutteth and cleaveth wood upon the earth.
^8But mine eyes are unto thee, O God the Lord: in thee is my trust; leave not my soul destitute.
^9Keep me from the snares which they have laid for me, and the gins of the workers of iniquity.
^10Let the wicked fall into their own nets, whilst that I withal escape.

CXLII

^1I cried unto the Lord with my voice; with my voice unto the Lord did I make my supplication.
^2I poured out my complaint before him; I shewed before him my trouble.
^3When my spirit was overwhelmed within me, then thou knewest my path. In the way wherein I walked have they privily laid a snare for me.
^4I looked on my right hand, and beheld, but there was no man that would know me: refuge failed me; no man cared for my soul.
^5I cried unto thee, O Lord: I said, Thou art my refuge and my portion in the land of the living.
^6Attend unto my cry; for I am brought very low: deliver me from my persecutors; for they are stronger than I.
^7Bring my soul out of prison, that I may praise thy name: the righteous shall compass me about; for thou shalt deal bountifully with me.

CXLIII

^1Hear my prayer, O Lord, give ear to my supplications: in thy faithfulness answer me, and in thy righteousness.
^2And enter not into judgment with thy servant: for in thy sight shall no man living be justified.
^3For the enemy hath persecuted my soul; he hath smitten my life down to the ground; he hath made me to dwell in darkness, as those that have been long dead.
^4Therefore is my spirit overwhelmed within me; my heart within me is desolate.
^5I remember the days of old; I meditate on all thy works; I muse on the work of thy hands.
^6I stretch forth my hands unto thee: my soul thirsteth after thee, as a thirsty land.
Selah.
^7Hear me speedily, O Lord: my spirit faileth: hide not thy face from me, lest I be like unto them that go down into the pit.
^8Cause me to hear thy lovingkindness in the morning; for in thee do I trust: cause me to know the way wherein I should walk; for I lift up my soul unto thee.
^9Deliver me, O Lord, from mine enemies: I flee unto thee to hide me.
^10Teach me to do thy will; for thou art my God: thy spirit is good; lead me into the land of uprightness.
^11Quicken me, O Lord, for thy name’s sake: for thy righteousness’ sake bring my soul out of trouble.
^12And of thy mercy cut off mine enemies, and destroy all them that afflict my soul: for I am thy servant.

CXLIV

^1Blessed be the Lord my strength which teacheth my hands to war, and my fingers to fight:
^2My goodness, and my fortress; my high tower, and my deliverer; my shield, and he in whom I trust; who subdueth my people under me.
^3Lord, what is man, that thou takest knowledge of him! or the son of man, that thou makest account of him!
^4Man is like to vanity: his days are as a shadow that passeth away.
^5Bow thy heavens, O Lord, and come down: touch the mountains, and they shall smoke.
^6Cast forth lightning, and scatter them: shoot out thine arrows, and destroy them.
^7Send thine hand from above; rid me, and deliver me out of great waters, from the hand of strange children;
^8Whose mouth speaketh vanity, and their right hand is a right hand of falsehood.
^9I will sing a new song unto thee, O God: upon a psaltery and an instrument of ten strings will I sing praises unto thee.
^10It is he that giveth salvation unto kings: who delivereth David his servant from the hurtful sword.
^11Rid me, and deliver me from the hand of strange children, whose mouth speaketh vanity, and their right hand is a right hand of falsehood:
^12That our sons may be as plants grown up in their youth; that our daughters may be as corner stones, polished after the similitude of a palace:
^13That our garners may be full, affording all manner of store: that our sheep may bring forth thousands and ten thousands in our streets:
^14That our oxen may be strong to labour; that there be no breaking in, nor going out; that there be no complaining in our streets.
^15Happy is that people, that is in such a case: yea, happy is that people, whose God is the Lord.

CXLV

^1I will extol thee, my God, O king; and I will bless thy name for ever and ever.
^2Every day will I bless thee; and I will praise thy name for ever and ever.
^3Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised; and his greatness is unsearchable.
^4One generation shall praise thy works to another, and shall declare thy mighty acts.
^5I will speak of the glorious honour of thy majesty, and of thy wondrous works.
^6And men shall speak of the might of thy terrible acts: and I will declare thy greatness.
^7They shall abundantly utter the memory of thy great goodness, and shall sing of thy righteousness.
^8The Lord is gracious, and full of compassion; slow to anger, and of great mercy.
^9The Lord is good to all: and his tender mercies are over all his works.
^10All thy works shall praise thee, O Lord; and thy saints shall bless thee.
^11They shall speak of the glory of thy kingdom, and talk of thy power;
^12To make known to the sons of men his mighty acts, and the glorious majesty of his kingdom.
^13Thy kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and thy dominion endureth throughout all generations.
^14The Lord upholdeth all that fall, and raiseth up all those that be bowed down.
^15The eyes of all wait upon thee; and thou givest them their meat in due season.
^16Thou openest thine hand, and satisfiest the desire of every living thing.
^17The Lord is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works.
^18The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him, to all that call upon him in truth.
^19He will fulfil the desire of them that fear him: he also will hear their cry, and will save them.
^20The Lord preserveth all them that love him: but all the wicked will he destroy.
^21My mouth shall speak the praise of the Lord: and let all flesh bless his holy name for ever and ever.

CXLVI

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise the Lord, O my soul.
^2While I live will I praise the Lord: I will sing praises unto my God while I have any being.
^3Put not your trust in princes, nor in the son of man, in whom there is no help.
^4His breath goeth forth, he returneth to his earth; in that very day his thoughts perish.
^5Happy is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help, whose hope is in the Lord his God:
^6Which made heaven, and earth, the sea, and all that therein is: which keepeth truth for ever:
^7Which executeth judgment for the oppressed: which giveth food to the hungry. The Lord looseth the prisoners:
^8The Lord openeth the eyes of the blind: the Lord raiseth them that are bowed down: the Lord loveth the righteous:
^9The Lord preserveth the strangers; he relieveth the fatherless and widow: but the way of the wicked he turneth upside down.
^10The Lord shall reign for ever, even thy God, O Zion, unto all generations. Praise ye the Lord.

CXLVII

^1Praise ye the Lord: for it is good to sing praises unto our God; for it is pleasant; and praise is comely.
^2The Lord doth build up Jerusalem: he gathereth together the outcasts of Israel.
^3He healeth the broken in heart, and bindeth up their wounds.
^4He telleth the number of the stars; he calleth them all by their names.
^5Great is our Lord, and of great power: his understanding is infinite.
^6The Lord lifteth up the meek: he casteth the wicked down to the ground.
^7Sing unto the Lord with thanksgiving; sing praise upon the harp unto our God:
^8Who covereth the heaven with clouds, who prepareth rain for the earth, who maketh grass to grow upon the mountains.
^9He giveth to the beast his food, and to the young ravens which cry.
^10He delighteth not in the strength of the horse: he taketh not pleasure in the legs of a man.
^11The Lord taketh pleasure in them that fear him, in those that hope in his mercy.
^12Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem; praise thy God, O Zion.
^13For he hath strengthened the bars of thy gates; he hath blessed thy children within thee.
^14He maketh peace in thy borders, and filleth thee with the finest of the wheat.
^15He sendeth forth his commandment upon earth: his word runneth very swiftly.
^16He giveth snow like wool: he scattereth the hoarfrost like ashes.
^17He casteth forth his ice like morsels: who can stand before his cold?
^18He sendeth out his word, and melteth them: he causeth his wind to blow, and the waters flow.
^19He sheweth his word unto Jacob, his statutes and his judgments unto Israel.
^20He hath not dealt so with any nation: and as for his judgments, they have not known them. Praise ye the Lord.

CXLVIII

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise ye the Lord from the heavens: praise him in the heights.
^2Praise ye him, all his angels: praise ye him, all his hosts.
^3Praise ye him, sun and moon: praise him, all ye stars of light.
^4Praise him, ye heavens of heavens, and ye waters that be above the heavens.
^5Let them praise the name of the Lord: for he commanded, and they were created.
^6He hath also stablished them for ever and ever: he hath made a decree which shall not pass.
^7Praise the Lord from the earth, ye dragons, and all deeps:
^8Fire, and hail; snow, and vapours; stormy wind fulfilling his word:
^9Mountains, and all hills; fruitful trees, and all cedars:
^10Beasts, and all cattle; creeping things, and flying fowl:
^11Kings of the earth, and all people; princes, and all judges of the earth:
^12Both young men, and maidens; old men, and children:
^13Let them praise the name of the Lord: for his name alone is excellent; his glory is above the earth and heaven.
^14He also exalteth the horn of his people, the praise of all his saints; even of the children of Israel, a people near unto him. Praise ye the Lord.

CXLIX

^1Praise ye the Lord. Sing unto the Lord a new song, and his praise in the congregation of saints.
^2Let Israel rejoice in him that made him: let the children of Zion be joyful in their King.
^3Let them praise his name in the dance: let them sing praises unto him with the timbrel and harp.
^4For the Lord taketh pleasure in his people: he will beautify the meek with salvation.
^5Let the saints be joyful in glory: let them sing aloud upon their beds.
^6Let the high praises of God be in their mouth, and a two-edged sword in their hand;
^7To execute vengeance upon the heathen, and punishments upon the people;
^8To bind their kings with chains, and their nobles with fetters of iron;
^9To execute upon them the judgment written: this honour have all his saints. Praise ye the Lord.

CL

^1Praise ye the Lord. Praise God in his sanctuary: praise him in the firmament of his power.
^2Praise him for his mighty acts: praise him according to his excellent greatness.
^3Praise him with the sound of the trumpet: praise him with the psaltery and harp.
^4Praise him with the timbrel and dance: praise him with stringed instruments and organs.
^5Praise him upon the loud cymbals: praise him upon the high sounding cymbals.
^6Let every thing that hath breath praise the Lord. Praise ye the Lord.

Proverbs

The Book of

Proverbs

I

^1The proverbs of Solomon the son of David, king of Israel;

^2To know wisdom and instruction; to perceive the words of understanding;

^3To receive the instruction of wisdom, justice, and judgment, and equity;

^4To give subtilty to the simple, to the young man knowledge and discretion.

^5A wise man will hear, and will increase learning; and a man of understanding shall attain unto wise counsels:

^6To understand a proverb, and the interpretation; the words of the wise, and their dark sayings.

^7The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge: but fools despise wisdom and instruction.

^8My son, hear the instruction of thy father, and forsake not the law of thy mother:

^9For they shall be an ornament of grace unto thy head, and chains about thy neck.

^10My son, if sinners entice thee, consent thou not.

^11If they say, Come with us, let us lay wait for blood, let us lurk privily for the innocent without cause:

^12Let us swallow them up alive as the grave; and whole, as those that go down into the pit:

^13We shall find all precious substance, we shall fill our houses with spoil:

^14Cast in thy lot among us; let us all have one purse:

^15My son, walk not thou in the way with them; refrain thy foot from their path:

^16For their feet run to evil, and make haste to shed blood.

^17Surely in vain the net is spread in the sight of any bird.

^18And they lay wait for their own blood; they lurk privily for their own lives.

^19So are the ways of every one that is greedy of gain; which taketh away the life of the owners thereof.

^20Wisdom crieth without; she uttereth her voice in the streets:

^21She crieth in the chief place of concourse, in the openings of the gates: in the city she uttereth her words, saying,

^22How long, ye simple ones, will ye love simplicity? and the scorners delight in their scorning, and fools hate knowledge?

^23Turn you at my reproof: behold, I will pour out my spirit unto you, I will make known my words unto you.

^24Because I have called, and ye refused; I have stretched out my hand, and no man regarded;

^25But ye have set at nought all my counsel, and would none of my reproof:

^26I also will laugh at your calamity; I will mock when your fear cometh;

^27When your fear cometh as desolation, and your destruction cometh as a whirlwind; when distress and anguish cometh upon you.

^28Then shall they call upon me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me early, but they shall not find me:

^29For that they hated knowledge, and did not choose the fear of the Lord:

^30They would none of my counsel: they despised all my reproof.

^31Therefore shall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices.

^32For the turning away of the simple shall slay them, and the prosperity of fools shall destroy them.

^33But whoso hearkeneth unto me shall dwell safely, and shall be quiet from fear of evil.

II

^1My son, if thou wilt receive my words, and hide my commandments with thee;

^2So that thou incline thine ear unto wisdom, and apply thine heart to understanding;

^3Yea, if thou criest after knowledge, and liftest up thy voice for understanding;

^4If thou seekest her as silver, and searchest for her as for hid treasures;

^5Then shalt thou understand the fear of the Lord, and find the knowledge of God.

^6For the Lord giveth wisdom: out of his mouth cometh knowledge and understanding.

^7He layeth up sound wisdom for the righteous: he is a buckler to them that walk uprightly.

^8He keepeth the paths of judgment, and preserveth the way of his saints.

^9Then shalt thou understand righteousness, and judgment, and equity; yea, every good path.

^10When wisdom entereth into thine heart, and knowledge is pleasant unto thy soul;

^11Discretion shall preserve thee, understanding shall keep thee:

^12To deliver thee from the way of the evil man, from the man that speaketh froward things;

^13Who leave the paths of uprightness, to walk in the ways of darkness;

^14Who rejoice to do evil, and delight in the frowardness of the wicked;

^15Whose ways are crooked, and they froward in their paths:

^16To deliver thee from the strange woman, even from the stranger which flattereth with her words;

^17Which forsaketh the guide of her youth, and forgetteth the covenant of her God.

^18For her house inclineth unto death, and her paths unto the dead.

^19None that go unto her return again, neither take they hold of the paths of life.

^20That thou mayest walk in the way of good men, and keep the paths of the righteous.

^21For the upright shall dwell in the land, and the perfect shall remain in it.

^22But the wicked shall be cut off from the earth, and the transgressors shall be rooted out of it.

III

^1My son, forget not my law; but let thine heart keep my commandments:

^2For length of days, and long life, and peace, shall they add to thee.

^3Let not mercy and truth forsake thee: bind them about thy neck; write them upon the table of thine heart:

^4So shalt thou find favour and good understanding in the sight of God and man.

^5Trust in the Lord with all thine heart; and lean not unto thine own understanding.

^6In all thy ways acknowledge him, and he shall direct thy paths.

^7Be not wise in thine own eyes: fear the Lord, and depart from evil.

^8It shall be health to thy navel, and marrow to thy bones.

^9Honour the Lord with thy substance, and with the firstfruits of all thine increase:

^10So shall thy barns be filled with plenty, and thy presses shall burst out with new wine.

^11My son, despise not the chastening of the Lord; neither be weary of his correction:

^12For whom the Lord loveth he correcteth; even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.

^13Happy is the man that findeth wisdom, and the man that getteth understanding.

^14For the merchandise of it is better than the merchandise of silver, and the gain thereof than fine gold.

^15She is more precious than rubies: and all the things thou canst desire are not to be compared unto her.

^16Length of days is in her right hand; and in her left hand riches and honour.

^17Her ways are ways of pleasantness, and all her paths are peace.

^18She is a tree of life to them that lay hold upon her: and happy is every one that retaineth her.

^19The Lord by wisdom hath founded the earth; by understanding hath he established the heavens.

^20By his knowledge the depths are broken up, and the clouds drop down the dew.

^21My son, let not them depart from thine eyes: keep sound wisdom and discretion:

^22So shall they be life unto thy soul, and grace to thy neck.

^23Then shalt thou walk in thy way safely, and thy foot shall not stumble.

^24When thou liest down, thou shalt not be afraid: yea, thou shalt lie down, and thy sleep shall be sweet.

^25Be not afraid of sudden fear, neither of the desolation of the wicked, when it cometh.

^26For the Lord shall be thy confidence, and shall keep thy foot from being taken.

^27Withhold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to do it.

^28Say not unto thy neighbour, Go, and come again, and to morrow I will give; when thou hast it by thee.

^29Devise not evil against thy neighbour, seeing he dwelleth securely by thee.

^30Strive not with a man without cause, if he have done thee no harm.

^31Envy thou not the oppressor, and choose none of his ways.

^32For the froward is abomination to the Lord: but his secret is with the righteous.

^33The curse of the Lord is in the house of the wicked: but he blesseth the habitation of the just.

^34Surely he scorneth the scorners: but he giveth grace unto the lowly.

^35The wise shall inherit glory: but shame shall be the promotion of fools.

IV

^1Hear, ye children, the instruction of a father, and attend to know understanding.

^2For I give you good doctrine, forsake ye not my law.

^3For I was my father’s son, tender and only beloved in the sight of my mother.

^4He taught me also, and said unto me, Let thine heart retain my words: keep my commandments, and live.

^5Get wisdom, get understanding: forget it not; neither decline from the words of my mouth.

^6Forsake her not, and she shall preserve thee: love her, and she shall keep thee.

^7Wisdom is the principal thing; therefore get wisdom: and with all thy getting get understanding.

^8Exalt her, and she shall promote thee: she shall bring thee to honour, when thou dost embrace her.

^9She shall give to thine head an ornament of grace: a crown of glory shall she deliver to thee.

^10Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings; and the years of thy life shall be many.

^11I have taught thee in the way of wisdom; I have led thee in right paths.

^12When thou goest, thy steps shall not be straitened; and when thou runnest, thou shalt not stumble.

^13Take fast hold of instruction; let her not go: keep her; for she is thy life.

^14Enter not into the path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men.

^15Avoid it, pass not by it, turn from it, and pass away.

^16For they sleep not, except they have done mischief; and their sleep is taken away, unless they cause some to fall.

^17For they eat the bread of wickedness, and drink the wine of violence.

^18But the path of the just is as the shining light, that shineth more and more unto the perfect day.

^19The way of the wicked is as darkness: they know not at what they stumble.

^20My son, attend to my words; incline thine ear unto my sayings.

^21Let them not depart from thine eyes; keep them in the midst of thine heart.

^22For they are life unto those that find them, and health to all their flesh.

^23Keep thy heart with all diligence; for out of it are the issues of life.

^24Put away from thee a froward mouth, and perverse lips put far from thee.

^25Let thine eyes look right on, and let thine eyelids look straight before thee.

^26Ponder the path of thy feet, and let all thy ways be established.

^27Turn not to the right hand nor to the left: remove thy foot from evil.

V

^1My son, attend unto my wisdom, and bow thine ear to my understanding:

^2That thou mayest regard discretion, and that thy lips may keep knowledge.

^3For the lips of a strange woman drop as an honeycomb, and her mouth is smoother than oil:

^4But her end is bitter as wormwood, sharp as a two-edged sword.

^5Her feet go down to death; her steps take hold on hell.

^6Lest thou shouldest ponder the path of life, her ways are moveable, that thou canst not know them.

^7Hear me now therefore, O ye children, and depart not from the words of my mouth.

^8Remove thy way far from her, and come not nigh the door of her house:

^9Lest thou give thine honour unto others, and thy years unto the cruel:

^10Lest strangers be filled with thy wealth; and thy labours be in the house of a stranger;

^11And thou mourn at the last, when thy flesh and thy body are consumed,

^12And say, How have I hated instruction, and my heart despised reproof;

^13And have not obeyed the voice of my teachers, nor inclined mine ear to them that instructed me!

^14I was almost in all evil in the midst of the congregation and assembly.

^15Drink waters out of thine own cistern, and running waters out of thine own well.

^16Let thy fountains be dispersed abroad, and rivers of waters in the streets.

^17Let them be only thine own, and not strangers’ with thee.

^18Let thy fountain be blessed: and rejoice with the wife of thy youth.

^19Let her be as the loving hind and pleasant roe; let her breasts satisfy thee at all times; and be thou ravished always with her love.

^20And why wilt thou, my son, be ravished with a strange woman, and embrace the bosom of a stranger?

^21For the ways of man are before the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his goings.

^22His own iniquities shall take the wicked himself, and he shall be holden with the cords of his sins.

^23He shall die without instruction; and in the greatness of his folly he shall go astray.

VI

^1My son, if thou be surety for thy friend, if thou hast stricken thy hand with a stranger,

^2Thou art snared with the words of thy mouth, thou art taken with the words of thy mouth.

^3Do this now, my son, and deliver thyself, when thou art come into the hand of thy friend; go, humble thyself, and make sure thy friend.

^4Give not sleep to thine eyes, nor slumber to thine eyelids.

^5Deliver thyself as a roe from the hand of the hunter, and as a bird from the hand of the fowler.

^6Go to the ant, thou sluggard; consider her ways, and be wise:

^7Which having no guide, overseer, or ruler,

^8Provideth her meat in the summer, and gathereth her food in the harvest.

^9How long wilt thou sleep, O sluggard? when wilt thou arise out of thy sleep?

^10Yet a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep:

^11So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth, and thy want as an armed man.

^12A naughty person, a wicked man, walketh with a froward mouth.

^13He winketh with his eyes, he speaketh with his feet, he teacheth with his fingers;

^14Frowardness is in his heart, he deviseth mischief continually; he soweth discord.

^15Therefore shall his calamity come suddenly; suddenly shall he be broken without remedy.

^16These six things doth the Lord hate: yea, seven are an abomination unto him:

^17A proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood,

^18An heart that deviseth wicked imaginations, feet that be swift in running to mischief,

^19A false witness that speaketh lies, and he that soweth discord among brethren.

^20My son, keep thy father’s commandment, and forsake not the law of thy mother:

^21Bind them continually upon thine heart, and tie them about thy neck.

^22When thou goest, it shall lead thee; when thou sleepest, it shall keep thee; and when thou awakest, it shall talk with thee.

^23For the commandment is a lamp; and the law is light; and reproofs of instruction are the way of life:

^24To keep thee from the evil woman, from the flattery of the tongue of a strange woman.

^25Lust not after her beauty in thine heart; neither let her take thee with her eyelids.

^26For by means of a whorish woman a man is brought to a piece of bread: and the adultress will hunt for the precious life.

^27Can a man take fire in his bosom, and his clothes not be burned?

^28Can one go upon hot coals, and his feet not be burned?

^29So he that goeth in to his neighbour’s wife; whosoever toucheth her shall not be innocent.

^30Men do not despise a thief, if he steal to satisfy his soul when he is hungry;

^31But if he be found, he shall restore sevenfold; he shall give all the substance of his house.

^32But whoso committeth adultery with a woman lacketh understanding: he that doeth it destroyeth his own soul.

^33A wound and dishonour shall he get; and his reproach shall not be wiped away.

^34For jealousy is the rage of a man: therefore he will not spare in the day of vengeance.

^35He will not regard any ransom; neither will he rest content, though thou givest many gifts.

VII

^1My son, keep my words, and lay up my commandments with thee.

^2Keep my commandments, and live; and my law as the apple of thine eye.

^3Bind them upon thy fingers, write them upon the table of thine heart.

^4Say unto wisdom, Thou art my sister; and call understanding thy kinswoman:

^5That they may keep thee from the strange woman, from the stranger which flattereth with her words.

^6For at the window of my house I looked through my casement,

^7And beheld among the simple ones, I discerned among the youths, a young man void of understanding,

^8Passing through the street near her corner; and he went the way to her house,

^9In the twilight, in the evening, in the black and dark night:

^10And, behold, there met him a woman with the attire of an harlot, and subtil of heart.

^11(She is loud and stubborn; her feet abide not in her house:

^12Now is she without, now in the streets, and lieth in wait at every corner.)

^13So she caught him, and kissed him, and with an impudent face said unto him,

^14I have peace offerings with me; this day have I payed my vows.

^15Therefore came I forth to meet thee, diligently to seek thy face, and I have found thee.

^16I have decked my bed with coverings of tapestry, with carved works, with fine linen of Egypt.

^17I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

^18Come, let us take our fill of love until the morning: let us solace ourselves with loves.

^19For the goodman is not at home, he is gone a long journey:

^20He hath taken a bag of money with him, and will come home at the day appointed.

^21With her much fair speech she caused him to yield, with the flattering of her lips she forced him.

^22He goeth after her straightway, as an ox goeth to the slaughter, or as a fool to the correction of the stocks;

^23Till a dart strike through his liver; as a bird hasteth to the snare, and knoweth not that it is for his life.

^24Hearken unto me now therefore, O ye children, and attend to the words of my mouth.

^25Let not thine heart decline to her ways, go not astray in her paths.

^26For she hath cast down many wounded: yea, many strong men have been slain by her.

^27Her house is the way to hell, going down to the chambers of death.

VIII

^1Doth not wisdom cry? and understanding put forth her voice?

^2She standeth in the top of high places, by the way in the places of the paths.

^3She crieth at the gates, at the entry of the city, at the coming in at the doors.

^4Unto you, O men, I call; and my voice is to the sons of man.

^5O ye simple, understand wisdom: and, ye fools, be ye of an understanding heart.

^6Hear; for I will speak of excellent things; and the opening of my lips shall be right things.

^7For my mouth shall speak truth; and wickedness is an abomination to my lips.

^8All the words of my mouth are in righteousness; there is nothing froward or perverse in them.

^9They are all plain to him that understandeth, and right to them that find knowledge.

^10Receive my instruction, and not silver; and knowledge rather than choice gold.

^11For wisdom is better than rubies; and all the things that may be desired are not to be compared to it.

^12I wisdom dwell with prudence, and find out knowledge of witty inventions.

^13The fear of the Lord is to hate evil: pride, and arrogancy, and the evil way, and the froward mouth, do I hate.

^14Counsel is mine, and sound wisdom: I am understanding; I have strength.

^15By me kings reign, and princes decree justice.

^16By me princes rule, and nobles, even all the judges of the earth.

^17I love them that love me; and those that seek me early shall find me.

^18Riches and honour are with me; yea, durable riches and righteousness.

^19My fruit is better than gold, yea, than fine gold; and my revenue than choice silver.

^20I lead in the way of righteousness, in the midst of the paths of judgment:

^21That I may cause those that love me to inherit substance; and I will fill their treasures.

^22The Lord possessed me in the beginning of his way, before his works of old.

^23I was set up from everlasting, from the beginning, or ever the earth was.

^24When there were no depths, I was brought forth; when there were no fountains abounding with water.

^25Before the mountains were settled, before the hills was I brought forth:

^26While as yet he had not made the earth, nor the fields, nor the highest part of the dust of the world.

^27When he prepared the heavens, I was there: when he set a compass upon the face of the depth:

^28When he established the clouds above: when he strengthened the fountains of the deep:

^29When he gave to the sea his decree, that the waters should not pass his commandment: when he appointed the foundations of the earth:

^30Then I was by him, as one brought up with him: and I was daily his delight, rejoicing always before him;

^31Rejoicing in the habitable part of his earth; and my delights were with the sons of men.

^32Now therefore hearken unto me, O ye children: for blessed are they that keep my ways.

^33Hear instruction, and be wise, and refuse it not.

^34Blessed is the man that heareth me, watching daily at my gates, waiting at the posts of my doors.

^35For whoso findeth me findeth life, and shall obtain favour of the Lord.

^36But he that sinneth against me wrongeth his own soul: all they that hate me love death.

IX

^1Wisdom hath builded her house, she hath hewn out her seven pillars:

^2She hath killed her beasts; she hath mingled her wine; she hath also furnished her table.

^3She hath sent forth her maidens: she crieth upon the highest places of the city,

^4Whoso is simple, let him turn in hither: as for him that wanteth understanding, she saith to him,

^5Come, eat of my bread, and drink of the wine which I have mingled.

^6Forsake the foolish, and live; and go in the way of understanding.

^7He that reproveth a scorner getteth to himself shame: and he that rebuketh a wicked man getteth himself a blot.

^8Reprove not a scorner, lest he hate thee: rebuke a wise man, and he will love thee.

^9Give instruction to a wise man, and he will be yet wiser: teach a just man, and he will increase in learning.

^10The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom: and the knowledge of the holy is understanding.

^11For by me thy days shall be multiplied, and the years of thy life shall be increased.

^12If thou be wise, thou shalt be wise for thyself: but if thou scornest, thou alone shalt bear it.

^13A foolish woman is clamorous: she is simple, and knoweth nothing.

^14For she sitteth at the door of her house, on a seat in the high places of the city,

^15To call passengers who go right on their ways:

^16Whoso is simple, let him turn in hither: and as for him that wanteth understanding, she saith to him,

^17Stolen waters are sweet, and bread eaten in secret is pleasant.

^18But he knoweth not that the dead are there; and that her guests are in the depths of hell.

X

^1The proverbs of Solomon. A wise son maketh a glad father: but a foolish son is the heaviness of his mother.

^2Treasures of wickedness profit nothing: but righteousness delivereth from death.

^3The Lord will not suffer the soul of the righteous to famish: but he casteth away the substance of the wicked.

^4He becometh poor that dealeth with a slack hand: but the hand of the diligent maketh rich.

^5He that gathereth in summer is a wise son: but he that sleepeth in harvest is a son that causeth shame.

^6Blessings are upon the head of the just: but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked.

^7The memory of the just is blessed: but the name of the wicked shall rot.

^8The wise in heart will receive commandments: but a prating fool shall fall.

^9He that walketh uprightly walketh surely: but he that perverteth his ways shall be known.

^10He that winketh with the eye causeth sorrow: but a prating fool shall fall.

^11The mouth of a righteous man is a well of life: but violence covereth the mouth of the wicked.

^12Hatred stirreth up strifes: but love covereth all sins.

^13In the lips of him that hath understanding wisdom is found: but a rod is for the back of him that is void of understanding.

^14Wise men lay up knowledge: but the mouth of the foolish is near destruction.

^15The rich man’s wealth is his strong city: the destruction of the poor is their poverty.

^16The labour of the righteous tendeth to life: the fruit of the wicked to sin.

^17He is in the way of life that keepeth instruction: but he that refuseth reproof erreth.

^18He that hideth hatred with lying lips, and he that uttereth a slander, is a fool.

^19In the multitude of words there wanteth not sin: but he that refraineth his lips is wise.

^20The tongue of the just is as choice silver: the heart of the wicked is little worth.

^21The lips of the righteous feed many: but fools die for want of wisdom.

^22The blessing of the Lord, it maketh rich, and he addeth no sorrow with it.

^23It is as sport to a fool to do mischief: but a man of understanding hath wisdom.

^24The fear of the wicked, it shall come upon him: but the desire of the righteous shall be granted.

^25As the whirlwind passeth, so is the wicked no more: but the righteous is an everlasting foundation.

^26As vinegar to the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to them that send him.

^27The fear of the Lord prolongeth days: but the years of the wicked shall be shortened.

^28The hope of the righteous shall be gladness: but the expectation of the wicked shall perish.

^29The way of the Lord is strength to the upright: but destruction shall be to the workers of iniquity.

^30The righteous shall never be removed: but the wicked shall not inhabit the earth.

^31The mouth of the just bringeth forth wisdom: but the froward tongue shall be cut out.

^32The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable: but the mouth of the wicked speaketh frowardness.

XI

^1A false balance is abomination to the Lord: but a just weight is his delight.

^2When pride cometh, then cometh shame: but with the lowly is wisdom.

^3The integrity of the upright shall guide them: but the perverseness of transgressors shall destroy them.

^4Riches profit not in the day of wrath: but righteousness delivereth from death.

^5The righteousness of the perfect shall direct his way: but the wicked shall fall by his own wickedness.

^6The righteousness of the upright shall deliver them: but transgressors shall be taken in their own naughtiness.

^7When a wicked man dieth, his expectation shall perish: and the hope of unjust men perisheth.

^8The righteous is delivered out of trouble, and the wicked cometh in his stead.

^9An hypocrite with his mouth destroyeth his neighbour: but through knowledge shall the just be delivered.

^10When it goeth well with the righteous, the city rejoiceth: and when the wicked perish, there is shouting.

^11By the blessing of the upright the city is exalted: but it is overthrown by the mouth of the wicked.

^12He that is void of wisdom despiseth his neighbour: but a man of understanding holdeth his peace.

^13A talebearer revealeth secrets: but he that is of a faithful spirit concealeth the matter.

^14Where no counsel is, the people fall: but in the multitude of counsellors there is safety.

^15He that is surety for a stranger shall smart for it: and he that hateth suretiship is sure.

^16A gracious woman retaineth honour: and strong men retain riches.

^17The merciful man doeth good to his own soul: but he that is cruel troubleth his own flesh.

^18The wicked worketh a deceitful work: but to him that soweth righteousness shall be a sure reward.

^19As righteousness tendeth to life: so he that pursueth evil pursueth it to his own death.

^20They that are of a froward heart are abomination to the Lord: but such as are upright in their way are his delight.

^21Though hand join in hand, the wicked shall not be unpunished: but the seed of the righteous shall be delivered.

^22As a jewel of gold in a swine’s snout, so is a fair woman which is without discretion.

^23The desire of the righteous is only good: but the expectation of the wicked is wrath.

^24There is that scattereth, and yet increaseth; and there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to poverty.

^25The liberal soul shall be made fat: and he that watereth shall be watered also himself.

^26He that withholdeth corn, the people shall curse him: but blessing shall be upon the head of him that selleth it.

^27He that diligently seeketh good procureth favour: but he that seeketh mischief, it shall come unto him.

^28He that trusteth in his riches shall fall; but the righteous shall flourish as a branch.

^29He that troubleth his own house shall inherit the wind: and the fool shall be servant to the wise of heart.

^30The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life; and he that winneth souls is wise.

^31Behold, the righteous shall be recompensed in the earth: much more the wicked and the sinner.

XII

^1Whoso loveth instruction loveth knowledge: but he that hateth reproof is brutish.

^2A good man obtaineth favour of the Lord: but a man of wicked devices will he condemn.

^3A man shall not be established by wickedness: but the root of the righteous shall not be moved.

^4A virtuous woman is a crown to her husband: but she that maketh ashamed is as rottenness in his bones.

^5The thoughts of the righteous are right: but the counsels of the wicked are deceit.

^6The words of the wicked are to lie in wait for blood: but the mouth of the upright shall deliver them.

^7The wicked are overthrown, and are not: but the house of the righteous shall stand.

^8A man shall be commended according to his wisdom: but he that is of a perverse heart shall be despised.

^9He that is despised, and hath a servant, is better than he that honoureth himself, and lacketh bread.

^10A righteous man regardeth the life of his beast: but the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.

^11He that tilleth his land shall be satisfied with bread: but he that followeth vain persons is void of understanding.

^12The wicked desireth the net of evil men: but the root of the righteous yieldeth fruit.

^13The wicked is snared by the transgression of his lips: but the just shall come out of trouble.

^14A man shall be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth: and the recompence of a man’s hands shall be rendered unto him.

^15The way of a fool is right in his own eyes: but he that hearkeneth unto counsel is wise.

^16A fool’s wrath is presently known: but a prudent man covereth shame.

^17He that speaketh truth sheweth forth righteousness: but a false witness deceit.

^18There is that speaketh like the piercings of a sword: but the tongue of the wise is health.

^19The lip of truth shall be established for ever: but a lying tongue is but for a moment.

^20Deceit is in the heart of them that imagine evil: but to the counsellors of peace is joy.

^21There shall no evil happen to the just: but the wicked shall be filled with mischief.

^22Lying lips are abomination to the Lord: but they that deal truly are his delight.

^23A prudent man concealeth knowledge: but the heart of fools proclaimeth foolishness.

^24The hand of the diligent shall bear rule: but the slothful shall be under tribute.

^25Heaviness in the heart of man maketh it stoop: but a good word maketh it glad.

^26The righteous is more excellent than his neighbour: but the way of the wicked seduceth them.

^27The slothful man roasteth not that which he took in hunting: but the substance of a diligent man is precious.

^28In the way of righteousness is life: and in the pathway thereof there is no death.

XIII

^1A wise son heareth his father’s instruction: but a scorner heareth not rebuke.

^2A man shall eat good by the fruit of his mouth: but the soul of the transgressors shall eat violence.

^3He that keepeth his mouth keepeth his life: but he that openeth wide his lips shall have destruction.

^4The soul of the sluggard desireth, and hath nothing: but the soul of the diligent shall be made fat.

^5A righteous man hateth lying: but a wicked man is loathsome, and cometh to shame.

^6Righteousness keepeth him that is upright in the way: but wickedness overthroweth the sinner.

^7There is that maketh himself rich, yet hath nothing: there is that maketh himself poor, yet hath great riches.

^8The ransom of a man’s life are his riches: but the poor heareth not rebuke.

^9The light of the righteous rejoiceth: but the lamp of the wicked shall be put out.

^10Only by pride cometh contention: but with the well advised is wisdom.

^11Wealth gotten by vanity shall be diminished: but he that gathereth by labour shall increase.

^12Hope deferred maketh the heart sick: but when the desire cometh, it is a tree of life.

^13Whoso despiseth the word shall be destroyed: but he that feareth the commandment shall be rewarded.

^14The law of the wise is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death.

^15Good understanding giveth favour: but the way of transgressors is hard.

^16Every prudent man dealeth with knowledge: but a fool layeth open his folly.

^17A wicked messenger falleth into mischief: but a faithful ambassador is health.

^18Poverty and shame shall be to him that refuseth instruction: but he that regardeth reproof shall be honoured.

^19The desire accomplished is sweet to the soul: but it is abomination to fools to depart from evil.

^20He that walketh with wise men shall be wise: but a companion of fools shall be destroyed.

^21Evil pursueth sinners: but to the righteous good shall be repayed.

^22A good man leaveth an inheritance to his children’s children: and the wealth of the sinner is laid up for the just.

^23Much food is in the tillage of the poor: but there is that is destroyed for want of judgment.

^24He that spareth his rod hateth his son: but he that loveth him chasteneth him betimes.

^25The righteous eateth to the satisfying of his soul: but the belly of the wicked shall want.

XIV

^1Every wise woman buildeth her house: but the foolish plucketh it down with her hands.

^2He that walketh in his uprightness feareth the Lord: but he that is perverse in his ways despiseth him.

^3In the mouth of the foolish is a rod of pride: but the lips of the wise shall preserve them.

^4Where no oxen are, the crib is clean: but much increase is by the strength of the ox.

^5A faithful witness will not lie: but a false witness will utter lies.

^6A scorner seeketh wisdom, and findeth it not: but knowledge is easy unto him that understandeth.

^7Go from the presence of a foolish man, when thou perceivest not in him the lips of knowledge.

^8The wisdom of the prudent is to understand his way: but the folly of fools is deceit.

^9Fools make a mock at sin: but among the righteous there is favour.

^10The heart knoweth his own bitterness; and a stranger doth not intermeddle with his joy.

^11The house of the wicked shall be overthrown: but the tabernacle of the upright shall flourish.

^12There is a way which seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death.

^13Even in laughter the heart is sorrowful; and the end of that mirth is heaviness.

^14The backslider in heart shall be filled with his own ways: and a good man shall be satisfied from himself.

^15The simple believeth every word: but the prudent man looketh well to his going.

^16A wise man feareth, and departeth from evil: but the fool rageth, and is confident.

^17He that is soon angry dealeth foolishly: and a man of wicked devices is hated.

^18The simple inherit folly: but the prudent are crowned with knowledge.

^19The evil bow before the good; and the wicked at the gates of the righteous.

^20The poor is hated even of his own neighbour: but the rich hath many friends.

^21He that despiseth his neighbour sinneth: but he that hath mercy on the poor, happy is he.

^22Do they not err that devise evil? but mercy and truth shall be to them that devise good.

^23In all labour there is profit: but the talk of the lips tendeth only to penury.

^24The crown of the wise is their riches: but the foolishness of fools is folly.

^25A true witness delivereth souls: but a deceitful witness speaketh lies.

^26In the fear of the Lord is strong confidence: and his children shall have a place of refuge.

^27The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death.

^28In the multitude of people is the king’s honour: but in the want of people is the destruction of the prince.

^29He that is slow to wrath is of great understanding: but he that is hasty of spirit exalteth folly.

^30A sound heart is the life of the flesh: but envy the rottenness of the bones.

^31He that oppresseth the poor reproacheth his Maker: but he that honoureth him hath mercy on the poor.

^32The wicked is driven away in his wickedness: but the righteous hath hope in his death.

^33Wisdom resteth in the heart of him that hath understanding: but that which is in the midst of fools is made known.

^34Righteousness exalteth a nation: but sin is a reproach to any people.

^35The king’s favour is toward a wise servant: but his wrath is against him that causeth shame.

XV

^1A soft answer turneth away wrath: but grievous words stir up anger.

^2The tongue of the wise useth knowledge aright: but the mouth of fools poureth out foolishness.

^3The eyes of the Lord are in every place, beholding the evil and the good.

^4A wholesome tongue is a tree of life: but perverseness therein is a breach in the spirit.

^5A fool despiseth his father’s instruction: but he that regardeth reproof is prudent.

^6In the house of the righteous is much treasure: but in the revenues of the wicked is trouble.

^7The lips of the wise disperse knowledge: but the heart of the foolish doeth not so.

^8The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord: but the prayer of the upright is his delight.

^9The way of the wicked is an abomination unto the Lord: but he loveth him that followeth after righteousness.

^10Correction is grievous unto him that forsaketh the way: and he that hateth reproof shall die.

^11Hell and destruction are before the Lord: how much more then the hearts of the children of men?

^12A scorner loveth not one that reproveth him: neither will he go unto the wise.

^13A merry heart maketh a cheerful countenance: but by sorrow of the heart the spirit is broken.

^14The heart of him that hath understanding seeketh knowledge: but the mouth of fools feedeth on foolishness.

^15All the days of the afflicted are evil: but he that is of a merry heart hath a continual feast.

^16Better is little with the fear of the Lord than great treasure and trouble therewith.

^17Better is a dinner of herbs where love is, than a stalled ox and hatred therewith.

^18A wrathful man stirreth up strife: but he that is slow to anger appeaseth strife.

^19The way of the slothful man is as an hedge of thorns: but the way of the righteous is made plain.

^20A wise son maketh a glad father: but a foolish man despiseth his mother.

^21Folly is joy to him that is destitute of wisdom: but a man of understanding walketh uprightly.

^22Without counsel purposes are disappointed: but in the multitude of counsellors they are established.

^23A man hath joy by the answer of his mouth: and a word spoken in due season, how good is it!

^24The way of life is above to the wise, that he may depart from hell beneath.

^25The Lord will destroy the house of the proud: but he will establish the border of the widow.

^26The thoughts of the wicked are an abomination to the Lord: but the words of the pure are pleasant words.

^27He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own house; but he that hateth gifts shall live.

^28The heart of the righteous studieth to answer: but the mouth of the wicked poureth out evil things.

^29The Lord is far from the wicked: but he heareth the prayer of the righteous.

^30The light of the eyes rejoiceth the heart: and a good report maketh the bones fat.

^31The ear that heareth the reproof of life abideth among the wise.

^32He that refuseth instruction despiseth his own soul: but he that heareth reproof getteth understanding.

^33The fear of the Lord is the instruction of wisdom; and before honour is humility.

XVI

^1The preparations of the heart in man, and the answer of the tongue, is from the Lord.

^2All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes; but the Lord weigheth the spirits.

^3Commit thy works unto the Lord, and thy thoughts shall be established.

^4The Lord hath made all things for himself: yea, even the wicked for the day of evil.

^5Every one that is proud in heart is an abomination to the Lord: though hand join in hand, he shall not be unpunished.

^6By mercy and truth iniquity is purged: and by the fear of the Lord men depart from evil.

^7When a man’s ways please the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him.

^8Better is a little with righteousness than great revenues without right.

^9A man’s heart deviseth his way: but the Lord directeth his steps.

^10A divine sentence is in the lips of the king: his mouth transgresseth not in judgment.

^11A just weight and balance are the Lord’s: all the weights of the bag are his work.

^12It is an abomination to kings to commit wickedness: for the throne is established by righteousness.

^13Righteous lips are the delight of kings; and they love him that speaketh right.

^14The wrath of a king is as messengers of death: but a wise man will pacify it.

^15In the light of the king’s countenance is life; and his favour is as a cloud of the latter rain.

^16How much better is it to get wisdom than gold! and to get understanding rather to be chosen than silver!

^17The highway of the upright is to depart from evil: he that keepeth his way preserveth his soul.

^18Pride goeth before destruction, and an haughty spirit before a fall.

^19Better it is to be of an humble spirit with the lowly, than to divide the spoil with the proud.

^20He that handleth a matter wisely shall find good: and whoso trusteth in the Lord, happy is he.

^21The wise in heart shall be called prudent: and the sweetness of the lips increaseth learning.

^22Understanding is a wellspring of life unto him that hath it: but the instruction of fools is folly.

^23The heart of the wise teacheth his mouth, and addeth learning to his lips.

^24Pleasant words are as an honeycomb, sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.

^25There is a way that seemeth right unto a man, but the end thereof are the ways of death.

^26He that laboureth laboureth for himself; for his mouth craveth it of him.

^27An ungodly man diggeth up evil: and in his lips there is as a burning fire.

^28A froward man soweth strife: and a whisperer separateth chief friends.

^29A violent man enticeth his neighbour, and leadeth him into the way that is not good.

^30He shutteth his eyes to devise froward things: moving his lips he bringeth evil to pass.

^31The hoary head is a crown of glory, if it be found in the way of righteousness.

^32He that is slow to anger is better than the mighty; and he that ruleth his spirit than he that taketh a city.

^33The lot is cast into the lap; but the whole disposing thereof is of the Lord.

XVII

^1Better is a dry morsel, and quietness therewith, than an house full of sacrifices with strife.

^2A wise servant shall have rule over a son that causeth shame, and shall have part of the inheritance among the brethren.

^3The fining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold: but the Lord trieth the hearts.

^4A wicked doer giveth heed to false lips; and a liar giveth ear to a naughty tongue.

^5Whoso mocketh the poor reproacheth his Maker: and he that is glad at calamities shall not be unpunished.

^6Children’s children are the crown of old men; and the glory of children are their fathers.

^7Excellent speech becometh not a fool: much less do lying lips a prince.

^8A gift is as a precious stone in the eyes of him that hath it: whithersoever it turneth, it prospereth.

^9He that covereth a transgression seeketh love; but he that repeateth a matter separateth very friends.

^10A reproof entereth more into a wise man than an hundred stripes into a fool.

^11An evil man seeketh only rebellion: therefore a cruel messenger shall be sent against him.

^12Let a bear robbed of her whelps meet a man, rather than a fool in his folly.

^13Whoso rewardeth evil for good, evil shall not depart from his house.

^14The beginning of strife is as when one letteth out water: therefore leave off contention, before it be meddled with.

^15He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the just, even they both are abomination to the Lord.

^16Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a fool to get wisdom, seeing he hath no heart to it?

^17A friend loveth at all times, and a brother is born for adversity.

^18A man void of understanding striketh hands, and becometh surety in the presence of his friend.

^19He loveth transgression that loveth strife: and he that exalteth his gate seeketh destruction.

^20He that hath a froward heart findeth no good: and he that hath a perverse tongue falleth into mischief.

^21He that begetteth a fool doeth it to his sorrow: and the father of a fool hath no joy.

^22A merry heart doeth good like a medicine: but a broken spirit drieth the bones.

^23A wicked man taketh a gift out of the bosom to pervert the ways of judgment.

^24Wisdom is before him that hath understanding; but the eyes of a fool are in the ends of the earth.

^25A foolish son is a grief to his father, and bitterness to her that bare him.

^26Also to punish the just is not good, nor to strike princes for equity.

^27He that hath knowledge spareth his words: and a man of understanding is of an excellent spirit.

^28Even a fool, when he holdeth his peace, is counted wise: and he that shutteth his lips is esteemed a man of understanding.

XVIII

^1Through desire a man, having separated himself, seeketh and intermeddleth with all wisdom.

^2A fool hath no delight in understanding, but that his heart may discover itself.

^3When the wicked cometh, then cometh also contempt, and with ignominy reproach.

^4The words of a man’s mouth are as deep waters, and the wellspring of wisdom as a flowing brook.

^5It is not good to accept the person of the wicked, to overthrow the righteous in judgment.

^6A fool’s lips enter into contention, and his mouth calleth for strokes.

^7A fool’s mouth is his destruction, and his lips are the snare of his soul.

^8The words of a talebearer are as wounds, and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.

^9He also that is slothful in his work is brother to him that is a great waster.

^10The name of the Lord is a strong tower: the righteous runneth into it, and is safe.

^11The rich man’s wealth is his strong city, and as an high wall in his own conceit.

^12Before destruction the heart of man is haughty, and before honour is humility.

^13He that answereth a matter before he heareth it, it is folly and shame unto him.

^14The spirit of a man will sustain his infirmity; but a wounded spirit who can bear?

^15The heart of the prudent getteth knowledge; and the ear of the wise seeketh knowledge.

^16A man’s gift maketh room for him, and bringeth him before great men.

^17He that is first in his own cause seemeth just; but his neighbour cometh and searcheth him.

^18The lot causeth contentions to cease, and parteth between the mighty.

^19A brother offended is harder to be won than a strong city: and their contentions are like the bars of a castle.

^20A man’s belly shall be satisfied with the fruit of his mouth; and with the increase of his lips shall he be filled.

^21Death and life are in the power of the tongue: and they that love it shall eat the fruit thereof.

^22Whoso findeth a wife findeth a good thing, and obtaineth favour of the Lord.

^23The poor useth intreaties; but the rich answereth roughly.

^24A man that hath friends must shew himself friendly: and there is a friend that sticketh closer than a brother.

XIX

^1Better is the poor that walketh in his integrity, than he that is perverse in his lips, and is a fool.

^2Also, that the soul be without knowledge, it is not good; and he that hasteth with his feet sinneth.

^3The foolishness of man perverteth his way: and his heart fretteth against the Lord.

^4Wealth maketh many friends; but the poor is separated from his neighbour.

^5A false witness shall not be unpunished, and he that speaketh lies shall not escape.

^6Many will intreat the favour of the prince: and every man is a friend to him that giveth gifts.

^7All the brethren of the poor do hate him: how much more do his friends go far from him? he pursueth them with words, yet they are wanting to him.

^8He that getteth wisdom loveth his own soul: he that keepeth understanding shall find good.

^9A false witness shall not be unpunished, and he that speaketh lies shall perish.

^10Delight is not seemly for a fool; much less for a servant to have rule over princes.

^11The discretion of a man deferreth his anger; and it is his glory to pass over a transgression.

^12The king’s wrath is as the roaring of a lion; but his favour is as dew upon the grass.

^13A foolish son is the calamity of his father: and the contentions of a wife are a continual dropping.

^14House and riches are the inheritance of fathers: and a prudent wife is from the Lord.

^15Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep; and an idle soul shall suffer hunger.

^16He that keepeth the commandment keepeth his own soul; but he that despiseth his ways shall die.

^17He that hath pity upon the poor lendeth unto the Lord; and that which he hath given will he pay him again.

^18Chasten thy son while there is hope, and let not thy soul spare for his crying.

^19A man of great wrath shall suffer punishment: for if thou deliver him, yet thou must do it again.

^20Hear counsel, and receive instruction, that thou mayest be wise in thy latter end.

^21There are many devices in a man’s heart; nevertheless the counsel of the Lord, that shall stand.

^22The desire of a man is his kindness: and a poor man is better than a liar.

^23The fear of the Lord tendeth to life: and he that hath it shall abide satisfied; he shall not be visited with evil.

^24A slothful man hideth his hand in his bosom, and will not so much as bring it to his mouth again.

^25Smite a scorner, and the simple will beware: and reprove one that hath understanding, and he will understand knowledge.

^26He that wasteth his father, and chaseth away his mother, is a son that causeth shame, and bringeth reproach.

^27Cease, my son, to hear the instruction that causeth to err from the words of knowledge.

^28An ungodly witness scorneth judgment: and the mouth of the wicked devoureth iniquity.

^29Judgments are prepared for scorners, and stripes for the back of fools.

XX

^1Wine is a mocker, strong drink is raging: and whosoever is deceived thereby is not wise.

^2The fear of a king is as the roaring of a lion: whoso provoketh him to anger sinneth against his own soul.

^3It is an honour for a man to cease from strife: but every fool will be meddling.

^4The sluggard will not plow by reason of the cold; therefore shall he beg in harvest, and have nothing.

^5Counsel in the heart of man is like deep water; but a man of understanding will draw it out.

^6Most men will proclaim every one his own goodness: but a faithful man who can find?

^7The just man walketh in his integrity: his children are blessed after him.

^8A king that sitteth in the throne of judgment scattereth away all evil with his eyes.

^9Who can say, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my sin?

^10Divers weights, and divers measures, both of them are alike abomination to the Lord.

^11Even a child is known by his doings, whether his work be pure, and whether it be right.

^12The hearing ear, and the seeing eye, the Lord hath made even both of them.

^13Love not sleep, lest thou come to poverty; open thine eyes, and thou shalt be satisfied with bread.

^14It is naught, it is naught, saith the buyer: but when he is gone his way, then he boasteth.

^15There is gold, and a multitude of rubies: but the lips of knowledge are a precious jewel.

^16Take his garment that is surety for a stranger: and take a pledge of him for a strange woman.

^17Bread of deceit is sweet to a man; but afterwards his mouth shall be filled with gravel.

^18Every purpose is established by counsel: and with good advice make war.

^19He that goeth about as a talebearer revealeth secrets: therefore meddle not with him that flattereth with his lips.

^20Whoso curseth his father or his mother, his lamp shall be put out in obscure darkness.

^21An inheritance may be gotten hastily at the beginning; but the end thereof shall not be blessed.

^22Say not thou, I will recompense evil; but wait on the Lord, and he shall save thee.

^23Divers weights are an abomination unto the Lord; and a false balance is not good.

^24Man’s goings are of the Lord; how can a man then understand his own way?

^25It is a snare to the man who devoureth that which is holy, and after vows to make enquiry.

^26A wise king scattereth the wicked, and bringeth the wheel over them.

^27The spirit of man is the candle of the Lord, searching all the inward parts of the belly.

^28Mercy and truth preserve the king: and his throne is upholden by mercy.

^29The glory of young men is their strength: and the beauty of old men is the grey head.

^30The blueness of a wound cleanseth away evil: so do stripes the inward parts of the belly.

XXI

^1The king’s heart is in the hand of the Lord, as the rivers of water: he turneth it whithersoever he will.

^2Every way of a man is right in his own eyes: but the Lord pondereth the hearts.

^3To do justice and judgment is more acceptable to the Lord than sacrifice.

^4An high look, and a proud heart, and the plowing of the wicked, is sin.

^5The thoughts of the diligent tend only to plenteousness; but of every one that is hasty only to want.

^6The getting of treasures by a lying tongue is a vanity tossed to and fro of them that seek death.

^7The robbery of the wicked shall destroy them; because they refuse to do judgment.

^8The way of man is froward and strange: but as for the pure, his work is right.

^9It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman in a wide house.

^10The soul of the wicked desireth evil: his neighbour findeth no favour in his eyes.

^11When the scorner is punished, the simple is made wise: and when the wise is instructed, he receiveth knowledge.

^12The righteous man wisely considereth the house of the wicked: but God overthroweth the wicked for their wickedness.

^13Whoso stoppeth his ears at the cry of the poor, he also shall cry himself, but shall not be heard.

^14A gift in secret pacifieth anger: and a reward in the bosom strong wrath.

^15It is joy to the just to do judgment: but destruction shall be to the workers of iniquity.

^16The man that wandereth out of the way of understanding shall remain in the congregation of the dead.

^17He that loveth pleasure shall be a poor man: he that loveth wine and oil shall not be rich.

^18The wicked shall be a ransom for the righteous, and the transgressor for the upright.

^19It is better to dwell in the wilderness, than with a contentious and an angry woman.

^20There is treasure to be desired and oil in the dwelling of the wise; but a foolish man spendeth it up.

^21He that followeth after righteousness and mercy findeth life, righteousness, and honour.

^22A wise man scaleth the city of the mighty, and casteth down the strength of the confidence thereof.

^23Whoso keepeth his mouth and his tongue keepeth his soul from troubles.

^24Proud and haughty scorner is his name, who dealeth in proud wrath.

^25The desire of the slothful killeth him; for his hands refuse to labour.

^26He coveteth greedily all the day long: but the righteous giveth and spareth not.

^27The sacrifice of the wicked is abomination: how much more, when he bringeth it with a wicked mind?

^28A false witness shall perish: but the man that heareth speaketh constantly.

^29A wicked man hardeneth his face: but as for the upright, he directeth his way.

^30There is no wisdom nor understanding nor counsel against the Lord.

^31The horse is prepared against the day of battle: but safety is of the Lord.

XXII

^1A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches, and loving favour rather than silver and gold.

^2The rich and poor meet together: the Lord is the maker of them all.

^3A prudent man foreseeth the evil, and hideth himself: but the simple pass on, and are punished.

^4By humility and the fear of the Lord are riches, and honour, and life.

^5Thorns and snares are in the way of the froward: he that doth keep his soul shall be far from them.

^6Train up a child in the way he should go: and when he is old, he will not depart from it.

^7The rich ruleth over the poor, and the borrower is servant to the lender.

^8He that soweth iniquity shall reap vanity: and the rod of his anger shall fail.

^9He that hath a bountiful eye shall be blessed; for he giveth of his bread to the poor.

^10Cast out the scorner, and contention shall go out; yea, strife and reproach shall cease.

^11He that loveth pureness of heart, for the grace of his lips the king shall be his friend.

^12The eyes of the Lord preserve knowledge, and he overthroweth the words of the transgressor.

^13The slothful man saith, There is a lion without, I shall be slain in the streets.

^14The mouth of strange women is a deep pit: he that is abhorred of the Lord shall fall therein.

^15Foolishness is bound in the heart of a child; but the rod of correction shall drive it far from him.

^16He that oppresseth the poor to increase his riches, and he that giveth to the rich, shall surely come to want.

^17Bow down thine ear, and hear the words of the wise, and apply thine heart unto my knowledge.

^18For it is a pleasant thing if thou keep them within thee; they shall withal be fitted in thy lips.

^19That thy trust may be in the Lord, I have made known to thee this day, even to thee.

^20Have not I written to thee excellent things in counsels and knowledge,

^21That I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth; that thou mightest answer the words of truth to them that send unto thee?

^22Rob not the poor, because he is poor: neither oppress the afflicted in the gate:

^23For the Lord will plead their cause, and spoil the soul of those that spoiled them.

^24Make no friendship with an angry man; and with a furious man thou shalt not go:

^25Lest thou learn his ways, and get a snare to thy soul.

^26Be not thou one of them that strike hands, or of them that are sureties for debts.

^27If thou hast nothing to pay, why should he take away thy bed from under thee?

^28Remove not the ancient landmark, which thy fathers have set.

^29Seest thou a man diligent in his business? he shall stand before kings; he shall not stand before mean men.

XXIII

^1When thou sittest to eat with a ruler, consider diligently what is before thee:

^2And put a knife to thy throat, if thou be a man given to appetite.

^3Be not desirous of his dainties: for they are deceitful meat.

^4Labour not to be rich: cease from thine own wisdom.

^5Wilt thou set thine eyes upon that which is not? for riches certainly make themselves wings; they fly away as an eagle toward heaven.

^6Eat thou not the bread of him that hath an evil eye, neither desire thou his dainty meats:

^7For as he thinketh in his heart, so is he: Eat and drink, saith he to thee; but his heart is not with thee.

^8The morsel which thou hast eaten shalt thou vomit up, and lose thy sweet words.

^9Speak not in the ears of a fool: for he will despise the wisdom of thy words.

^10Remove not the old landmark; and enter not into the fields of the fatherless:

^11For their redeemer is mighty; he shall plead their cause with thee.

^12Apply thine heart unto instruction, and thine ears to the words of knowledge.

^13Withhold not correction from the child: for if thou beatest him with the rod, he shall not die.

^14Thou shalt beat him with the rod, and shalt deliver his soul from hell.

^15My son, if thine heart be wise, my heart shall rejoice, even mine.

^16Yea, my reins shall rejoice, when thy lips speak right things.

^17Let not thine heart envy sinners: but be thou in the fear of the Lord all the day long.

^18For surely there is an end; and thine expectation shall not be cut off.

^19Hear thou, my son, and be wise, and guide thine heart in the way.

^20Be not among winebibbers; among riotous eaters of flesh:

^21For the drunkard and the glutton shall come to poverty: and drowsiness shall clothe a man with rags.

^22Hearken unto thy father that begat thee, and despise not thy mother when she is old.

^23Buy the truth, and sell it not; also wisdom, and instruction, and understanding.

^24The father of the righteous shall greatly rejoice: and he that begetteth a wise child shall have joy of him.

^25Thy father and thy mother shall be glad, and she that bare thee shall rejoice.

^26My son, give me thine heart, and let thine eyes observe my ways.

^27For a whore is a deep ditch; and a strange woman is a narrow pit.

^28She also lieth in wait as for a prey, and increaseth the transgressors among men.

^29Who hath woe? who hath sorrow? who hath contentions? who hath babbling? who hath wounds without cause? who hath redness of eyes?

^30They that tarry long at the wine; they that go to seek mixed wine.

^31Look not thou upon the wine when it is red, when it giveth his colour in the cup, when it moveth itself aright.

^32At the last it biteth like a serpent, and stingeth like an adder.

^33Thine eyes shall behold strange women, and thine heart shall utter perverse things.

^34Yea, thou shalt be as he that lieth down in the midst of the sea, or as he that lieth upon the top of a mast.

^35They have stricken me, shalt thou say, and I was not sick; they have beaten me, and I felt it not: when shall I awake? I will seek it yet again.

XXIV

^1Be not thou envious against evil men, neither desire to be with them.

^2For their heart studieth destruction, and their lips talk of mischief.

^3Through wisdom is an house builded; and by understanding it is established:

^4And by knowledge shall the chambers be filled with all precious and pleasant riches.

^5A wise man is strong; yea, a man of knowledge increaseth strength.

^6For by wise counsel thou shalt make thy war: and in multitude of counsellors there is safety.

^7Wisdom is too high for a fool: he openeth not his mouth in the gate.

^8He that deviseth to do evil shall be called a mischievous person.

^9The thought of foolishness is sin: and the scorner is an abomination to men.

^10If thou faint in the day of adversity, thy strength is small.

^11If thou forbear to deliver them that are drawn unto death, and those that are ready to be slain;

^12If thou sayest, Behold, we knew it not; doth not he that pondereth the heart consider it? and he that keepeth thy soul, doth not he know it? and shall not he render to every man according to his works?

^13My son, eat thou honey, because it is good; and the honeycomb, which is sweet to thy taste:

^14So shall the knowledge of wisdom be unto thy soul: when thou hast found it, then there shall be a reward, and thy expectation shall not be cut off.

^15Lay not wait, O wicked man, against the dwelling of the righteous; spoil not his resting place:

^16For a just man falleth seven times, and riseth up again: but the wicked shall fall into mischief.

^17Rejoice not when thine enemy falleth, and let not thine heart be glad when he stumbleth:

^18Lest the Lord see it, and it displease him, and he turn away his wrath from him.

^19Fret not thyself because of evil men, neither be thou envious at the wicked:

^20For there shall be no reward to the evil man; the candle of the wicked shall be put out.

^21My son, fear thou the Lord and the king: and meddle not with them that are given to change:

^22For their calamity shall rise suddenly; and who knoweth the ruin of them both?

^23These things also belong to the wise. It is not good to have respect of persons in judgment.

^24He that saith unto the wicked, Thou are righteous; him shall the people curse, nations shall abhor him:

^25But to them that rebuke him shall be delight, and a good blessing shall come upon them.

^26Every man shall kiss his lips that giveth a right answer.

^27Prepare thy work without, and make it fit for thyself in the field; and afterwards build thine house.

^28Be not a witness against thy neighbour without cause; and deceive not with thy lips.

^29Say not, I will do so to him as he hath done to me: I will render to the man according to his work.

^30I went by the field of the slothful, and by the vineyard of the man void of understanding;

^31And, lo, it was all grown over with thorns, and nettles had covered the face thereof, and the stone wall thereof was broken down.

^32Then I saw, and considered it well: I looked upon it, and received instruction.

^33Yet a little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to sleep:

^34So shall thy poverty come as one that travelleth; and thy want as an armed man.

XXV

^1These are also proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied out.

^2It is the glory of God to conceal a thing: but the honour of kings is to search out a matter.

^3The heaven for height, and the earth for depth, and the heart of kings is unsearchable.

^4Take away the dross from the silver, and there shall come forth a vessel for the finer.

^5Take away the wicked from before the king, and his throne shall be established in righteousness.

^6Put not forth thyself in the presence of the king, and stand not in the place of great men:

^7For better it is that it be said unto thee, Come up hither; than that thou shouldest be put lower in the presence of the prince whom thine eyes have seen.

^8Go not forth hastily to strive, lest thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to shame.

^9Debate thy cause with thy neighbour himself; and discover not a secret to another:

^10Lest he that heareth it put thee to shame, and thine infamy turn not away.

^11A word fitly spoken is like apples of gold in pictures of silver.

^12As an earring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold, so is a wise reprover upon an obedient ear.

^13As the cold of snow in the time of harvest, so is a faithful messenger to them that send him: for he refresheth the soul of his masters.

^14Whoso boasteth himself of a false gift is like clouds and wind without rain.

^15By long forbearing is a prince persuaded, and a soft tongue breaketh the bone.

^16Hast thou found honey? eat so much as is sufficient for thee, lest thou be filled therewith, and vomit it.

^17Withdraw thy foot from thy neighbour’s house; lest he be weary of thee, and so hate thee.

^18A man that beareth false witness against his neighbour is a maul, and a sword, and a sharp arrow.

^19Confidence in an unfaithful man in time of trouble is like a broken tooth, and a foot out of joint.

^20As he that taketh away a garment in cold weather, and as vinegar upon nitre, so is he that singeth songs to an heavy heart.

^21If thine enemy be hungry, give him bread to eat; and if he be thirsty, give him water to drink:

^22For thou shalt heap coals of fire upon his head, and the Lord shall reward thee.

^23The north wind driveth away rain: so doth an angry countenance a backbiting tongue.

^24It is better to dwell in the corner of the housetop, than with a brawling woman and in a wide house.

^25As cold waters to a thirsty soul, so is good news from a far country.

^26A righteous man falling down before the wicked is as a troubled fountain, and a corrupt spring.

^27It is not good to eat much honey: so for men to search their own glory is not glory.

^28He that hath no rule over his own spirit is like a city that is broken down, and without walls.

XXVI

^1As snow in summer, and as rain in harvest, so honour is not seemly for a fool.

^2As the bird by wandering, as the swallow by flying, so the curse causeless shall not come.

^3A whip for the horse, a bridle for the ass, and a rod for the fool’s back.

^4Answer not a fool according to his folly, lest thou also be like unto him.

^5Answer a fool according to his folly, lest he be wise in his own conceit.

^6He that sendeth a message by the hand of a fool cutteth off the feet, and drinketh damage.

^7The legs of the lame are not equal: so is a parable in the mouth of fools.

^8As he that bindeth a stone in a sling, so is he that giveth honour to a fool.

^9As a thorn goeth up into the hand of a drunkard, so is a parable in the mouths of fools.

^10The great God that formed all things both rewardeth the fool, and rewardeth transgressors.

^11As a dog returneth to his vomit, so a fool returneth to his folly.

^12Seest thou a man wise in his own conceit? there is more hope of a fool than of him.

^13The slothful man saith, There is a lion in the way; a lion is in the streets.

^14As the door turneth upon his hinges, so doth the slothful upon his bed.

^15The slothful hideth his hand in his bosom; it grieveth him to bring it again to his mouth.

^16The sluggard is wiser in his own conceit than seven men that can render a reason.

^17He that passeth by, and meddleth with strife belonging not to him, is like one that taketh a dog by the ears.

^18As a mad man who casteth firebrands, arrows, and death,

^19So is the man that deceiveth his neighbour, and saith, Am not I in sport?

^20Where no wood is, there the fire goeth out: so where there is no talebearer, the strife ceaseth.

^21As coals are to burning coals, and wood to fire; so is a contentious man to kindle strife.

^22The words of a talebearer are as wounds, and they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.

^23Burning lips and a wicked heart are like a potsherd covered with silver dross.

^24He that hateth dissembleth with his lips, and layeth up deceit within him;

^25When he speaketh fair, believe him not: for there are seven abominations in his heart.

^26Whose hatred is covered by deceit, his wickedness shall be shewed before the whole congregation.

^27Whoso diggeth a pit shall fall therein: and he that rolleth a stone, it will return upon him.

^28A lying tongue hateth those that are afflicted by it; and a flattering mouth worketh ruin.

XXVII

^1Boast not thyself of to morrow; for thou knowest not what a day may bring forth.

^2Let another man praise thee, and not thine own mouth; a stranger, and not thine own lips.

^3A stone is heavy, and the sand weighty; but a fool’s wrath is heavier than them both.

^4Wrath is cruel, and anger is outrageous; but who is able to stand before envy?

^5Open rebuke is better than secret love.

^6Faithful are the wounds of a friend; but the kisses of an enemy are deceitful.

^7The full soul loatheth an honeycomb; but to the hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet.

^8As a bird that wandereth from her nest, so is a man that wandereth from his place.

^9Ointment and perfume rejoice the heart: so doth the sweetness of a man’s friend by hearty counsel.

^10Thine own friend, and thy father’s friend, forsake not; neither go into thy brother’s house in the day of thy calamity: for better is a neighbour that is near than a brother far off.

^11My son, be wise, and make my heart glad, that I may answer him that reproacheth me.

^12A prudent man foreseeth the evil, and hideth himself; but the simple pass on, and are punished.

^13Take his garment that is surety for a stranger, and take a pledge of him for a strange woman.

^14He that blesseth his friend with a loud voice, rising early in the morning, it shall be counted a curse to him.

^15A continual dropping in a very rainy day and a contentious woman are alike.

^16Whosoever hideth her hideth the wind, and the ointment of his right hand, which bewrayeth itself.

^17Iron sharpeneth iron; so a man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend.

^18Whoso keepeth the fig tree shall eat the fruit thereof: so he that waiteth on his master shall be honoured.

^19As in water face answereth to face, so the heart of man to man.

^20Hell and destruction are never full; so the eyes of man are never satisfied.

^21As the fining pot for silver, and the furnace for gold; so is a man to his praise.

^22Though thou shouldest bray a fool in a mortar among wheat with a pestle, yet will not his foolishness depart from him.

^23Be thou diligent to know the state of thy flocks, and look well to thy herds.

^24For riches are not for ever: and doth the crown endure to every generation?

^25The hay appeareth, and the tender grass sheweth itself, and herbs of the mountains are gathered.

^26The lambs are for thy clothing, and the goats are the price of the field.

^27And thou shalt have goats’ milk enough for thy food, for the food of thy household, and for the maintenance for thy maidens.

XXVIII

^1The wicked flee when no man pursueth: but the righteous are bold as a lion.

^2For the transgression of a land many are the princes thereof: but by a man of understanding and knowledge the state thereof shall be prolonged.

^3A poor man that oppresseth the poor is like a sweeping rain which leaveth no food.

^4They that forsake the law praise the wicked: but such as keep the law contend with them.

^5Evil men understand not judgment: but they that seek the Lord understand all things.

^6Better is the poor that walketh in his uprightness, than he that is perverse in his ways, though he be rich.

^7Whoso keepeth the law is a wise son: but he that is a companion of riotous men shameth his father.

^8He that by usury and unjust gain increaseth his substance, he shall gather it for him that will pity the poor.

^9He that turneth away his ear from hearing the law, even his prayer shall be abomination.

^10Whoso causeth the righteous to go astray in an evil way, he shall fall himself into his own pit: but the upright shall have good things in possession.

^11The rich man is wise in his own conceit; but the poor that hath understanding searcheth him out.

^12When righteous men do rejoice, there is great glory: but when the wicked rise, a man is hidden.

^13He that covereth his sins shall not prosper: but whoso confesseth and forsaketh them shall have mercy.

^14Happy is the man that feareth alway: but he that hardeneth his heart shall fall into mischief.

^15As a roaring lion, and a ranging bear; so is a wicked ruler over the poor people.

^16The prince that wanteth understanding is also a great oppressor: but he that hateth covetousness shall prolong his days.

^17A man that doeth violence to the blood of any person shall flee to the pit; let no man stay him.

^18Whoso walketh uprightly shall be saved: but he that is perverse in his ways shall fall at once.

^19He that tilleth his land shall have plenty of bread: but he that followeth after vain persons shall have poverty enough.

^20A faithful man shall abound with blessings: but he that maketh haste to be rich shall not be innocent.

^21To have respect of persons is not good: for for a piece of bread that man will transgress.

^22He that hasteth to be rich hath an evil eye, and considereth not that poverty shall come upon him.

^23He that rebuketh a man afterwards shall find more favour than he that flattereth with the tongue.

^24Whoso robbeth his father or his mother, and saith, It is no transgression; the same is the companion of a destroyer.

^25He that is of a proud heart stirreth up strife: but he that putteth his trust in the Lord shall be made fat.

^26He that trusteth in his own heart is a fool: but whoso walketh wisely, he shall be delivered.

^27He that giveth unto the poor shall not lack: but he that hideth his eyes shall have many a curse.

^28When the wicked rise, men hide themselves: but when they perish, the righteous increase.

XXIX

^1He, that being often reproved hardeneth his neck, shall suddenly be destroyed, and that without remedy.

^2When the righteous are in authority, the people rejoice: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.

^3Whoso loveth wisdom rejoiceth his father: but he that keepeth company with harlots spendeth his substance.

^4The king by judgment establisheth the land: but he that receiveth gifts overthroweth it.

^5A man that flattereth his neighbour spreadeth a net for his feet.

^6In the transgression of an evil man there is a snare: but the righteous doth sing and rejoice.

^7The righteous considereth the cause of the poor: but the wicked regardeth not to know it.

^8Scornful men bring a city into a snare: but wise men turn away wrath.

^9If a wise man contendeth with a foolish man, whether he rage or laugh, there is no rest.

^10The bloodthirsty hate the upright: but the just seek his soul.

^11A fool uttereth all his mind: but a wise man keepeth it in till afterwards.

^12If a ruler hearken to lies, all his servants are wicked.

^13The poor and the deceitful man meet together: the Lord lighteneth both their eyes.

^14The king that faithfully judgeth the poor, his throne shall be established for ever.

^15The rod and reproof give wisdom: but a child left to himself bringeth his mother to shame.

^16When the wicked are multiplied, transgression increaseth: but the righteous shall see their fall.

^17Correct thy son, and he shall give thee rest; yea, he shall give delight unto thy soul.

^18Where there is no vision, the people perish: but he that keepeth the law, happy is he.

^19A servant will not be corrected by words: for though he understand he will not answer.

^20Seest thou a man that is hasty in his words? there is more hope of a fool than of him.

^21He that delicately bringeth up his servant from a child shall have him become his son at the length.

^22An angry man stirreth up strife, and a furious man aboundeth in transgression.

^23A man’s pride shall bring him low: but honour shall uphold the humble in spirit.

^24Whoso is partner with a thief hateth his own soul: he heareth cursing, and bewrayeth it not.

^25The fear of man bringeth a snare: but whoso putteth his trust in the Lord shall be safe.

^26Many seek the ruler’s favour; but every man’s judgment cometh from the Lord.

^27An unjust man is an abomination to the just: and he that is upright in the way is abomination to the wicked.

XXX

^1The words of Agur the son of Jakeh, even the prophecy: the man spake unto Ithiel, even unto Ithiel and Ucal,

^2Surely I am more brutish than any man, and have not the understanding of a man.

^3I neither learned wisdom, nor have the knowledge of the holy.

^4Who hath ascended up into heaven, or descended? who hath gathered the wind in his fists? who hath bound the waters in a garment? who hath established all the ends of the earth? what is his name, and what is his son’s name, if thou canst tell?

^5Every word of God is pure: he is a shield unto them that put their trust in him.

^6Add thou not unto his words, lest he reprove thee, and thou be found a liar.

^7Two things have I required of thee; deny me them not before I die:

^8Remove far from me vanity and lies: give me neither poverty nor riches; feed me with food convenient for me:

^9Lest I be full, and deny thee, and say, Who is the Lord? or lest I be poor, and steal, and take the name of my God in vain.

^10Accuse not a servant unto his master, lest he curse thee, and thou be found guilty.

^11There is a generation that curseth their father, and doth not bless their mother.

^12There is a generation that are pure in their own eyes, and yet is not washed from their filthiness.

^13There is a generation, O how lofty are their eyes! and their eyelids are lifted up.

^14There is a generation, whose teeth are as swords, and their jaw teeth as knives, to devour the poor from off the earth, and the needy from among men.

^15The horseleach hath two daughters, crying, Give, give. There are three things that are never satisfied, yea, four things say not, It is enough:

^16The grave; and the barren womb; the earth that is not filled with water; and the fire that saith not, It is enough.

^17The eye that mocketh at his father, and despiseth to obey his mother, the ravens of the valley shall pick it out, and the young eagles shall eat it.

^18There be three things which are too wonderful for me, yea, four which I know not:

^19The way of an eagle in the air; the way of a serpent upon a rock; the way of a ship in the midst of the sea; and the way of a man with a maid.

^20Such is the way of an adulterous woman; she eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and saith, I have done no wickedness.

^21For three things the earth is disquieted, and for four which it cannot bear:

^22For a servant when he reigneth; and a fool when he is filled with meat;

^23For an odious woman when she is married; and an handmaid that is heir to her mistress.

^24There be four things which are little upon the earth, but they are exceeding wise:

^25The ants are a people not strong, yet they prepare their meat in the summer;

^26The conies are but a feeble folk, yet make they their houses in the rocks;

^27The locusts have no king, yet go they forth all of them by bands;

^28The spider taketh hold with her hands, and is in kings’ palaces.

^29There be three things which go well, yea, four are comely in going:

^30A lion which is strongest among beasts, and turneth not away for any;

^31A greyhound; an he goat also; and a king, against whom there is no rising up.

^32If thou hast done foolishly in lifting up thyself, or if thou hast thought evil, lay thine hand upon thy mouth.

^33Surely the churning of milk bringeth forth butter, and the wringing of the nose bringeth forth blood: so the forcing of wrath bringeth forth strife.

XXXI

^1The words of king Lemuel, the prophecy that his mother taught him.

^2What, my son? and what, the son of my womb? and what, the son of my vows?

^3Give not thy strength unto women, nor thy ways to that which destroyeth kings.

^4It is not for kings, O Lemuel, it is not for kings to drink wine; nor for princes strong drink:

^5Lest they drink, and forget the law, and pervert the judgment of any of the afflicted.

^6Give strong drink unto him that is ready to perish, and wine unto those that be of heavy hearts.

^7Let him drink, and forget his poverty, and remember his misery no more.

^8Open thy mouth for the dumb in the cause of all such as are appointed to destruction.

^9Open thy mouth, judge righteously, and plead the cause of the poor and needy.

^10Who can find a virtuous woman? for her price is far above rubies.

^11The heart of her husband doth safely trust in her, so that he shall have no need of spoil.

^12She will do him good and not evil all the days of her life.

^13She seeketh wool, and flax, and worketh willingly with her hands.

^14She is like the merchants’ ships; she bringeth her food from afar.

^15She riseth also while it is yet night, and giveth meat to her household, and a portion to her maidens.

^16She considereth a field, and buyeth it: with the fruit of her hands she planteth a vineyard.

^17She girdeth her loins with strength, and strengtheneth her arms.

^18She perceiveth that her merchandise is good: her candle goeth not out by night.

^19She layeth her hands to the spindle, and her hands hold the distaff.

^20She stretcheth out her hand to the poor; yea, she reacheth forth her hands to the needy.

^21She is not afraid of the snow for her household: for all her household are clothed with scarlet.

^22She maketh herself coverings of tapestry; her clothing is silk and purple.

^23Her husband is known in the gates, when he sitteth among the elders of the land.

^24She maketh fine linen, and selleth it; and delivereth girdles unto the merchant.

^25Strength and honour are her clothing; and she shall rejoice in time to come.

^26She openeth her mouth with wisdom; and in her tongue is the law of kindness.

^27She looketh well to the ways of her household, and eateth not the bread of idleness.

^28Her children arise up, and call her blessed; her husband also, and he praiseth her.

^29Many daughters have done virtuously, but thou excellest them all.

^30Favour is deceitful, and beauty is vain: but a woman that feareth the Lord, she shall be praised.

^31Give her of the fruit of her hands; and let her own works praise her in the gates.

Ecclesiastes

The Book of

Ecclesiastes

I

^1The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem. ^2Vanity of vanities, saith the Preacher, vanity of vanities; all is vanity. ^3What profit hath a man of all his labour which he taketh under the sun? ^4One generation passeth away, and another generation cometh: but the earth abideth for ever. ^5The sun also ariseth, and the sun goeth down, and hasteth to his place where he arose. ^6The wind goeth toward the south, and turneth about unto the north; it whirleth about continually, and the wind returneth again according to his circuits. ^7All the rivers run into the sea; yet the sea is not full; unto the place from whence the rivers come, thither they return again. ^8All things are full of labour; man cannot utter it: the eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing. ^9The thing that hath been, it is that which shall be; and that which is done is that which shall be done: and there is no new thing under the sun. ^10Is there any thing whereof it may be said, See, this is new? it hath been already of old time, which was before us. ^11There is no remembrance of former things; neither shall there be any remembrance of things that are to come with those that shall come after.

^12I the Preacher was king over Israel in Jerusalem. ^13And I gave my heart to seek and search out by wisdom concerning all things that are done under heaven: this sore travail hath God given to the sons of man to be exercised therewith. ^14I have seen all the works that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and vexation of spirit. ^15That which is crooked cannot be made straight: and that which is wanting cannot be numbered. ^16I communed with mine own heart, saying, Lo, I am come to great estate, and have gotten more wisdom than all they that have been before me in Jerusalem: yea, my heart had great experience of wisdom and knowledge. ^17And I gave my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I perceived that this also is vexation of spirit. ^18For in much wisdom is much grief: and he that increaseth knowledge increaseth sorrow.

II

^1I said in mine heart, Go to now, I will prove thee with mirth, therefore enjoy pleasure: and, behold, this also is vanity. ^2I said of laughter, It is mad: and of mirth, What doeth it? ^3I sought in mine heart to give myself unto wine, yet acquainting mine heart with wisdom; and to lay hold on folly, till I might see what was that good for the sons of men, which they should do under the heaven all the days of their life. ^4I made me great works; I builded me houses; I planted me vineyards: ^5I made me gardens and orchards, and I planted trees in them of all kind of fruits: ^6I made me pools of water, to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees: ^7I got me servants and maidens, and had servants born in my house; also I had great possessions of great and small cattle above all that were in Jerusalem before me: ^8I gathered me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces: I gat me men singers and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, as musical instruments, and that of all sorts. ^9So I was great, and increased more than all that were before me in Jerusalem: also my wisdom remained with me. ^10And whatsoever mine eyes desired I kept not from them, I withheld not my heart from any joy; for my heart rejoiced in all my labour: and this was my portion of all my labour. ^11Then I looked on all the works that my hands had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and, behold, all was vanity and vexation of spirit, and there was no profit under the sun.

^12And I turned myself to behold wisdom, and madness, and folly: for what can the man do that cometh after the king? even that which hath been already done. ^13Then I saw that wisdom excelleth folly, as far as light excelleth darkness. ^14The wise man’s eyes are in his head; but the fool walketh in darkness: and I myself perceived also that one event happeneth to them all. ^15Then said I in my heart, As it happeneth to the fool, so it happeneth even to me; and why was I then more wise? Then I said in my heart, that this also is vanity. ^16For there is no remembrance of the wise more than of the fool for ever; seeing that which now is in the days to come shall all be forgotten. And how dieth the wise man? as the fool.

^17Therefore I hated life; because the work that is wrought under the sun is grievous unto me: for all is vanity and vexation of spirit.

^18Yea, I hated all my labour which I had taken under the sun: because I should leave it unto the man that shall be after me. ^19And who knoweth whether he shall be a wise man or a fool? yet shall he have rule over all my labour wherein I have laboured, and wherein I have shewed myself wise under the sun. This is also vanity. ^20Therefore I went about to cause my heart to despair of all the labour which I took under the sun. ^21For there is a man whose labour is in wisdom, and in knowledge, and in equity; yet to a man that hath not laboured therein shall he leave it for his portion. This also is vanity and a great evil. ^22For what hath man of all his labour, and of the vexation of his heart, wherein he hath laboured under the sun? ^23For all his days are sorrows, and his travail grief; yea, his heart taketh not rest in the night. This is also vanity.

^24There is nothing better for a man, than that he should eat and drink, and that he should make his soul enjoy good in his labour. This also I saw, that it was from the hand of God. ^25For who can eat, or who else can hasten hereunto, more than I? ^26For God giveth to a man that is good in his sight wisdom, and knowledge, and joy: but to the sinner he giveth travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him that is good before God. This also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

III

^1To every thing there is a season, and a time to every purpose under the heaven:

^2A time to be born,
and a time to die;
a time to plant,
and a time to pluck up that which is planted;
^3A time to kill,
and a time to heal;
a time to break down,
and a time to build up;
^4A time to weep,
and a time to laugh;
a time to mourn,
and a time to dance;
^5A time to cast away stones,
and a time to gather stones together;
a time to embrace,
and a time to refrain from embracing;
^6A time to get,
and a time to lose;
a time to keep,
and a time to cast away;
^7A time to rend,
and a time to sew;
a time to keep silence,
and a time to speak;
^8A time to love,
and a time to hate;
a time of war,
and a time of peace.

^9What profit hath he that worketh in that wherein he laboureth? ^10I have seen the travail, which God hath given to the sons of men to be exercised in it. ^11He hath made every thing beautiful in his time: also he hath set the world in their heart, so that no man can find out the work that God maketh from the beginning to the end. ^12I know that there is no good in them, but for a man to rejoice, and to do good in his life. ^13And also that every man should eat and drink, and enjoy the good of all his labour, it is the gift of God. ^14I know that, whatsoever God doeth, it shall be for ever: nothing can be put to it, nor any thing taken from it: and God doeth it, that men should fear before him. ^15That which hath been is now; and that which is to be hath already been; and God requireth that which is past.

^16And moreover I saw under the sun the place of judgment, that wickedness was there; and the place of righteousness, that iniquity was there. ^17I said in mine heart, God shall judge the righteous and the wicked: for there is a time there for every purpose and for every work. ^18I said in mine heart concerning the estate of the sons of men, that God might manifest them, and that they might see that they themselves are beasts. ^19For that which befalleth the sons of men befalleth beasts; even one thing befalleth them: as the one dieth, so dieth the other; yea, they have all one breath; so that a man hath no preeminence above a beast: for all is vanity. ^20All go unto one place; all are of the dust, and all turn to dust again. ^21Who knoweth the spirit of man that goeth upward, and the spirit of the beast that goeth downward to the earth? ^22Wherefore I perceive that there is nothing better, than that a man should rejoice in his own works; for that is his portion: for who shall bring him to see what shall be after him?

IV

^1So I returned, and considered all the oppressions that are done under the sun: and behold the tears of such as were oppressed, and they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was power; but they had no comforter. ^2Wherefore I praised the dead which are already dead more than the living which are yet alive. ^3Yea, better is he than both they, which hath not yet been, who hath not seen the evil work that is done under the sun.

^4Again, I considered all travail, and every right work, that for this a man is envied of his neighbour. This is also vanity and vexation of spirit. ^5The fool foldeth his hands together, and eateth his own flesh. ^6Better is an handful with quietness, than both the hands full with travail and vexation of spirit.

^7Then I returned, and I saw vanity under the sun. ^8There is one alone, and there is not a second; yea, he hath neither child nor brother: yet is there no end of all his labour; neither is his eye satisfied with riches; neither saith he, For whom do I labour, and bereave my soul of good? This is also vanity, yea, it is a sore travail. ^9Two are better than one; because they have a good reward for their labour. ^10For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow: but woe to him that is alone when he falleth; for he hath not another to help him up. ^11Again, if two lie together, then they have heat: but how can one be warm alone? ^12And if one prevail against him, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not quickly broken.

^13Better is a poor and a wise child than an old and foolish king, who will no more be admonished. ^14For out of prison he cometh to reign; whereas also he that is born in his kingdom becometh poor. ^15I considered all the living which walk under the sun, with the second child that shall stand up in his stead. ^16There is no end of all the people, even of all that have been before them: they also that come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

V

^1Keep thy foot when thou goest to the house of God, and be more ready to hear, than to give the sacrifice of fools: for they consider not that they do evil. ^2Be not rash with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be hasty to utter any thing before God: for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth: therefore let thy words be few. ^3For a dream cometh through the multitude of business; and a fool’s voice is known by multitude of words. ^4When thou vowest a vow unto God, defer not to pay it; for he hath no pleasure in fools: pay that which thou hast vowed. ^5Better is it that thou shouldest not vow, than that thou shouldest vow and not pay. ^6Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin; neither say thou before the angel, that it was an error: wherefore should God be angry at thy voice, and destroy the work of thine hands? ^7For in the multitude of dreams and many words there are also divers vanities: but fear thou God.

^8If thou seest the oppression of the poor, and violent perverting of judgment and justice in a province, marvel not at the matter: for he that is higher than the highest regardeth; and there be higher than they. ^9Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field.

^10He that loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he that loveth abundance with increase: this is also vanity. ^11When goods increase, they are increased that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, saving the beholding of them with their eyes? ^12The sleep of a labouring man is sweet, whether he eat little or much: but the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleep.

^13There is a sore evil which I have seen under the sun, namely, riches kept for the owners thereof to their hurt. ^14But those riches perish by evil travail: and he begetteth a son, and there is nothing in his hand. ^15As he came forth of his mother’s womb, naked shall he return to go as he came, and shall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand. ^16And this also is a sore evil, that in all points as he came, so shall he go: and what profit hath he that hath laboured for the wind? ^17All his days also he eateth in darkness, and he hath much sorrow and wrath with his sickness.

^18Behold that which I have seen: it is good and comely for one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy the good of all his labour that he taketh under the sun all the days of his life, which God giveth him: for it is his portion. ^19Every man also to whom God hath given riches and wealth, and hath given him power to eat thereof, and to take his portion, and to rejoice in his labour; this is the gift of God. ^20For he shall not much remember the days of his life; because God answereth him in the joy of his heart.

VI

^1There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is common among men: ^2a man to whom God hath given riches, wealth, and honour, so that he wanteth nothing for his soul of all that he desireth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a stranger eateth it: this is vanity, and it is an evil disease. ^3If a man beget an hundred children, and live many years, so that the days of his years be many, and his soul be not filled with good, and also that he have no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is better than he. ^4For he cometh in with vanity, and departeth in darkness, and his name shall be covered with darkness. ^5Moreover he hath not seen the sun, nor known any thing: this hath more rest than the other. ^6Yea, though he live a thousand years twice told, yet hath he seen no good: do not all go to one place?

^7All the labour of man is for his mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled. ^8For what hath the wise more than the fool? what hath the poor, that knoweth to walk before the living? ^9Better is the sight of the eyes than the wandering of the desire: this is also vanity and vexation of spirit.

^10That which hath been is named already, and it is known that it is man: neither may he contend with him that is mightier than he. ^11Seeing there be many things that increase vanity, what is man the better? ^12For who knoweth what is good for man in this life, all the days of his vain life which he spendeth as a shadow? for who can tell a man what shall be after him under the sun?

VII

^1A good name is better than precious ointment; and the day of death than the day of one’s birth. ^2It is better to go to the house of mourning, than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the end of all men; and the living will lay it to his heart. ^3Sorrow is better than laughter: for by the sadness of the countenance the heart is made better. ^4The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but the heart of fools is in the house of mirth.

^5It is better to hear the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools. ^6For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the fool: this also is vanity. ^7Surely oppression maketh a wise man mad; and a gift destroyeth the heart.

^8Better is the end of a thing than the beginning thereof: and the patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit. ^9Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry: for anger resteth in the bosom of fools. ^10Say not thou, What is the cause that the former days were better than these? for thou dost not enquire wisely concerning this.

^11Wisdom is good with an inheritance: and by it there is profit to them that see the sun. ^12For wisdom is a defence, and money is a defence: but the excellency of knowledge is, that wisdom giveth life to them that have it. ^13Consider the work of God: for who can make that straight, which he hath made crooked? ^14In the day of prosperity be joyful, but in the day of adversity consider: God also hath set the one over against the other, to the end that man should find nothing after him.

^15All things have I seen in the days of my vanity: there is a just man that perisheth in his righteousness, and there is a wicked man that prolongeth his life in his wickedness. ^16Be not righteous over much; neither make thyself over wise: why shouldest thou destroy thyself? ^17Be not over much wicked, neither be thou foolish: why shouldest thou die before thy time? ^18It is good that thou shouldest take hold of this; yea, also from this withdraw not thine hand: for he that feareth God shall come forth of them all.

^19Wisdom strengtheneth the wise more than ten mighty men which are in the city. ^20For there is not a just man upon earth, that doeth good, and sinneth not. ^21Also take no heed unto all words that are spoken; lest thou hear thy servant curse thee: ^22for oftentimes also thine own heart knoweth that thou thyself likewise hast cursed others.

^23All this have I proved by wisdom: I said, I will be wise; but it was far from me. ^24That which is far off, and exceeding deep, who can find it out? ^25I applied mine heart to know, and to search, and to seek out wisdom, and the reason of things, and to know the wickedness of folly, even of foolishness and madness: ^26and I find more bitter than death the woman, whose heart is snares and nets, and her hands as bands: whoso pleaseth God shall escape from her; but the sinner shall be taken by her. ^27Behold, this have I found, saith the preacher, counting one by one, to find out the account: ^28which yet my soul seeketh, but I find not: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all those have I not found. ^29Lo, this only have I found, that God hath made man upright; but they have sought out many inventions.

VIII

^1Who is as the wise man? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? a man’s wisdom maketh his face to shine, and the boldness of his face shall be changed. ^2I counsel thee to keep the king’s commandment, and that in regard of the oath of God. ^3Be not hasty to go out of his sight: stand not in an evil thing; for he doeth whatsoever pleaseth him. ^4Where the word of a king is, there is power: and who may say unto him, What doest thou? ^5Whoso keepeth the commandment shall feel no evil thing: and a wise man’s heart discerneth both time and judgment. ^6Because to every purpose there is time and judgment, therefore the misery of man is great upon him. ^7For he knoweth not that which shall be: for who can tell him when it shall be? ^8There is no man that hath power over the spirit to retain the spirit; neither hath he power in the day of death: and there is no discharge in that war; neither shall wickedness deliver those that are given to it.

^9All this have I seen, and applied my heart unto every work that is done under the sun: there is a time wherein one man ruleth over another to his own hurt. ^10And so I saw the wicked buried, who had come and gone from the place of the holy, and they were forgotten in the city where they had so done: this is also vanity. ^11Because sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil. ^12Though a sinner do evil an hundred times, and his days be prolonged, yet surely I know that it shall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him: ^13but it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he prolong his days, which are as a shadow; because he feareth not before God.

^14There is a vanity which is done upon the earth; that there be just men, unto whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked; again, there be wicked men, to whom it happeneth according to the work of the righteous: I said that this also is vanity. ^15Then I commended mirth, because a man hath no better thing under the sun, than to eat, and to drink, and to be merry: for that shall abide with him of his labour the days of his life, which God giveth him under the sun.

^16When I applied mine heart to know wisdom, and to see the business that is done upon the earth: (for also there is that neither day nor night seeth sleep with his eyes:) ^17then I beheld all the work of God, that a man cannot find out the work that is done under the sun: because though a man labour to seek it out, yet he shall not find it; yea farther; though a wise man think to know it, yet shall he not be able to find it.

IX

^1For all this I considered in my heart even to declare all this, that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of God: no man knoweth either love or hatred by all that is before them.

^2All things come alike to all: there is one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not: as is the good, so is the sinner; and he that sweareth, as he that feareth an oath. ^3This is an evil among all things that are done under the sun, that there is one event unto all: yea, also the heart of the sons of men is full of evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that they go to the dead.

^4For to him that is joined to all the living there is hope: for a living dog is better than a dead lion. ^5For the living know that they shall die: but the dead know not any thing, neither have they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten. ^6Also their love, and their hatred, and their envy, is now perished; neither have they any more a portion for ever in any thing that is done under the sun.

^7Go thy way, eat thy bread with joy, and drink thy wine with a merry heart; for God now accepteth thy works. ^8Let thy garments be always white; and let thy head lack no ointment. ^9Live joyfully with the wife whom thou lovest all the days of the life of thy vanity, which he hath given thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity: for that is thy portion in this life, and in thy labour which thou takest under the sun. ^10Whatsoever thy hand findeth to do, do it with thy might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave, whither thou goest.

^11I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise, nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance happeneth to them all. ^12For man also knoweth not his time: as the fishes that are taken in an evil net, and as the birds that are caught in the snare; so are the sons of men snared in an evil time, when it falleth suddenly upon them.

^13This wisdom have I seen also under the sun, and it seemed great unto me: ^14there was a little city, and few men within it; and there came a great king against it, and besieged it, and built great bulwarks against it: ^15now there was found in it a poor wise man, and he by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor man. ^16Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength: nevertheless the poor man’s wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard. ^17The words of wise men are heard in quiet more than the cry of him that ruleth among fools. ^18Wisdom is better than weapons of war: but one sinner destroyeth much good.

X

^1Dead flies cause the ointment of the apothecary to send forth a stinking savour: so doth a little folly him that is in reputation for wisdom and honour. ^2A wise man’s heart is at his right hand; but a fool’s heart at his left. ^3Yea also, when he that is a fool walketh by the way, his wisdom faileth him, and he saith to every one that he is a fool. ^4If the spirit of the ruler rise up against thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifieth great offences. ^5There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, as an error which proceedeth from the ruler: ^6folly is set in great dignity, and the rich sit in low place. ^7I have seen servants upon horses, and princes walking as servants upon the earth.

^8He that diggeth a pit shall fall into it; and whoso breaketh an hedge, a serpent shall bite him. ^9Whoso removeth stones shall be hurt therewith; and he that cleaveth wood shall be endangered thereby. ^10If the iron be blunt, and he do not whet the edge, then must he put to more strength: but wisdom is profitable to direct. ^11Surely the serpent will bite without enchantment; and a babbler is no better.

^12The words of a wise man’s mouth are gracious; but the lips of a fool will swallow up himself. ^13The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness: and the end of his talk is mischievous madness. ^14A fool also is full of words: a man cannot tell what shall be; and what shall be after him, who can tell him? ^15The labour of the foolish wearieth every one of them, because he knoweth not how to go to the city.

^16Woe to thee, O land, when thy king is a child, and thy princes eat in the morning! ^17Blessed art thou, O land, when thy king is the son of nobles, and thy princes eat in due season, for strength, and not for drunkenness! ^18By much slothfulness the building decayeth; and through idleness of the hands the house droppeth through. ^19A feast is made for laughter, and wine maketh merry: but money answereth all things. ^20Curse not the king, no not in thy thought; and curse not the rich in thy bedchamber: for a bird of the air shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall tell the matter.

XI

^1Cast thy bread upon the waters: for thou shalt find it after many days. ^2Give a portion to seven, and also to eight; for thou knowest not what evil shall be upon the earth. ^3If the clouds be full of rain, they empty themselves upon the earth: and if the tree fall toward the south, or toward the north, in the place where the tree falleth, there it shall be. ^4He that observeth the wind shall not sow; and he that regardeth the clouds shall not reap. ^5As thou knowest not what is the way of the spirit, nor how the bones do grow in the womb of her that is with child: even so thou knowest not the works of God who maketh all. ^6In the morning sow thy seed, and in the evening withhold not thine hand: for thou knowest not whether shall prosper, either this or that, or whether they both shall be alike good. ^7Truly the light is sweet, and a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to behold the sun: ^8but if a man live many years, and rejoice in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkness; for they shall be many. All that cometh is vanity.

^9Rejoice, O young man, in thy youth; and let thy heart cheer thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thine heart, and in the sight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all these things God will bring thee into judgment. ^10Therefore remove sorrow from thy heart, and put away evil from thy flesh: for childhood and youth are vanity.

XII

^1Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou shalt say, I have no pleasure in them; ^2while the sun, or the light, or the moon, or the stars, be not darkened, nor the clouds return after the rain: ^3in the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble, and the strong men shall bow themselves, and the grinders cease because they are few, and those that look out of the windows be darkened, ^4and the doors shall be shut in the streets, when the sound of the grinding is low, and he shall rise up at the voice of the bird, and all the daughters of musick shall be brought low; ^5also when they shall be afraid of that which is high, and fears shall be in the way, and the almond tree shall flourish, and the grasshopper shall be a burden, and desire shall fail: because man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the streets: ^6or ever the silver cord be loosed, or the golden bowl be broken, or the pitcher be broken at the fountain, or the wheel broken at the cistern. ^7Then shall the dust return to the earth as it was: and the spirit shall return unto God who gave it. ^8Vanity of vanities, saith the preacher; all is vanity. ^9And moreover, because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge; yea, he gave good heed, and sought out, and set in order many proverbs. ^10The preacher sought to find out acceptable words: and that which was written was upright, even words of truth.

^11The words of the wise are as goads, and as nails fastened by the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd. ^12And further, by these, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh.

^13Let us hear the conclusion of the whole matter: Fear God, and keep his commandments: for this is the whole duty of man. ^14For God shall bring every work into judgment, with every secret thing, whether it be good, or whether it be evil.

Song of Solomon 1

1^1The song of songs, which is Solomon’s.

^2Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth: for thy love is better than wine.

^3Because of the savour of thy good ointments thy name is as ointment poured forth, therefore do the virgins love thee.

^4Draw me, we will run after thee: the king hath brought me into his chambers: we will be glad and rejoice in thee, we will remember thy love more than wine: the upright love thee.

^5I am black, but comely, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, as the tents of Kedar, as the curtains of Solomon.

^6Look not upon me, because I am black, because the sun hath looked upon me: my mother’s children were angry with me; they made me the keeper of the vineyards; but mine own vineyard have I not kept.

^7Tell me, O thou whom my soul loveth, where thou feedest, where thou makest thy flock to rest at noon: for why should I be as one that turneth aside by the flocks of thy companions?

^8If thou know not, O thou fairest among women, go thy way forth by the footsteps of the flock, and feed thy kids beside the shepherds’ tents.

^9I have compared thee, O my love, to a company of horses in Pharaoh’s chariots.

^10Thy cheeks are comely with rows of jewels, thy neck with chains of gold.

^11We will make thee borders of gold with studs of silver.

^12While the king sitteth at his table, my spikenard sendeth forth the smell thereof.

^13A bundle of myrrh is my well-beloved unto me; he shall lie all night betwixt my breasts.

^14My beloved is unto me as a cluster of camphire in the vineyards of Engedi.

^15Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; thou hast doves’ eyes.

^16Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant: also our bed is green.

^17The beams of our house are cedar, and our rafters of fir.

Song of Solomon 2

2^1I am the rose of Sharon, and the lily of the valleys.

^2As the lily among thorns, so is my love among the daughters.

^3As the apple tree among the trees of the wood, so is my beloved among the sons. I sat down under his shadow with great delight, and his fruit was sweet to my taste.

^4He brought me to the banqueting house, and his banner over me was love.

^5Stay me with flagons, comfort me with apples: for I am sick of love.

^6His left hand is under my head, and his right hand doth embrace me.

^7I charge you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and by the hinds of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.

^8The voice of my beloved! behold, he cometh leaping upon the mountains, skipping upon the hills.

^9My beloved is like a roe or a young hart: behold, he standeth behind our wall, he looketh forth at the windows, shewing himself through the lattice.

^10My beloved spake, and said unto me, Rise up, my love, my fair one, and come away.

^11For, lo, the winter is past, the rain is over and gone;

^12The flowers appear on the earth; the time of the singing of birds is come, and the voice of the turtle is heard in our land;

^13The fig tree putteth forth her green figs, and the vines with the tender grape give a good smell. Arise, my love, my fair one, and come away.

^14O my dove, that art in the clefts of the rock, in the secret places of the stairs, let me see thy countenance, let me hear thy voice; for sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.

^15Take us the foxes, the little foxes, that spoil the vines: for our vines have tender grapes.

^16My beloved is mine, and I am his: he feedeth among the lilies.

^17Until the day break, and the shadows flee away, turn, my beloved, and be thou like a roe or a young hart upon the mountains of Bether.

Song of Solomon 3

3^1By night on my bed I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.

^2I will rise now, and go about the city in the streets, and in the broad ways I will seek him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.

^3The watchmen that go about the city found me: to whom I said, Saw ye him whom my soul loveth?

^4It was but a little that I passed from them, but I found him whom my soul loveth: I held him, and would not let him go, until I had brought him into my mother’s house, and into the chamber of her that conceived me.

^5I charge you, O ye daughters of Jerusalem, by the roes, and by the hinds of the field, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, till he please.

^6Who is this that cometh out of the wilderness like pillars of smoke, perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, with all powders of the merchant?

^7Behold his bed, which is Solomon’s; threescore valiant men are about it, of the valiant of Israel.

^8They all hold swords, being expert in war: every man hath his sword upon his thigh because of fear in the night.

^9King Solomon made himself a chariot of the wood of Lebanon.

^10He made the pillars thereof of silver, the bottom thereof of gold, the covering of it of purple, the midst thereof being paved with love, for the daughters of Jerusalem.

^11Go forth, O ye daughters of Zion, and behold king Solomon with the crown wherewith his mother crowned him in the day of his espousals, and in the day of the gladness of his heart.

Song of Solomon 4

4^1Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair; thou hast doves’ eyes within thy locks: thy hair is as a flock of goats, that appear from mount Gilead.

^2Thy teeth are like a flock of sheep that are even shorn, which came up from the washing; whereof every one bear twins, and none is barren among them.

^3Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet, and thy speech is comely: thy temples are like a piece of a pomegranate within thy locks.

^4Thy neck is like the tower of David builded for an armoury, whereon there hang a thousand bucklers, all shields of mighty men.

^5Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins, which feed among the lilies.

^6Until the day break, and the shadows flee away, I will get me to the mountain of myrrh, and to the hill of frankincense.

^7Thou art all fair, my love; there is no spot in thee.

^8Come with me from Lebanon, my spouse, with me from Lebanon: look from the top of Amana, from the top of Shenir and Hermon, from the lions’ dens, from the mountains of the leopards.

^9Thou hast ravished my heart, my sister, my spouse; thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes, with one chain of thy neck.

^10How fair is thy love, my sister, my spouse! how much better is thy love than wine! and the smell of thine ointments than all spices!

^11Thy lips, O my spouse, drop as the honeycomb: honey and milk are under thy tongue; and the smell of thy garments is like the smell of Lebanon.

^12A garden inclosed is my sister, my spouse; a spring shut up, a fountain sealed.

^13Thy plants are an orchard of pomegranates, with pleasant fruits; camphire, with spikenard,

^14Spikenard and saffron; calamus and cinnamon, with all trees of frankincense; myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices:

^15A fountain of gardens, a well of living waters, and streams from Lebanon.

^16Awake, O north wind; and come, thou south; blow upon my garden, that the spices thereof may flow out. Let my beloved come into his garden, and eat his pleasant fruits.

Song of Solomon 5

5^1I am come into my garden, my sister, my spouse: I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk: eat, O friends; drink, yea, drink abundantly, O beloved.

^2I sleep, but my heart waketh: it is the voice of my beloved that knocketh, saying, Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled: for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night.

^3I have put off my coat; how shall I put it on? I have washed my feet; how shall I defile them?

^4My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door, and my bowels were moved for him.

^5I rose up to open to my beloved; and my hands dropped with myrrh, and my fingers with sweet smelling myrrh, upon the handles of the lock.

^6I opened to my beloved; but my beloved had withdrawn himself, and was gone: my soul failed when he spake: I sought him, but I could not find him; I called him, but he gave me no answer.

^7The watchmen that went about the city found me, they smote me, they wounded me; the keepers of the walls took away my veil from me.

^8I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, if ye find my beloved, that ye tell him, that I am sick of love.

^9What is thy beloved more than another beloved, O thou fairest among women? what is thy beloved more than another beloved, that thou dost so charge us?

^10My beloved is white and ruddy, the chiefest among ten thousand.

^11His head is as the most fine gold, his locks are bushy, and black as a raven.

^12His eyes are as the eyes of doves by the rivers of waters, washed with milk, and fitly set.

^13His cheeks are as a bed of spices, as sweet flowers: his lips like lilies, dropping sweet smelling myrrh.

^14His hands are as gold rings set with the beryl: his belly is as bright ivory overlaid with sapphires.

^15His legs are as pillars of marble, set upon sockets of fine gold: his countenance is as Lebanon, excellent as the cedars.

^16His mouth is most sweet: yea, he is altogether lovely. This is my beloved, and this is my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem.

Song of Solomon 6

6^1Whither is thy beloved gone, O thou fairest among women? whither is thy beloved turned aside? that we may seek him with thee.

^2My beloved is gone down into his garden, to the beds of spices, to feed in the gardens, and to gather lilies.

^3I am my beloved’s, and my beloved is mine: he feedeth among the lilies.

^4Thou art beautiful, O my love, as Tirzah, comely as Jerusalem, terrible as an army with banners.

^5Turn away thine eyes from me, for they have overcome me: thy hair is as a flock of goats that appear from Gilead.

^6Thy teeth are as a flock of sheep which go up from the washing, whereof every one beareth twins, and there is not one barren among them.

^7As a piece of a pomegranate are thy temples within thy locks.

^8There are threescore queens, and fourscore concubines, and virgins without number.

^9My dove, my undefiled is but one; she is the only one of her mother, she is the choice one of her that bare her. The daughters saw her, and blessed her; yea, the queens and the concubines, and they praised her.

^10Who is she that looketh forth as the morning, fair as the moon, clear as the sun, and terrible as an army with banners?

^11I went down into the garden of nuts to see the fruits of the valley, and to see whether the vine flourished and the pomegranates budded.

^12Or ever I was aware, my soul made me like the chariots of Amminadib.

^13Return, return, O Shulamite; return, return, that we may look upon thee. What will ye see in the Shulamite? As it were the company of two armies.

Song of Solomon 7

7^1How beautiful are thy feet with shoes, O prince’s daughter! the joints of thy thighs are like jewels, the work of the hands of a cunning workman.

^2Thy navel is like a round goblet, which wanteth not liquor: thy belly is like an heap of wheat set about with lilies.

^3Thy two breasts are like two young roes that are twins.

^4Thy neck is as a tower of ivory; thine eyes like the fishpools in Heshbon, by the gate of Bathrabbim: thy nose is as the tower of Lebanon which looketh toward Damascus.

^5Thine head upon thee is like Carmel, and the hair of thine head like purple; the king is held in the galleries.

^6How fair and how pleasant art thou, O love, for delights!

^7This thy stature is like to a palm tree, and thy breasts to clusters of grapes.

^8I said, I will go up to the palm tree, I will take hold of the boughs thereof: now also thy breasts shall be as clusters of the vine, and the smell of thy nose like apples;

^9And the roof of thy mouth like the best wine for my beloved, that goeth down sweetly, causing the lips of those that are asleep to speak.

^10I am my beloved’s, and his desire is toward me.

^11Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the field; let us lodge in the villages.

^12Let us get up early to the vineyards; let us see if the vine flourish, whether the tender grape appear, and the pomegranates bud forth: there will I give thee my loves.

^13The mandrakes give a smell, and at our gates are all manner of pleasant fruits, new and old, which I have laid up for thee, O my beloved.

Song of Solomon 8

8^1O that thou wert as my brother, that sucked the breasts of my mother! when I should find thee without, I would kiss thee; yea, I should not be despised.

^2I would lead thee, and bring thee into my mother’s house, who would instruct me: I would cause thee to drink of spiced wine of the juice of my pomegranate.

^3His left hand should be under my head, and his right hand should embrace me.

^4I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, that ye stir not up, nor awake my love, until he please.

^5Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness, leaning upon her beloved? I raised thee up under the apple tree: there thy mother brought thee forth: there she brought thee forth that bare thee.

^6Set me as a seal upon thine heart, as a seal upon thine arm: for love is strong as death; jealousy is cruel as the grave: the coals thereof are coals of fire, which hath a most vehement flame.

^7Many waters cannot quench love, neither can the floods drown it: if a man would give all the substance of his house for love, it would utterly be contemned.

^8We have a little sister, and she hath no breasts: what shall we do for our sister in the day when she shall be spoken for?

^9If she be a wall, we will build upon her a palace of silver: and if she be a door, we will inclose her with boards of cedar.

^10I am a wall, and my breasts like towers: then was I in his eyes as one that found favour.

^11Solomon had a vineyard at Baalhamon; he let out the vineyard unto keepers; every one for the fruit thereof was to bring a thousand pieces of silver.

^12My vineyard, which is mine, is before me: thou, O Solomon, must have a thousand, and those that keep the fruit thereof two hundred.

^13Thou that dwellest in the gardens, the companions hearken to thy voice: cause me to hear it.

^14Make haste, my beloved, and be thou like to a roe or to a young hart upon the mountains of spices.

Isaiah 1

1^1The vision of Isaiah the son of Amoz, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah.

^2Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth: for the Lord hath spoken, I have nourished and brought up children, and they have rebelled against me.

^3The ox knoweth his owner, and the ass his master’s crib: but Israel doth not know, my people doth not consider.

^4Ah sinful nation, a people laden with iniquity, a seed of evildoers, children that are corrupters: they have forsaken the Lord, they have provoked the Holy One of Israel unto anger, they are gone away backward.

^5Why should ye be stricken any more? ye will revolt more and more: the whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint.

^6From the sole of the foot even unto the head there is no soundness in it; but wounds, and bruises, and putrifying sores: they have not been closed, neither bound up, neither mollified with ointment.

^7Your country is desolate, your cities are burned with fire: your land, strangers devour it in your presence, and it is desolate, as overthrown by strangers.

^8And the daughter of Zion is left as a cottage in a vineyard, as a lodge in a garden of cucumbers, as a besieged city.

^9Except the Lord of hosts had left unto us a very small remnant, we should have been as Sodom, and we should have been like unto Gomorrah.

^10Hear the word of the Lord, ye rulers of Sodom; give ear unto the law of our God, ye people of Gomorrah.

^11To what purpose is the multitude of your sacrifices unto me? saith the Lord: I am full of the burnt offerings of rams, and the fat of fed beasts; and I delight not in the blood of bullocks, or of lambs, or of he goats.

^12When ye come to appear before me, who hath required this at your hand, to tread my courts?

^13Bring no more vain oblations; incense is an abomination unto me; the new moons and sabbaths, the calling of assemblies, I cannot away with; it is iniquity, even the solemn meeting.

^14Your new moons and your appointed feasts my soul hateth: they are a trouble unto me; I am weary to bear them.

^15And when ye spread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you: yea, when ye make many prayers, I will not hear: your hands are full of blood.

^16Wash you, make you clean; put away the evil of your doings from before mine eyes; cease to do evil;

^17Learn to do well; seek judgment, relieve the oppressed, judge the fatherless, plead for the widow.

^18Come now, and let us reason together, saith the Lord: though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they be red like crimson, they shall be as wool.

^19If ye be willing and obedient, ye shall eat the good of the land:

^20But if ye refuse and rebel, ye shall be devoured with the sword: for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.

^21How is the faithful city become an harlot! it was full of judgment; righteousness lodged in it; but now murderers.

^22Thy silver is become dross, thy wine mixed with water:

^23Thy princes are rebellious, and companions of thieves: every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards: they judge not the fatherless, neither doth the cause of the widow come unto them.

^24Therefore saith the Lord, the Lord of hosts, the mighty One of Israel, Ah, I will ease me of mine adversaries, and avenge me of mine enemies:

^25And I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy dross, and take away all thy tin:

^26And I will restore thy judges as at the first, and thy counsellors as at the beginning: afterward thou shalt be called, The city of righteousness, the faithful city.

^27Zion shall be redeemed with judgment, and her converts with righteousness.

^28And the destruction of the transgressors and of the sinners shall be together, and they that forsake the Lord shall be consumed.

^29For they shall be ashamed of the oaks which ye have desired, and ye shall be confounded for the gardens that ye have chosen.

^30For ye shall be as an oak whose leaf fadeth, and as a garden that hath no water.

^31And the strong shall be as tow, and the maker of it as a spark, and they shall both burn together, and none shall quench them.

Isaiah 2

2^1The word that Isaiah the son of Amoz saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem.

^2And it shall come to pass in the last days, that the mountain of the Lord’s house shall be established in the top of the mountains, and shall be exalted above the hills; and all nations shall flow unto it.

^3And many people shall go and say, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths: for out of Zion shall go forth the law, and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem.

^4And he shall judge among the nations, and shall rebuke many people: and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruninghooks: nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more.

^5O house of Jacob, come ye, and let us walk in the light of the Lord.

^6Therefore thou hast forsaken thy people the house of Jacob, because they be replenished from the east, and are soothsayers like the Philistines, and they please themselves in the children of strangers.

^7Their land also is full of silver and gold, neither is there any end of their treasures; their land is also full of horses, neither is there any end of their chariots:

^8Their land also is full of idols; they worship the work of their own hands, that which their own fingers have made:

^9And the mean man boweth down, and the great man humbleth himself: therefore forgive them not.

^10Enter into the rock, and hide thee in the dust, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his majesty.

^11The lofty looks of man shall be humbled, and the haughtiness of men shall be bowed down, and the Lord alone shall be exalted in that day.

^12For the day of the Lord of hosts shall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up; and he shall be brought low:

^13And upon all the cedars of Lebanon, that are high and lifted up, and upon all the oaks of Bashan,

^14And upon all the high mountains, and upon all the hills that are lifted up,

^15And upon every high tower, and upon every fenced wall,

^16And upon all the ships of Tarshish, and upon all pleasant pictures.

^17And the loftiness of man shall be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men shall be made low: and the Lord alone shall be exalted in that day.

^18And the idols he shall utterly abolish.

^19And they shall go into the holes of the rocks, and into the caves of the earth, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake terribly the earth.

^20In that day a man shall cast his idols of silver, and his idols of gold, which they made each one for himself to worship, to the moles and to the bats;

^21To go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the tops of the ragged rocks, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake terribly the earth.

^22Cease ye from man, whose breath is in his nostrils: for wherein is he to be accounted of?

Isaiah 3

3^1For, behold, the Lord, the Lord of hosts, doth take away from Jerusalem and from Judah the stay and the staff, the whole stay of bread, and the whole stay of water.

^2The mighty man, and the man of war, the judge, and the prophet, and the prudent, and the ancient,

^3The captain of fifty, and the honourable man, and the counsellor, and the cunning artificer, and the eloquent orator.

^4And I will give children to be their princes, and babes shall rule over them.

^5And the people shall be oppressed, every one by another, and every one by his neighbour: the child shall behave himself proudly against the ancient, and the base against the honourable.

^6When a man shall take hold of his brother of the house of his father, saying, Thou hast clothing, be thou our ruler, and let this ruin be under thy hand:

^7In that day shall he swear, saying, I will not be an healer; for in my house is neither bread nor clothing: make me not a ruler of the people.

^8For Jerusalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen: because their tongue and their doings are against the Lord, to provoke the eyes of his glory.

^9The shew of their countenance doth witness against them; and they declare their sin as Sodom, they hide it not. Woe unto their soul! for they have rewarded evil unto themselves.

^10Say ye to the righteous, that it shall be well with him: for they shall eat the fruit of their doings.

^11Woe unto the wicked! it shall be ill with him: for the reward of his hands shall be given him.

^12As for my people, children are their oppressors, and women rule over them. O my people, they which lead thee cause thee to err, and destroy the way of thy paths.

^13The Lord standeth up to plead, and standeth to judge the people.

^14The Lord will enter into judgment with the ancients of his people, and the princes thereof: for ye have eaten up the vineyard; the spoil of the poor is in your houses.

^15What mean ye that ye beat my people to pieces, and grind the faces of the poor? saith the Lord God of hosts.

^16Moreover the Lord saith, Because the daughters of Zion are haughty, and walk with stretched forth necks and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet:

^17Therefore the Lord will smite with a scab the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion, and the Lord will discover their secret parts.

^18In that day the Lord will take away the bravery of their tinkling ornaments about their feet, and their cauls, and their round tires like the moon,

^19The chains, and the bracelets, and the mufflers,

^20The bonnets, and the ornaments of the legs, and the headbands, and the tablets, and the earrings,

^21The rings, and nose jewels,

^22The changeable suits of apparel, and the mantles, and the wimples, and the crisping pins,

^23The glasses, and the fine linen, and the hoods, and the vails.

^24And it shall come to pass, that instead of sweet smell there shall be stink; and instead of a girdle a rent; and instead of well set hair baldness; and instead of a stomacher a girding of sackcloth; and burning instead of beauty.

^25Thy men shall fall by the sword, and thy mighty in the war.

^26And her gates shall lament and mourn; and she being desolate shall sit upon the ground.

Isaiah 4

4^1And in that day seven women shall take hold of one man, saying, We will eat our own bread, and wear our own apparel: only let us be called by thy name, to take away our reproach.

^2In that day shall the branch of the Lord be beautiful and glorious, and the fruit of the earth shall be excellent and comely for them that are escaped of Israel.

^3And it shall come to pass, that he that is left in Zion, and he that remaineth in Jerusalem, shall be called holy, even every one that is written among the living in Jerusalem:

^4When the Lord shall have washed away the filth of the daughters of Zion, and shall have purged the blood of Jerusalem from the midst thereof by the spirit of judgment, and by the spirit of burning.

^5And the Lord will create upon every dwelling place of mount Zion, and upon her assemblies, a cloud and smoke by day, and the shining of a flaming fire by night: for upon all the glory shall be a defence.

^6And there shall be a tabernacle for a shadow in the day time from the heat, and for a place of refuge, and for a covert from storm and from rain.

Isaiah 5

5^1Now will I sing to my wellbeloved a song of my beloved touching his vineyard. My wellbeloved hath a vineyard in a very fruitful hill:

^2And he fenced it, and gathered out the stones thereof, and planted it with the choicest vine, and built a tower in the midst of it, and also made a winepress therein: and he looked that it should bring forth grapes, and it brought forth wild grapes.

^3And now, O inhabitants of Jerusalem, and men of Judah, judge, I pray you, betwixt me and my vineyard.

^4What could have been done more to my vineyard, that I have not done in it? wherefore, when I looked that it should bring forth grapes, brought it forth wild grapes?

^5And now go to; I will tell you what I will do to my vineyard: I will take away the hedge thereof, and it shall be eaten up; and break down the wall thereof, and it shall be trodden down:

^6And I will lay it waste: it shall not be pruned, nor digged; but there shall come up briers and thorns: I will also command the clouds that they rain no rain upon it.

^7For the vineyard of the Lord of hosts is the house of Israel, and the men of Judah his pleasant plant: and he looked for judgment, but behold oppression; for righteousness, but behold a cry.

^8Woe unto them that join house to house, that lay field to field, till there be no place, that they may be placed alone in the midst of the earth!

^9In mine ears said the Lord of hosts, Of a truth many houses shall be desolate, even great and fair, without inhabitant.

^10Yea, ten acres of vineyard shall yield one bath, and the seed of an homer shall yield an ephah.

^11Woe unto them that rise up early in the morning, that they may follow strong drink; that continue until night, till wine inflame them!

^12And the harp, and the viol, the tabret, and pipe, and wine, are in their feasts: but they regard not the work of the Lord, neither consider the operation of his hands.

^13Therefore my people are gone into captivity, because they have no knowledge: and their honourable men are famished, and their multitude dried up with thirst.

^14Therefore hell hath enlarged herself, and opened her mouth without measure: and their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoiceth, shall descend into it.

^15And the mean man shall be brought down, and the mighty man shall be humbled, and the eyes of the lofty shall be humbled:

^16But the Lord of hosts shall be exalted in judgment, and God that is holy shall be sanctified in righteousness.

^17Then shall the lambs feed after their manner, and the waste places of the fat ones shall strangers eat.

^18Woe unto them that draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and sin as it were with a cart rope:

^19That say, Let him make speed, and hasten his work, that we may see it: and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel draw nigh and come, that we may know it!

^20Woe unto them that call evil good, and good evil; that put darkness for light, and light for darkness; that put bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter!

^21Woe unto them that are wise in their own eyes, and prudent in their own sight!

^22Woe unto them that are mighty to drink wine, and men of strength to mingle strong drink:

^23Which justify the wicked for reward, and take away the righteousness of the righteous from him!

^24Therefore as the fire devoureth the stubble, and the flame consumeth the chaff, so their root shall be as rottenness, and their blossom shall go up as dust: because they have cast away the law of the Lord of hosts, and despised the word of the Holy One of Israel.

^25Therefore is the anger of the Lord kindled against his people, and he hath stretched forth his hand against them, and hath smitten them: and the hills did tremble, and their carcases were torn in the midst of the streets. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

^26And he will lift up an ensign to the nations from far, and will hiss unto them from the end of the earth: and, behold, they shall come with speed swiftly:

^27None shall be weary nor stumble among them; none shall slumber nor sleep; neither shall the girdle of their loins be loosed, nor the latchet of their shoes be broken:

^28Whose arrows are sharp, and all their bows bent, their horses’ hoofs shall be counted like flint, and their wheels like a whirlwind:

^29Their roaring shall be like a lion, they shall roar like young lions: yea, they shall roar, and lay hold of the prey, and shall carry it away safe, and none shall deliver it.

^30And in that day they shall roar against them like the roaring of the sea: and if one look unto the land, behold darkness and sorrow, and the light is darkened in the heavens thereof.

Isaiah 6

6^1In the year that king Uzziah died I saw also the Lord sitting upon a throne, high and lifted up, and his train filled the temple.

^2Above it stood the seraphims: each one had six wings; with twain he covered his face, and with twain he covered his feet, and with twain he did fly.

^3And one cried unto another, and said, Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of hosts: the whole earth is full of his glory.

^4And the posts of the door moved at the voice of him that cried, and the house was filled with smoke.

^5Then said I, Woe is me! for I am undone; because I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell in the midst of a people of unclean lips: for mine eyes have seen the King, the Lord of hosts.

^6Then flew one of the seraphims unto me, having a live coal in his hand, which he had taken with the tongs from off the altar:

^7And he laid it upon my mouth, and said, Lo, this hath touched thy lips; and thine iniquity is taken away, and thy sin purged.

^8Also I heard the voice of the Lord, saying, Whom shall I send, and who will go for us? Then said I, Here am I; send me.

^9And he said, Go, and tell this people, Hear ye indeed, but understand not; and see ye indeed, but perceive not.

^10Make the heart of this people fat, and make their ears heavy, and shut their eyes; lest they see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and convert, and be healed.

^11Then said I, Lord, how long? And he answered, Until the cities be wasted without inhabitant, and the houses without man, and the land be utterly desolate,

^12And the Lord have removed men far away, and there be a great forsaking in the midst of the land.

^13But yet in it shall be a tenth, and it shall return, and shall be eaten: as a teil tree, and as an oak, whose substance is in them, when they cast their leaves: so the holy seed shall be the substance thereof.

Isaiah 7

7^1And it came to pass in the days of Ahaz the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, that Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, went up toward Jerusalem to war against it, but could not prevail against it.

^2And it was told the house of David, saying, Syria is confederate with Ephraim. And his heart was moved, and the heart of his people, as the trees of the wood are moved with the wind.

^3Then said the Lord unto Isaiah, Go forth now to meet Ahaz, thou, and Shearjashub thy son, at the end of the conduit of the upper pool in the highway of the fuller’s field;

^4And say unto him, Take heed, and be quiet; fear not, neither be fainthearted for the two tails of these smoking firebrands, for the fierce anger of Rezin with Syria, and of the son of Remaliah.

^5Because Syria, Ephraim, and the son of Remaliah, have taken evil counsel against thee, saying,

^6Let us go up against Judah, and vex it, and let us make a breach therein for us, and set a king in the midst of it, even the son of Tabeal:

^7Thus saith the Lord God, It shall not stand, neither shall it come to pass.

^8For the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within threescore and five years shall Ephraim be broken, that it be not a people.

^9And the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliah’s son. If ye will not believe, surely ye shall not be established.

^10Moreover the Lord spake again unto Ahaz, saying,

^11Ask thee a sign of the Lord thy God; ask it either in the depth, or in the height above.

^12But Ahaz said, I will not ask, neither will I tempt the Lord.

^13And he said, Hear ye now, O house of David; Is it a small thing for you to weary men, but will ye weary my God also?

^14Therefore the Lord himself shall give you a sign; Behold, a virgin shall conceive, and bear a son, and shall call his name Immanuel.

^15Butter and honey shall he eat, that he may know to refuse the evil, and choose the good.

^16For before the child shall know to refuse the evil, and choose the good, the land that thou abhorrest shall be forsaken of both her kings.

^17The Lord shall bring upon thee, and upon thy people, and upon thy father’s house, days that have not come, from the day that Ephraim departed from Judah; even the king of Assyria.

^18And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall hiss for the fly that is in the uttermost part of the rivers of Egypt, and for the bee that is in the land of Assyria.

^19And they shall come, and shall rest all of them in the desolate valleys, and in the holes of the rocks, and upon all thorns, and upon all bushes.

^20In the same day shall the Lord shave with a razor that is hired, namely, by them beyond the river, by the king of Assyria, the head, and the hair of the feet: and it shall also consume the beard.

^21And it shall come to pass in that day, that a man shall nourish a young cow, and two sheep;

^22And it shall come to pass, for the abundance of milk that they shall give he shall eat butter: for butter and honey shall every one eat that is left in the land.

^23And it shall come to pass in that day, that every place shall be, where there were a thousand vines at a thousand silverlings, it shall even be for briers and thorns.

^24With arrows and with bows shall men come thither; because all the land shall become briers and thorns.

^25And on all hills that shall be digged with the mattock, there shall not come thither the fear of briers and thorns: but it shall be for the sending forth of oxen, and for the treading of lesser cattle.

Isaiah 8

8^1Moreover the Lord said unto me, Take thee a great roll, and write in it with a man’s pen concerning Mahershalalhashbaz.

^2And I took unto me faithful witnesses to record, Uriah the priest, and Zechariah the son of Jeberechiah.

^3And I went unto the prophetess; and she conceived, and bare a son. Then said the Lord to me, Call his name Mahershalalhashbaz.

^4For before the child shall have knowledge to cry, My father, and my mother, the riches of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria shall be taken away before the king of Assyria.

^5The Lord spake also unto me again, saying,

^6Forasmuch as this people refuseth the waters of Shiloah that go softly, and rejoice in Rezin and Remaliah’s son;

^7Now therefore, behold, the Lord bringeth up upon them the waters of the river, strong and many, even the king of Assyria, and all his glory: and he shall come up over all his channels, and go over all his banks:

^8And he shall pass through Judah; he shall overflow and go over, he shall reach even to the neck; and the stretching out of his wings shall fill the breadth of thy land, O Immanuel.

^9Associate yourselves, O ye people, and ye shall be broken in pieces; and give ear, all ye of far countries: gird yourselves, and ye shall be broken in pieces; gird yourselves, and ye shall be broken in pieces.

^10Take counsel together, and it shall come to nought; speak the word, and it shall not stand: for God is with us.

^11For the Lord spake thus to me with a strong hand, and instructed me that I should not walk in the way of this people, saying,

^12Say ye not, A confederacy, to all them to whom this people shall say, A confederacy; neither fear ye their fear, nor be afraid.

^13Sanctify the Lord of hosts himself; and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread.

^14And he shall be for a sanctuary; but for a stone of stumbling and for a rock of offence to both the houses of Israel, for a gin and for a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

^15And many among them shall stumble, and fall, and be broken, and be snared, and be taken.

^16Bind up the testimony, seal the law among my disciples.

^17And I will wait upon the Lord, that hideth his face from the house of Jacob, and I will look for him.

^18Behold, I and the children whom the Lord hath given me are for signs and for wonders in Israel from the Lord of hosts, which dwelleth in mount Zion.

^19And when they shall say unto you, Seek unto them that have familiar spirits, and unto wizards that peep, and that mutter: should not a people seek unto their God? for the living to the dead?

^20To the law and to the testimony: if they speak not according to this word, it is because there is no light in them.

^21And they shall pass through it, hardly bestead and hungry: and it shall come to pass, that when they shall be hungry, they shall fret themselves, and curse their king and their God, and look upward.

^22And they shall look unto the earth; and behold trouble and darkness, dimness of anguish; and they shall be driven to darkness.

Isaiah 9

9^1Nevertheless the dimness shall not be such as was in her vexation, when at the first he lightly afflicted the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali, and afterward did more grievously afflict her by the way of the sea, beyond Jordan, in Galilee of the nations.

^2The people that walked in darkness have seen a great light: they that dwell in the land of the shadow of death, upon them hath the light shined.

^3Thou hast multiplied the nation, and not increased the joy: they joy before thee according to the joy in harvest, and as men rejoice when they divide the spoil.

^4For thou hast broken the yoke of his burden, and the staff of his shoulder, the rod of his oppressor, as in the day of Midian.

^5For every battle of the warrior is with confused noise, and garments rolled in blood; but this shall be with burning and fuel of fire.

^6For unto us a child is born, unto us a son is given: and the government shall be upon his shoulder: and his name shall be called Wonderful, Counsellor, The mighty God, The everlasting Father, The Prince of Peace.

^7Of the increase of his government and peace there shall be no end, upon the throne of David, and upon his kingdom, to order it, and to establish it with judgment and with justice from henceforth even for ever. The zeal of the Lord of hosts will perform this.

^8The Lord sent a word into Jacob, and it hath lighted upon Israel.

^9And all the people shall know, even Ephraim and the inhabitant of Samaria, that say in the pride and stoutness of heart,

^10The bricks are fallen down, but we will build with hewn stones: the sycomores are cut down, but we will change them into cedars.

^11Therefore the Lord shall set up the adversaries of Rezin against him, and join his enemies together;

^12The Syrians before, and the Philistines behind; and they shall devour Israel with open mouth. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

^13For the people turneth not unto him that smiteth them, neither do they seek the Lord of hosts.

^14Therefore the Lord will cut off from Israel head and tail, branch and rush, in one day.

^15The ancient and honourable, he is the head; and the prophet that teacheth lies, he is the tail.

^16For the leaders of this people cause them to err; and they that are led of them are destroyed.

^17Therefore the Lord shall have no joy in their young men, neither shall have mercy on their fatherless and widows: for every one is an hypocrite and an evildoer, and every mouth speaketh folly. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

^18For wickedness burneth as the fire: it shall devour the briers and thorns, and shall kindle in the thickets of the forest, and they shall mount up like the lifting up of smoke.

^19Through the wrath of the Lord of hosts is the land darkened, and the people shall be as the fuel of the fire: no man shall spare his brother.

^20And he shall snatch on the right hand, and be hungry; and he shall eat on the left hand, and they shall not be satisfied: they shall eat every man the flesh of his own arm:

^21Manasseh, Ephraim; and Ephraim, Manasseh: and they together shall be against Judah. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

Isaiah 10

10^1Woe unto them that decree unrighteous decrees, and that write grievousness which they have prescribed;

^2To turn aside the needy from judgment, and to take away the right from the poor of my people, that widows may be their prey, and that they may rob the fatherless!

^3And what will ye do in the day of visitation, and in the desolation which shall come from far? to whom will ye flee for help? and where will ye leave your glory?

^4Without me they shall bow down under the prisoners, and they shall fall under the slain. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

^5O Assyrian, the rod of mine anger, and the staff in their hand is mine indignation.

^6I will send him against an hypocritical nation, and against the people of my wrath will I give him a charge, to take the spoil, and to take the prey, and to tread them down like the mire of the streets.

^7Howbeit he meaneth not so, neither doth his heart think so; but it is in his heart to destroy and cut off nations not a few.

^8For he saith, Are not my princes altogether kings?

^9Is not Calno as Carchemish? is not Hamath as Arpad? is not Samaria as Damascus?

^10As my hand hath found the kingdoms of the idols, and whose graven images did excel them of Jerusalem and of Samaria;

^11Shall I not, as I have done unto Samaria and her idols, so do to Jerusalem and her idols?

^12Wherefore it shall come to pass, that when the Lord hath performed his whole work upon mount Zion and on Jerusalem, I will punish the fruit of the stout heart of the king of Assyria, and the glory of his high looks.

^13For he saith, By the strength of my hand I have done it, and by my wisdom; for I am prudent: and I have removed the bounds of the people, and have robbed their treasures, and I have put down the inhabitants like a valiant man:

^14And my hand hath found as a nest the riches of the people: and as one gathereth eggs that are left, have I gathered all the earth; and there was none that moved the wing, or opened the mouth, or peeped.

^15Shall the axe boast itself against him that heweth therewith? or shall the saw magnify itself against him that shaketh it? as if the rod should shake itself against them that lift it up, or as if the staff should lift up itself, as if it were no wood.

^16Therefore shall the Lord, the Lord of hosts, send among his fat ones leanness; and under his glory he shall kindle a burning like the burning of a fire.

^17And the light of Israel shall be for a fire, and his Holy One for a flame: and it shall burn and devour his thorns and his briers in one day;

^18And shall consume the glory of his forest, and of his fruitful field, both soul and body: and they shall be as when a standard-bearer fainteth.

^19And the rest of the trees of his forest shall be few, that a child may write them.

^20And it shall come to pass in that day, that the remnant of Israel, and such as are escaped of the house of Jacob, shall no more again stay upon him that smote them; but shall stay upon the Lord, the Holy One of Israel, in truth.

^21The remnant shall return, even the remnant of Jacob, unto the mighty God.

^22For though thy people Israel be as the sand of the sea, yet a remnant of them shall return: the consumption decreed shall overflow with righteousness.

^23For the Lord God of hosts shall make a consumption, even determined, in the midst of all the land.

^24Therefore thus saith the Lord God of hosts, O my people that dwellest in Zion, be not afraid of the Assyrian: he shall smite thee with a rod, and shall lift up his staff against thee, after the manner of Egypt.

^25For yet a very little while, and the indignation shall cease, and mine anger in their destruction.

^26And the Lord of hosts shall stir up a scourge for him according to the slaughter of Midian at the rock of Oreb: and as his rod was upon the sea, so shall he lift it up after the manner of Egypt.

^27And it shall come to pass in that day, that his burden shall be taken away from off thy shoulder, and his yoke from off thy neck, and the yoke shall be destroyed because of the anointing.

^28He is come to Aiath, he is passed to Migron; at Michmash he hath laid up his carriages:

^29They are gone over the passage: they have taken up their lodging at Geba; Ramah is afraid; Gibeah of Saul is fled.

^30Lift up thy voice, O daughter of Gallim: cause it to be heard unto Laish, O poor Anathoth.

^31Madmenah is removed; the inhabitants of Gebim gather themselves to flee.

^32As yet shall he remain at Nob that day: he shall shake his hand against the mount of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem.

^33Behold, the Lord, the Lord of hosts, shall lop the bough with terror: and the high ones of stature shall be hewn down, and the haughty shall be humbled.

^34And he shall cut down the thickets of the forest with iron, and Lebanon shall fall by a mighty one.

Isaiah 11

11^1And there shall come forth a rod out of the stem of Jesse, and a Branch shall grow out of his roots:

^2And the spirit of the Lord shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord;

^3And shall make him of quick understanding in the fear of the Lord: and he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes, neither reprove after the hearing of his ears:

^4But with righteousness shall he judge the poor, and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth: and he shall smite the earth: with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked.

^5And righteousness shall be the girdle of his loins, and faithfulness the girdle of his reins.

^6The wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid; and the calf and the young lion and the fatling together; and a little child shall lead them.

^7And the cow and the bear shall feed; their young ones shall lie down together: and the lion shall eat straw like the ox.

^8And the sucking child shall play on the hole of the asp, and the weaned child shall put his hand on the cockatrice’ den.

^9They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain: for the earth shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the sea.

^10And in that day there shall be a root of Jesse, which shall stand for an ensign of the people; to it shall the Gentiles seek: and his rest shall be glorious.

^11And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall set his hand again the second time to recover the remnant of his people, which shall be left, from Assyria, and from Egypt, and from Pathros, and from Cush, and from Elam, and from Shinar, and from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea.

^12And he shall set up an ensign for the nations, and shall assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the dispersed of Judah from the four corners of the earth.

^13The envy also of Ephraim shall depart, and the adversaries of Judah shall be cut off: Ephraim shall not envy Judah, and Judah shall not vex Ephraim.

^14But they shall fly upon the shoulders of the Philistines toward the west; they shall spoil them of the east together: they shall lay their hand upon Edom and Moab; and the children of Ammon shall obey them.

^15And the Lord shall utterly destroy the tongue of the Egyptian sea; and with his mighty wind shall he shake his hand over the river, and shall smite it in the seven streams, and make men go over dryshod.

^16And there shall be an highway for the remnant of his people, which shall be left, from Assyria; like as it was to Israel in the day that he came up out of the land of Egypt.

Isaiah 12

12^1And in that day thou shalt say, O Lord, I will praise thee: though thou wast angry with me, thine anger is turned away, and thou comfortedst me.

^2Behold, God is my salvation; I will trust, and not be afraid: for the Lord Jehovah is my strength and my song; he also is become my salvation.

^3Therefore with joy shall ye draw water out of the wells of salvation.

^4And in that day shall ye say, Praise the Lord, call upon his name, declare his doings among the people, make mention that his name is exalted.

^5Sing unto the Lord; for he hath done excellent things: this is known in all the earth.

^6Cry out and shout, thou inhabitant of Zion: for great is the Holy One of Israel in the midst of thee.

Isaiah 13

13^1The burden of Babylon, which Isaiah the son of Amoz did see.

^2Lift ye up a banner upon the high mountain, exalt the voice unto them, shake the hand, that they may go into the gates of the nobles.

^3I have commanded my sanctified ones, I have also called my mighty ones for mine anger, even them that rejoice in my highness.

^4The noise of a multitude in the mountains, like as of a great people; a tumultuous noise of the kingdoms of nations gathered together: the Lord of hosts mustereth the host of the battle.

^5They come from a far country, from the end of heaven, even the Lord, and the weapons of his indignation, to destroy the whole land.

^6Howl ye; for the day of the Lord is at hand; it shall come as a destruction from the Almighty.

^7Therefore shall all hands be faint, and every man’s heart shall melt:

^8And they shall be afraid: pangs and sorrows shall take hold of them; they shall be in pain as a woman that travaileth: they shall be amazed one at another; their faces shall be as flames.

^9Behold, the day of the Lord cometh, cruel both with wrath and fierce anger, to lay the land desolate: and he shall destroy the sinners thereof out of it.

^10For the stars of heaven and the constellations thereof shall not give their light: the sun shall be darkened in his going forth, and the moon shall not cause her light to shine.

^11And I will punish the world for their evil, and the wicked for their iniquity; and I will cause the arrogancy of the proud to cease, and will lay low the haughtiness of the terrible.

^12I will make a man more precious than fine gold; even a man than the golden wedge of Ophir.

^13Therefore I will shake the heavens, and the earth shall remove out of her place, in the wrath of the Lord of hosts, and in the day of his fierce anger.

^14And it shall be as the chased roe, and as a sheep that no man taketh up: they shall every man turn to his own people, and flee every one into his own land.

^15Every one that is found shall be thrust through; and every one that is joined unto them shall fall by the sword.

^16Their children also shall be dashed to pieces before their eyes; their houses shall be spoiled, and their wives ravished.

^17Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, which shall not regard silver; and as for gold, they shall not delight in it.

^18Their bows also shall dash the young men to pieces; and they shall have no pity on the fruit of the womb; their eyes shall not spare children.

^19And Babylon, the glory of kingdoms, the beauty of the Chaldees’ excellency, shall be as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah.

^20It shall never be inhabited, neither shall it be dwelt in from generation to generation: neither shall the Arabian pitch tent there; neither shall the shepherds make their fold there.

^21But wild beasts of the desert shall lie there; and their houses shall be full of doleful creatures; and owls shall dwell there, and satyrs shall dance there.

^22And the wild beasts of the islands shall cry in their desolate houses, and dragons in their pleasant palaces: and her time is near to come, and her days shall not be prolonged.

Isaiah 14

14^1For the Lord will have mercy on Jacob, and will yet choose Israel, and set them in their own land: and the strangers shall be joined with them, and they shall cleave to the house of Jacob.

^2And the people shall take them, and bring them to their place: and the house of Israel shall possess them in the land of the Lord for servants and handmaids: and they shall take them captives, whose captives they were; and they shall rule over their oppressors.

^3And it shall come to pass in the day that the Lord shall give thee rest from thy sorrow, and from thy fear, and from the hard bondage wherein thou wast made to serve,

^4That thou shalt take up this proverb against the king of Babylon, and say, How hath the oppressor ceased! the golden city ceased!

^5The Lord hath broken the staff of the wicked, and the sceptre of the rulers.

^6He who smote the people in wrath with a continual stroke, he that ruled the nations in anger, is persecuted, and none hindereth.

^7The whole earth is at rest, and is quiet: they break forth into singing.

^8Yea, the fir trees rejoice at thee, and the cedars of Lebanon, saying, Since thou art laid down, no feller is come up against us.

^9Hell from beneath is moved for thee to meet thee at thy coming: it stirreth up the dead for thee, even all the chief ones of the earth; it hath raised up from their thrones all the kings of the nations.

^10All they shall speak and say unto thee, Art thou also become weak as we? art thou become like unto us?

^11Thy pomp is brought down to the grave, and the noise of thy viols: the worm is spread under thee, and the worms cover thee.

^12How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, son of the morning! how art thou cut down to the ground, which didst weaken the nations!

^13For thou hast said in thine heart, I will ascend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God: I will sit also upon the mount of the congregation, in the sides of the north:

^14I will ascend above the heights of the clouds; I will be like the most High.

^15Yet thou shalt be brought down to hell, to the sides of the pit.

^16They that see thee shall narrowly look upon thee, and consider thee, saying, Is this the man that made the earth to tremble, that did shake kingdoms;

^17That made the world as a wilderness, and destroyed the cities thereof; that opened not the house of his prisoners?

^18All the kings of the nations, even all of them, lie in glory, every one in his own house.

^19But thou art cast out of thy grave like an abominable branch, and as the raiment of those that are slain, thrust through with a sword, that go down to the stones of the pit; as a carcase trodden under feet.

^20Thou shalt not be joined with them in burial, because thou hast destroyed thy land, and slain thy people: the seed of evildoers shall never be renowned.

^21Prepare slaughter for his children for the iniquity of their fathers; that they do not rise, nor possess the land, nor fill the face of the world with cities.

^22For I will rise up against them, saith the Lord of hosts, and cut off from Babylon the name, and remnant, and son, and nephew, saith the Lord.

^23I will also make it a possession for the bittern, and pools of water: and I will sweep it with the besom of destruction, saith the Lord of hosts.

^24The Lord of hosts hath sworn, saying, Surely as I have thought, so shall it come to pass; and as I have purposed, so shall it stand:

^25That I will break the Assyrian in my land, and upon my mountains tread him under foot: then shall his yoke depart from off them, and his burden depart from off their shoulders.

^26This is the purpose that is purposed upon the whole earth: and this is the hand that is stretched out upon all the nations.

^27For the Lord of hosts hath purposed, and who shall disannul it? and his hand is stretched out, and who shall turn it back?

^28In the year that king Ahaz died was this burden.

^29Rejoice not thou, whole Palestina, because the rod of him that smote thee is broken: for out of the serpent’s root shall come forth a cockatrice, and his fruit shall be a fiery flying serpent.

^30And the firstborn of the poor shall feed, and the needy shall lie down in safety: and I will kill thy root with famine, and he shall slay thy remnant.

^31Howl, O gate; cry, O city; thou, whole Palestina, art dissolved: for there shall come from the north a smoke, and none shall be alone in his appointed times.

^32What shall one then answer the messengers of the nation? That the Lord hath founded Zion, and the poor of his people shall trust in it.

Isaiah 15

15^1The burden of Moab. Because in the night Ar of Moab is laid waste, and brought to silence; because in the night Kir of Moab is laid waste, and brought to silence;

^2He is gone up to Bajith, and to Dibon, the high places, to weep: Moab shall howl over Nebo, and over Medeba: on all their heads shall be baldness, and every beard cut off.

^3In their streets they shall gird themselves with sackcloth: on the tops of their houses, and in their streets, every one shall howl, weeping abundantly.

^4And Heshbon shall cry, and Elealeh: their voice shall be heard even unto Jahaz: therefore the armed soldiers of Moab shall cry out; his life shall be grievous unto him.

^5My heart shall cry out for Moab; his fugitives shall flee unto Zoar, an heifer of three years old: for by the mounting up of Luhith with weeping shall they go it up; for in the way of Horonaim they shall raise up a cry of destruction.

^6For the waters of Nimrim shall be desolate: for the hay is withered away, the grass faileth, there is no green thing.

^7Therefore the abundance they have gotten, and that which they have laid up, shall they carry away to the brook of the willows.

^8For the cry is gone round about the borders of Moab; the howling thereof unto Eglaim, and the howling thereof unto Beerelim.

^9For the waters of Dimon shall be full of blood: for I will bring more upon Dimon, lions upon him that escapeth of Moab, and upon the remnant of the land.

Isaiah 16

16^1Send ye the lamb to the ruler of the land from Sela to the wilderness, unto the mount of the daughter of Zion.

^2For it shall be, that, as a wandering bird cast out of the nest, so the daughters of Moab shall be at the fords of Arnon.

^3Take counsel, execute judgment; make thy shadow as the night in the midst of the noonday; hide the outcasts; bewray not him that wandereth.

^4Let mine outcasts dwell with thee, Moab; be thou a covert to them from the face of the spoiler: for the extortioner is at an end, the spoiler ceaseth, the oppressors are consumed out of the land.

^5And in mercy shall the throne be established: and he shall sit upon it in truth in the tabernacle of David, judging, and seeking judgment, and hasting righteousness.

^6We have heard of the pride of Moab; he is very proud: even of his haughtiness, and his pride, and his wrath: but his lies shall not be so.

^7Therefore shall Moab howl for Moab, every one shall howl: for the foundations of Kirhareseth shall ye mourn; surely they are stricken.

^8For the fields of Heshbon languish, and the vine of Sibmah: the lords of the heathen have broken down the principal plants thereof, they are come even unto Jazer, they wandered through the wilderness: her branches are stretched out, they are gone over the sea.

^9Therefore I will bewail with the weeping of Jazer the vine of Sibmah: I will water thee with my tears, O Heshbon, and Elealeh: for the shouting for thy summer fruits and for thy harvest is fallen.

^10And gladness is taken away, and joy out of the plentiful field; and in the vineyards there shall be no singing, neither shall there be shouting: the treaders shall tread out no wine in their presses; I have made their vintage shouting to cease.

^11Wherefore my bowels shall sound like an harp for Moab, and mine inward parts for Kirharesh.

^12And it shall come to pass, when it is seen that Moab is weary on the high place, that he shall come to his sanctuary to pray; but he shall not prevail.

^13This is the word that the Lord hath spoken concerning Moab since that time.

^14But now the Lord hath spoken, saying, Within three years, as the years of an hireling, and the glory of Moab shall be contemned, with all that great multitude; and the remnant shall be very small and feeble.

Isaiah 17

17^1The burden of Damascus. Behold, Damascus is taken away from being a city, and it shall be a ruinous heap.

^2The cities of Aroer are forsaken: they shall be for flocks, which shall lie down, and none shall make them afraid.

^3The fortress also shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom from Damascus, and the remnant of Syria: they shall be as the glory of the children of Israel, saith the Lord of hosts.

^4And in that day it shall come to pass, that the glory of Jacob shall be made thin, and the fatness of his flesh shall wax lean.

^5And it shall be as when the harvestman gathereth the corn, and reapeth the ears with his arm; and it shall be as he that gathereth ears in the valley of Rephaim.

^6Yet gleaning grapes shall be left in it, as the shaking of an olive tree, two or three berries in the top of the uppermost bough, four or five in the outmost fruitful branches thereof, saith the Lord God of Israel.

^7At that day shall a man look to his Maker, and his eyes shall have respect to the Holy One of Israel.

^8And he shall not look to the altars, the work of his hands, neither shall respect that which his fingers have made, either the groves, or the images.

^9In that day shall his strong cities be as a forsaken bough, and an uppermost branch, which they left because of the children of Israel: and there shall be desolation.

^10Because thou hast forgotten the God of thy salvation, and hast not been mindful of the rock of thy strength, therefore shalt thou plant pleasant plants, and shalt set it with strange slips:

^11In the day shalt thou make thy plant to grow, and in the morning shalt thou make thy seed to flourish: but the harvest shall be a heap in the day of grief and of desperate sorrow.

^12Woe to the multitude of many people, which make a noise like the noise of the seas; and to the rushing of nations, that make a rushing like the rushing of mighty waters!

^13The nations shall rush like the rushing of many waters: but God shall rebuke them, and they shall flee far off, and shall be chased as the chaff of the mountains before the wind, and like a rolling thing before the whirlwind.

^14And behold at eveningtide trouble; and before the morning he is not. This is the portion of them that spoil us, and the lot of them that rob us.

Isaiah 18

18^1Woe to the land shadowing with wings, which is beyond the rivers of Ethiopia:

^2That sendeth ambassadors by the sea, even in vessels of bulrushes upon the waters, saying, Go, ye swift messengers, to a nation scattered and peeled, to a people terrible from their beginning hitherto; a nation meted out and trodden down, whose land the rivers have spoiled!

^3All ye inhabitants of the world, and dwellers on the earth, see ye, when he lifteth up an ensign on the mountains; and when he bloweth a trumpet, hear ye.

^4For so the Lord said unto me, I will take my rest, and I will consider in my dwelling place like a clear heat upon herbs, and like a cloud of dew in the heat of harvest.

^5For afore the harvest, when the bud is perfect, and the sour grape is ripening in the flower, he shall both cut off the sprigs with pruning hooks, and take away and cut down the branches.

^6They shall be left together unto the fowls of the mountains, and to the beasts of the earth: and the fowls shall summer upon them, and all the beasts of the earth shall winter upon them.

^7In that time shall the present be brought unto the Lord of hosts of a people scattered and peeled, and from a people terrible from their beginning hitherto; a nation meted out and trodden under foot, whose land the rivers have spoiled, to the place of the name of the Lord of hosts, the mount Zion.

Isaiah 19

19^1The burden of Egypt. Behold, the Lord rideth upon a swift cloud, and shall come into Egypt: and the idols of Egypt shall be moved at his presence, and the heart of Egypt shall melt in the midst of it.

^2And I will set the Egyptians against the Egyptians: and they shall fight every one against his brother, and every one against his neighbour; city against city, and kingdom against kingdom.

^3And the spirit of Egypt shall fail in the midst thereof; and I will destroy the counsel thereof: and they shall seek to the idols, and to the charmers, and to them that have familiar spirits, and to the wizards.

^4And the Egyptians will I give over into the hand of a cruel lord; and a fierce king shall rule over them, saith the Lord, the Lord of hosts.

^5And the waters shall fail from the sea, and the river shall be wasted and dried up.

^6And they shall turn the rivers far away; and the brooks of defence shall be emptied and dried up: the reeds and flags shall wither.

^7The paper reeds by the brooks, by the mouth of the brooks, and every thing sown by the brooks, shall wither, be driven away, and be no more.

^8The fishers also shall mourn, and all they that cast angle into the brooks shall lament, and they that spread nets upon the waters shall languish.

^9Moreover they that work in fine flax, and they that weave networks, shall be confounded.

^10And they shall be broken in the purposes thereof, all that make sluices and ponds for fish.

^11Surely the princes of Zoan are fools, the counsel of the wise counsellors of Pharaoh is become brutish: how say ye unto Pharaoh, I am the son of the wise, the son of ancient kings?

^12Where are they? where are thy wise men? and let them tell thee now, and let them know what the Lord of hosts hath purposed upon Egypt.

^13The princes of Zoan are become fools, the princes of Noph are deceived; they have also seduced Egypt, even they that are the stay of the tribes thereof.

^14The Lord hath mingled a perverse spirit in the midst thereof: and they have caused Egypt to err in every work thereof, as a drunken man staggereth in his vomit.

^15Neither shall there be any work for Egypt, which the head or tail, branch or rush, may do.

^16In that day shall Egypt be like unto women: and it shall be afraid and fear because of the shaking of the hand of the Lord of hosts, which he shaketh over it.

^17And the land of Judah shall be a terror unto Egypt, every one that maketh mention thereof shall be afraid in himself, because of the counsel of the Lord of hosts, which he hath determined against it.

^18In that day shall five cities in the land of Egypt speak the language of Canaan, and swear to the Lord of hosts; one shall be called, The city of destruction.

^19In that day shall there be an altar to the Lord in the midst of the land of Egypt, and a pillar at the border thereof to the Lord.

^20And it shall be for a sign and for a witness unto the Lord of hosts in the land of Egypt: for they shall cry unto the Lord because of the oppressors, and he shall send them a saviour, and a great one, and he shall deliver them.

^21And the Lord shall be known to Egypt, and the Egyptians shall know the Lord in that day, and shall do sacrifice and oblation; yea, they shall vow a vow unto the Lord, and perform it.

^22And the Lord shall smite Egypt: he shall smite and heal it: and they shall return even to the Lord, and he shall be intreated of them, and shall heal them.

^23In that day shall there be a highway out of Egypt to Assyria, and the Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria, and the Egyptians shall serve with the Assyrians.

^24In that day shall Israel be the third with Egypt and with Assyria, even a blessing in the midst of the land:

^25Whom the Lord of hosts shall bless, saying, Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria the work of my hands, and Israel mine inheritance.

Isaiah 20

20^1In the year that Tartan came unto Ashdod, (when Sargon the king of Assyria sent him,) and fought against Ashdod, and took it;

^2At the same time spake the Lord by Isaiah the son of Amoz, saying, Go and loose the sackcloth from off thy loins, and put off thy shoe from thy foot. And he did so, walking naked and barefoot.

^3And the Lord said, Like as my servant Isaiah hath walked naked and barefoot three years for a sign and wonder upon Egypt and upon Ethiopia;

^4So shall the king of Assyria lead away the Egyptians prisoners, and the Ethiopians captives, young and old, naked and barefoot, even with their buttocks uncovered, to the shame of Egypt.

^5And they shall be afraid and ashamed of Ethiopia their expectation, and of Egypt their glory.

^6And the inhabitant of this isle shall say in that day, Behold, such is our expectation, whither we flee for help to be delivered from the king of Assyria: and how shall we escape?

Isaiah 21

21^1The burden of the desert of the sea. As whirlwinds in the south pass through; so it cometh from the desert, from a terrible land.

^2A grievous vision is declared unto me; the treacherous dealer dealeth treacherously, and the spoiler spoileth. Go up, O Elam: besiege, O Media; all the sighing thereof have I made to cease.

^3Therefore are my loins filled with pain: pangs have taken hold upon me, as the pangs of a woman that travaileth: I was bowed down at the hearing of it; I was dismayed at the seeing of it.

^4My heart panted, fearfulness affrighted me: the night of my pleasure hath he turned into fear unto me.

^5Prepare the table, watch in the watchtower, eat, drink: arise, ye princes, and anoint the shield.

^6For thus hath the Lord said unto me, Go, set a watchman, let him declare what he seeth.

^7And he saw a chariot with a couple of horsemen, a chariot of asses, and a chariot of camels; and he hearkened diligently with much heed:

^8And he cried, A lion: My lord, I stand continually upon the watchtower in the daytime, and I am set in my ward whole nights:

^9And, behold, here cometh a chariot of men, with a couple of horsemen. And he answered and said, Babylon is fallen, is fallen; and all the graven images of her gods he hath broken unto the ground.

^10O my threshing, and the corn of my floor: that which I have heard of the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, have I declared unto you.

^11The burden of Dumah. He calleth to me out of Seir, Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night?

^12The watchman said, The morning cometh, and also the night: if ye will enquire, enquire ye: return, come.

^13The burden upon Arabia. In the forest in Arabia shall ye lodge, O ye travelling companies of Dedanim.

^14The inhabitants of the land of Tema brought water to him that was thirsty, they prevented with their bread him that fled.

^15For they fled from the swords, from the drawn sword, and from the bent bow, and from the grievousness of war.

^16For thus hath the Lord said unto me, Within a year, according to the years of an hireling, and all the glory of Kedar shall fail:

^17And the residue of the number of archers, the mighty men of the children of Kedar, shall be diminished: for the Lord God of Israel hath spoken it.

Isaiah 22

22^1The burden of the valley of vision. What aileth thee now, that thou art wholly gone up to the housetops?

^2Thou that art full of stirs, a tumultuous city, joyous city: thy slain men are not slain with the sword, nor dead in battle.

^3All thy rulers are fled together, they are bound by the archers: all that are found in thee are bound together, which have fled from far.

^4Therefore said I, Look away from me; I will weep bitterly, labour not to comfort me, because of the spoiling of the daughter of my people.

^5For it is a day of trouble, and of treading down, and of perplexity by the Lord God of hosts in the valley of vision, breaking down the walls, and of crying to the mountains.

^6And Elam bare the quiver with chariots of men and horsemen, and Kir uncovered the shield.

^7And it shall come to pass, that thy choicest valleys shall be full of chariots, and the horsemen shall set themselves in array at the gate.

^8And he discovered the covering of Judah, and thou didst look in that day to the armour of the house of the forest.

^9Ye have seen also the breaches of the city of David, that they are many: and ye gathered together the waters of the lower pool.

^10And ye have numbered the houses of Jerusalem, and the houses have ye broken down to fortify the wall.

^11Ye made also a ditch between the two walls for the water of the old pool: but ye have not looked unto the maker thereof, neither had respect unto him that fashioned it long ago.

^12And in that day did the Lord God of hosts call to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldness, and to girding with sackcloth:

^13And behold joy and gladness, slaying oxen, and killing sheep, eating flesh, and drinking wine: let us eat and drink; for to morrow we shall die.

^14And it was revealed in mine ears by the Lord of hosts, Surely this iniquity shall not be purged from you till ye die, saith the Lord God of hosts.

^15Thus saith the Lord God of hosts, Go, get thee unto this treasurer, even unto Shebna, which is over the house, and say,

^16What hast thou here? and whom hast thou here, that thou hast hewed thee out a sepulchre here, as he that heweth him out a sepulchre on high, and that graveth an habitation for himself in a rock?

^17Behold, the Lord will carry thee away with a mighty captivity, and will surely cover thee.

^18He will surely violently turn and toss thee like a ball into a large country: there shalt thou die, and there the chariots of thy glory shall be the shame of thy lord’s house.

^19And I will drive thee from thy station, and from thy state shall he pull thee down.

^20And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah:

^21And I will clothe him with thy robe, and strengthen him with thy girdle, and I will commit thy government into his hand: and he shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to the house of Judah.

^22And the key of the house of David will I lay upon his shoulder; so he shall open, and none shall shut; and he shall shut, and none shall open.

^23And I will fasten him as a nail in a sure place; and he shall be for a glorious throne to his father’s house.

^24And they shall hang upon him all the glory of his father’s house, the offspring and the issue, all vessels of small quantity, from the vessels of cups, even to all the vessels of flagons.

^25In that day, saith the Lord of hosts, shall the nail that is fastened in the sure place be removed, and be cut down, and fall; and the burden that was upon it shall be cut off: for the Lord hath spoken it.

Isaiah 23

23^1The burden of Tyre. Howl, ye ships of Tarshish; for it is laid waste, so that there is no house, no entering in: from the land of Chittim it is revealed to them.

^2Be still, ye inhabitants of the isle; thou whom the merchants of Zidon, that pass over the sea, have replenished.

^3And by great waters the seed of Sihor, the harvest of the river, is her revenue; and she is a mart of nations.

^4Be thou ashamed, O Zidon: for the sea hath spoken, even the strength of the sea, saying, I travail not, nor bring forth children, neither do I nourish up young men, nor bring up virgins.

^5As at the report concerning Egypt, so shall they be sorely pained at the report of Tyre.

^6Pass ye over to Tarshish; howl, ye inhabitants of the isle.

^7Is this your joyous city, whose antiquity is of ancient days? her own feet shall carry her afar off to sojourn.

^8Who hath taken this counsel against Tyre, the crowning city, whose merchants are princes, whose traffickers are the honourable of the earth?

^9The Lord of hosts hath purposed it, to stain the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the honourable of the earth.

^10Pass through thy land as a river, O daughter of Tarshish: there is no more strength.

^11He stretched out his hand over the sea, he shook the kingdoms: the Lord hath given a commandment against the merchant city, to destroy the strong holds thereof.

^12And he said, Thou shalt no more rejoice, O thou oppressed virgin, daughter of Zidon: arise, pass over to Chittim; there also shalt thou have no rest.

^13Behold the land of the Chaldeans; this people was not, till the Assyrian founded it for them that dwell in the wilderness: they set up the towers thereof, they raised up the palaces thereof; and he brought it to ruin.

^14Howl, ye ships of Tarshish: for your strength is laid waste.

^15And it shall come to pass in that day, that Tyre shall be forgotten seventy years, according to the days of one king: after the end of seventy years shall Tyre sing as an harlot.

^16Take an harp, go about the city, thou harlot that hast been forgotten; make sweet melody, sing many songs, that thou mayest be remembered.

^17And it shall come to pass after the end of seventy years, that the Lord will visit Tyre, and she shall turn to her hire, and shall commit fornication with all the kingdoms of the world upon the face of the earth.

^18And her merchandise and her hire shall be holiness to the Lord: it shall not be treasured nor laid up; for her merchandise shall be for them that dwell before the Lord, to eat sufficiently, and for durable clothing.

Isaiah 24

24^1Behold, the Lord maketh the earth empty, and maketh it waste, and turneth it upside down, and scattereth abroad the inhabitants thereof.

^2And it shall be, as with the people, so with the priest; as with the servant, so with his master; as with the maid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the lender, so with the borrower; as with the taker of usury, so with the giver of usury to him.

^3The land shall be utterly emptied, and utterly spoiled: for the Lord hath spoken this word.

^4The earth mourneth and fadeth away, the world languisheth and fadeth away, the haughty people of the earth do languish.

^5The earth also is defiled under the inhabitants thereof; because they have transgressed the laws, changed the ordinance, broken the everlasting covenant.

^6Therefore hath the curse devoured the earth, and they that dwell therein are desolate: therefore the inhabitants of the earth are burned, and few men left.

^7The new wine mourneth, the vine languisheth, all the merryhearted do sigh.

^8The mirth of tabrets ceaseth, the noise of them that rejoice endeth, the joy of the harp ceaseth.

^9They shall not drink wine with a song; strong drink shall be bitter to them that drink it.

^10The city of confusion is broken down: every house is shut up, that no man may come in.

^11There is a crying for wine in the streets; all joy is darkened, the mirth of the land is gone.

^12In the city is left desolation, and the gate is smitten with destruction.

^13When thus it shall be in the midst of the land among the people, there shall be as the shaking of an olive tree, and as the gleaning grapes when the vintage is done.

^14They shall lift up their voice, they shall sing for the majesty of the Lord, they shall cry aloud from the sea.

^15Wherefore glorify ye the Lord in the fires, even the name of the Lord God of Israel in the isles of the sea.

^16From the uttermost part of the earth have we heard songs, even glory to the righteous. But I said, My leanness, my leanness, woe unto me! the treacherous dealers have dealt treacherously; yea, the treacherous dealers have dealt very treacherously.

^17Fear, and the pit, and the snare, are upon thee, O inhabitant of the earth.

^18And it shall come to pass, that he who fleeth from the noise of the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that cometh up out of the midst of the pit shall be taken in the snare: for the windows from on high are open, and the foundations of the earth do shake.

^19The earth is utterly broken down, the earth is clean dissolved, the earth is moved exceedingly.

^20The earth shall reel to and fro like a drunkard, and shall be removed like a cottage; and the transgression thereof shall be heavy upon it; and it shall fall, and not rise again.

^21And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall punish the host of the high ones that are on high, and the kings of the earth upon the earth.

^22And they shall be gathered together, as prisoners are gathered in the pit, and shall be shut up in the prison, and after many days shall they be visited.

^23Then the moon shall be confounded, and the sun ashamed, when the Lord of hosts shall reign in mount Zion, and in Jerusalem, and before his ancients gloriously.

Isaiah 25

25^1O Lord, thou art my God; I will exalt thee, I will praise thy name; for thou hast done wonderful things; thy counsels of old are faithfulness and truth.

^2For thou hast made of a city an heap; of a defenced city a ruin: a palace of strangers to be no city; it shall never be built.

^3Therefore shall the strong people glorify thee, the city of the terrible nations shall fear thee.

^4For thou hast been a strength to the poor, a strength to the needy in his distress, a refuge from the storm, a shadow from the heat, when the blast of the terrible ones is as a storm against the wall.

^5Thou shalt bring down the noise of strangers, as the heat in a dry place; even the heat with the shadow of a cloud: the branch of the terrible ones shall be brought low.

^6And in this mountain shall the Lord of hosts make unto all people a feast of fat things, a feast of wines on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees well refined.

^7And he will destroy in this mountain the face of the covering cast over all people, and the vail that is spread over all nations.

^8He will swallow up death in victory; and the Lord God will wipe away tears from off all faces; and the rebuke of his people shall he take away from off all the earth: for the Lord hath spoken it.

^9And it shall be said in that day, Lo, this is our God; we have waited for him, and he will save us: this is the Lord; we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoice in his salvation.

^10For in this mountain shall the hand of the Lord rest, and Moab shall be trodden down under him, even as straw is trodden down for the dunghill.

^11And he shall spread forth his hands in the midst of them, as he that swimmeth spreadeth forth his hands to swim: and he shall bring down their pride together with the spoils of their hands.

^12And the fortress of the high fort of thy walls shall he bring down, lay low, and bring to the ground, even to the dust.

Isaiah 26

26^1In that day shall this song be sung in the land of Judah; We have a strong city; salvation will God appoint for walls and bulwarks.

^2Open ye the gates, that the righteous nation which keepeth the truth may enter in.

^3Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whose mind is stayed on thee: because he trusteth in thee.

^4Trust ye in the Lord for ever: for in the Lord Jehovah is everlasting strength:

^5For he bringeth down them that dwell on high; the lofty city, he layeth it low; he layeth it low, even to the ground; he bringeth it even to the dust.

^6The foot shall tread it down, even the feet of the poor, and the steps of the needy.

^7The way of the just is uprightness: thou, most upright, dost weigh the path of the just.

^8Yea, in the way of thy judgments, O Lord, have we waited for thee; the desire of our soul is to thy name, and to the remembrance of thee.

^9With my soul have I desired thee in the night; yea, with my spirit within me will I seek thee early: for when thy judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world will learn righteousness.

^10Let favour be shewed to the wicked, yet will he not learn righteousness: in the land of uprightness will he deal unjustly, and will not behold the majesty of the Lord.

^11Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not see: but they shall see, and be ashamed for their envy at the people; yea, the fire of thine enemies shall devour them.

^12Lord, thou wilt ordain peace for us: for thou also hast wrought all our works in us.

^13O Lord our God, other lords beside thee have had dominion over us: but by thee only will we make mention of thy name.

^14They are dead, they shall not live; they are deceased, they shall not rise: therefore hast thou visited and destroyed them, and made all their memory to perish.

^15Thou hast increased the nation, O Lord, thou hast increased the nation: thou art glorified: thou hadst removed it far unto all the ends of the earth.

^16Lord, in trouble have they visited thee, they poured out a prayer when thy chastening was upon them.

^17Like as a woman with child, that draweth near the time of her delivery, is in pain, and crieth out in her pangs; so have we been in thy sight, O Lord.

^18We have been with child, we have been in pain, we have as it were brought forth wind; we have not wrought any deliverance in the earth; neither have the inhabitants of the world fallen.

^19Thy dead men shall live, together with my dead body shall they arise. Awake and sing, ye that dwell in dust: for thy dew is as the dew of herbs, and the earth shall cast out the dead.

^20Come, my people, enter thou into thy chambers, and shut thy doors about thee: hide thyself as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be overpast.

^21For, behold, the Lord cometh out of his place to punish the inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity: the earth also shall disclose her blood, and shall no more cover her slain.

Isaiah 27

27^1In that day the Lord with his sore and great and strong sword shall punish leviathan the piercing serpent, even leviathan that crooked serpent; and he shall slay the dragon that is in the sea.

^2In that day sing ye unto her, A vineyard of red wine.

^3I the Lord do keep it; I will water it every moment: lest any hurt it, I will keep it night and day.

^4Fury is not in me: who would set the briers and thorns against me in battle? I would go through them, I would burn them together.

^5Or let him take hold of my strength, that he may make peace with me; and he shall make peace with me.

^6He shall cause them that come of Jacob to take root: Israel shall blossom and bud, and fill the face of the world with fruit.

^7Hath he smitten him, as he smote those that smote him? or is he slain according to the slaughter of them that are slain by him?

^8In measure, when it shooteth forth, thou wilt debate with it: he stayeth his rough wind in the day of the east wind.

^9By this therefore shall the iniquity of Jacob be purged; and this is all the fruit to take away his sin; when he maketh all the stones of the altar as chalkstones that are beaten in sunder, the groves and images shall not stand up.

^10Yet the defenced city shall be desolate, and the habitation forsaken, and left like a wilderness: there shall the calf feed, and there shall he lie down, and consume the branches thereof.

^11When the boughs thereof are withered, they shall be broken off: the women come, and set them on fire: for it is a people of no understanding: therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he that formed them will shew them no favour.

^12And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall beat off from the channel of the river unto the stream of Egypt, and ye shall be gathered one by one, O ye children of Israel.

^13And it shall come to pass in that day, that the great trumpet shall be blown, and they shall come which were ready to perish in the land of Assyria, and the outcasts in the land of Egypt, and shall worship the Lord in the holy mount at Jerusalem.

Isaiah 28

28^1Woe to the crown of pride, to the drunkards of Ephraim, whose glorious beauty is a fading flower, which are on the head of the fat valleys of them that are overcome with wine!

^2Behold, the Lord hath a mighty and strong one, which as a tempest of hail and a destroying storm, as a flood of mighty waters overflowing, shall cast down to the earth with the hand.

^3The crown of pride, the drunkards of Ephraim, shall be trodden under feet:

^4And the glorious beauty, which is on the head of the fat valley, shall be a fading flower, and as the hasty fruit before the summer; which when he that looketh upon it seeth, while it is yet in his hand he eateth it up.

^5In that day shall the Lord of hosts be for a crown of glory, and for a diadem of beauty, unto the residue of his people,

^6And for a spirit of judgment to him that sitteth in judgment, and for strength to them that turn the battle to the gate.

^7But they also have erred through wine, and through strong drink are out of the way; the priest and the prophet have erred through strong drink, they are swallowed up of wine, they are out of the way through strong drink; they err in vision, they stumble in judgment.

^8For all tables are full of vomit and filthiness, so that there is no place clean.

^9Whom shall he teach knowledge? and whom shall he make to understand doctrine? them that are weaned from the milk, and drawn from the breasts.

^10For precept must be upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, and there a little:

^11For with stammering lips and another tongue will he speak to this people.

^12To whom he said, This is the rest wherewith ye may cause the weary to rest; and this is the refreshing: yet they would not hear.

^13But the word of the Lord was unto them precept upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, and there a little; that they might go, and fall backward, and be broken, and snared, and taken.

^14Wherefore hear the word of the Lord, ye scornful men, that rule this people which is in Jerusalem.

^15Because ye have said, We have made a covenant with death, and with hell are we at agreement; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, it shall not come unto us: for we have made lies our refuge, and under falsehood have we hid ourselves:

^16Therefore thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I lay in Zion for a foundation a stone, a tried stone, a precious corner stone, a sure foundation: he that believeth shall not make haste.

^17Judgment also will I lay to the line, and righteousness to the plummet: and the hail shall sweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters shall overflow the hiding place.

^18And your covenant with death shall be disannulled, and your agreement with hell shall not stand; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, then ye shall be trodden down by it.

^19From the time that it goeth forth it shall take you: for morning by morning shall it pass over, by day and by night: and it shall be a vexation only to understand the report.

^20For the bed is shorter than that a man can stretch himself on it: and the covering narrower than that he can wrap himself in it.

^21For the Lord shall rise up as in mount Perazim, he shall be wroth as in the valley of Gibeon, that he may do his work, his strange work; and bring to pass his act, his strange act.

^22Now therefore be ye not mockers, lest your bands be made strong: for I have heard from the Lord God of hosts a consumption, even determined upon the whole earth.

^23Give ye ear, and hear my voice; hearken, and hear my speech.

^24Doth the plowman plow all day to sow? doth he open and break the clods of his ground?

^25When he hath made plain the face thereof, doth he not cast abroad the fitches, and scatter the cummin, and cast in the principal wheat and the appointed barley and the rie in their place?

^26For his God doth instruct him to discretion, and doth teach him.

^27For the fitches are not threshed with a threshing instrument, neither is a cart wheel turned about upon the cummin; but the fitches are beaten out with a staff, and the cummin with a rod.

^28Bread corn is bruised; because he will not ever be threshing it, nor break it with the wheel of his cart, nor bruise it with his horsemen.

^29This also cometh forth from the Lord of hosts, which is wonderful in counsel, and excellent in working.

Isaiah 29

29^1Woe to Ariel, to Ariel, the city where David dwelt! add ye year to year; let them kill sacrifices.

^2Yet I will distress Ariel, and there shall be heaviness and sorrow: and it shall be unto me as Ariel.

^3And I will camp against thee round about, and will lay siege against thee with a mount, and I will raise forts against thee.

^4And thou shalt be brought down, and shalt speak out of the ground, and thy speech shall be low out of the dust, and thy voice shall be, as of one that hath a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and thy speech shall whisper out of the dust.

^5Moreover the multitude of thy strangers shall be like small dust, and the multitude of the terrible ones shall be as chaff that passeth away: yea, it shall be at an instant suddenly.

^6Thou shalt be visited of the Lord of hosts with thunder, and with earthquake, and great noise, with storm and tempest, and the flame of devouring fire.

^7And the multitude of all the nations that fight against Ariel, even all that fight against her and her munition, and that distress her, shall be as a dream of a night vision.

^8It shall even be as when an hungry man dreameth, and, behold, he eateth; but he awaketh, and his soul is empty: or as when a thirsty man dreameth, and, behold, he drinketh; but he awaketh, and, behold, he is faint, and his soul hath appetite: so shall the multitude of all the nations be, that fight against mount Zion.

^9Stay yourselves, and wonder; cry ye out, and cry: they are drunken, but not with wine; they stagger, but not with strong drink.

^10For the Lord hath poured out upon you the spirit of deep sleep, and hath closed your eyes: the prophets and your rulers, the seers hath he covered.

^11And the vision of all is become unto you as the words of a book that is sealed, which men deliver to one that is learned, saying, Read this, I pray thee: and he saith, I cannot; for it is sealed:

^12And the book is delivered to him that is not learned, saying, Read this, I pray thee: and he saith, I am not learned.

^13Wherefore the Lord said, Forasmuch as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honour me, but have removed their heart far from me, and their fear toward me is taught by the precept of men:

^14Therefore, behold, I will proceed to do a marvellous work among this people, even a marvellous work and a wonder: for the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the understanding of their prudent men shall be hid.

^15Woe unto them that seek deep to hide their counsel from the Lord, and their works are in the dark, and they say, Who seeth us? and who knoweth us?

^16Surely your turning of things upside down shall be esteemed as the potter’s clay: for shall the work say of him that made it, He made me not? or shall the thing framed say of him that framed it, He had no understanding?

^17Is it not yet a very little while, and Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field shall be esteemed as a forest?

^18And in that day shall the deaf hear the words of the book, and the eyes of the blind shall see out of obscurity, and out of darkness.

^19The meek also shall increase their joy in the Lord, and the poor among men shall rejoice in the Holy One of Israel.

^20For the terrible one is brought to nought, and the scorner is consumed, and all that watch for iniquity are cut off:

^21That make a man an offender for a word, and lay a snare for him that reproveth in the gate, and turn aside the just for a thing of nought.

^22Therefore thus saith the Lord, who redeemed Abraham, concerning the house of Jacob, Jacob shall not now be ashamed, neither shall his face now wax pale.

^23But when he seeth his children, the work of mine hands, in the midst of him, they shall sanctify my name, and sanctify the Holy One of Jacob, and shall fear the God of Israel.

^24They also that erred in spirit shall come to understanding, and they that murmured shall learn doctrine.

Isaiah 30

30^1Woe to the rebellious children, saith the Lord, that take counsel, but not of me; and that cover with a covering, but not of my spirit, that they may add sin to sin:

^2That walk to go down into Egypt, and have not asked at my mouth; to strengthen themselves in the strength of Pharaoh, and to trust in the shadow of Egypt!

^3Therefore shall the strength of Pharaoh be your shame, and the trust in the shadow of Egypt your confusion.

^4For his princes were at Zoan, and his ambassadors came to Hanes.

^5They were all ashamed of a people that could not profit them, nor be an help nor profit, but a shame, and also a reproach.

^6The burden of the beasts of the south: into the land of trouble and anguish, from whence come the young and old lion, the viper and fiery flying serpent, they will carry their riches upon the shoulders of young asses, and their treasures upon the bunches of camels, to a people that shall not profit them.

^7For the Egyptians shall help in vain, and to no purpose: therefore have I cried concerning this, Their strength is to sit still.

^8Now go, write it before them in a table, and note it in a book, that it may be for the time to come for ever and ever:

^9That this is a rebellious people, lying children, children that will not hear the law of the Lord:

^10Which say to the seers, See not; and to the prophets, Prophesy not unto us right things, speak unto us smooth things, prophesy deceits:

^11Get you out of the way, turn aside out of the path, cause the Holy One of Israel to cease from before us.

^12Wherefore thus saith the Holy One of Israel, Because ye despise this word, and trust in oppression and perverseness, and stay thereon:

^13Therefore this iniquity shall be to you as a breach ready to fall, swelling out in a high wall, whose breaking cometh suddenly at an instant.

^14And he shall break it as the breaking of the potters’ vessel that is broken in pieces; he shall not spare: so that there shall not be found in the bursting of it a sherd to take fire from the hearth, or to take water withal out of the pit.

^15For thus saith the Lord God, the Holy One of Israel; In returning and rest shall ye be saved; in quietness and in confidence shall be your strength: and ye would not.

^16But ye said, No; for we will flee upon horses; therefore shall ye flee: and, We will ride upon the swift; therefore shall they that pursue you be swift.

^17One thousand shall flee at the rebuke of one; at the rebuke of five shall ye flee: till ye be left as a beacon upon the top of a mountain, and as an ensign on an hill.

^18And therefore will the Lord wait, that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you: for the Lord is a God of judgment: blessed are all they that wait for him.

^19For the people shall dwell in Zion at Jerusalem: thou shalt weep no more: he will be very gracious unto thee at the voice of thy cry; when he shall hear it, he will answer thee.

^20And though the Lord give you the bread of adversity, and the water of affliction, yet shall not thy teachers be removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes shall see thy teachers:

^21And thine ears shall hear a word behind thee, saying, This is the way, walk ye in it, when ye turn to the right hand, and when ye turn to the left.

^22Ye shall defile also the covering of thy graven images of silver, and the ornament of thy molten images of gold: thou shalt cast them away as a menstruous cloth; thou shalt say unto it, Get thee hence.

^23Then shall he give the rain of thy seed, that thou shalt sow the ground withal; and bread of the increase of the earth, and it shall be fat and plenteous: in that day shall thy cattle feed in large pastures.

^24The oxen likewise and the young asses that ear the ground shall eat clean provender, which hath been winnowed with the shovel and with the fan.

^25And there shall be upon every high mountain, and upon every high hill, rivers and streams of waters in the day of the great slaughter, when the towers fall.

^26Moreover the light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun, and the light of the sun shall be sevenfold, as the light of seven days, in the day that the Lord bindeth up the breach of his people, and healeth the stroke of their wound.

^27Behold, the name of the Lord cometh from far, burning with his anger, and the burden thereof is heavy: his lips are full of indignation, and his tongue as a devouring fire:

^28And his breath, as an overflowing stream, shall reach to the midst of the neck, to sift the nations with the sieve of vanity: and there shall be a bridle in the jaws of the people, causing them to err.

^29Ye shall have a song, as in the night when a holy solemnity is kept; and gladness of heart, as when one goeth with a pipe to come into the mountain of the Lord, to the mighty One of Israel.

^30And the Lord shall cause his glorious voice to be heard, and shall shew the lighting down of his arm, with the indignation of his anger, and with the flame of a devouring fire, with scattering, and tempest, and hailstones.

^31For through the voice of the Lord shall the Assyrian be beaten down, which smote with a rod.

^32And in every place where the grounded staff shall pass, which the Lord shall lay upon him, it shall be with tabrets and harps: and in battles of shaking will he fight with it.

^33For Tophet is ordained of old; yea, for the king it is prepared; he hath made it deep and large: the pile thereof is fire and much wood; the breath of the Lord, like a stream of brimstone, doth kindle it.

Isaiah 31

31^1Woe to them that go down to Egypt for help; and stay on horses, and trust in chariots, because they are many; and in horsemen, because they are very strong; but they look not unto the Holy One of Israel, neither seek the Lord!

^2Yet he also is wise, and will bring evil, and will not call back his words: but will arise against the house of the evildoers, and against the help of them that work iniquity.

^3Now the Egyptians are men, and not God; and their horses flesh, and not spirit. When the Lord shall stretch out his hand, both he that helpeth shall fall, and he that is holpen shall fall down, and they all shall fail together.

^4For thus hath the Lord spoken unto me, Like as the lion and the young lion roaring on his prey, when a multitude of shepherds is called forth against him, he will not be afraid of their voice, nor abase himself for the noise of them: so shall the Lord of hosts come down to fight for mount Zion, and for the hill thereof.

^5As birds flying, so will the Lord of hosts defend Jerusalem; defending also he will deliver it; and passing over he will preserve it.

^6Turn ye unto him from whom the children of Israel have deeply revolted.

^7For in that day every man shall cast away his idols of silver, and his idols of gold, which your own hands have made unto you for a sin.

^8Then shall the Assyrian fall with the sword, not of a mighty man; and the sword, not of a mean man, shall devour him: but he shall flee from the sword, and his young men shall be discomfited.

^9And he shall pass over to his strong hold for fear, and his princes shall be afraid of the ensign, saith the Lord, whose fire is in Zion, and his furnace in Jerusalem.

Isaiah 32

32^1Behold, a king shall reign in righteousness, and princes shall rule in judgment.

^2And a man shall be as an hiding place from the wind, and a covert from the tempest; as rivers of water in a dry place, as the shadow of a great rock in a weary land.

^3And the eyes of them that see shall not be dim, and the ears of them that hear shall hearken.

^4The heart also of the rash shall understand knowledge, and the tongue of the stammerers shall be ready to speak plainly.

^5The vile person shall be no more called liberal, nor the churl said to be bountiful.

^6For the vile person will speak villany, and his heart will work iniquity, to practise hypocrisy, and to utter error against the Lord, to make empty the soul of the hungry, and he will cause the drink of the thirsty to fail.

^7The instruments also of the churl are evil: he deviseth wicked devices to destroy the poor with lying words, even when the needy speaketh right.

^8But the liberal deviseth liberal things; and by liberal things shall he stand.

^9Rise up, ye women that are at ease; hear my voice, ye careless daughters; give ear unto my speech.

^10Many days and years shall ye be troubled, ye careless women: for the vintage shall fail, the gathering shall not come.

^11Tremble, ye women that are at ease; be troubled, ye careless ones: strip you, and make you bare, and gird sackcloth upon your loins.

^12They shall lament for the teats, for the pleasant fields, for the fruitful vine.

^13Upon the land of my people shall come up thorns and briers; yea, upon all the houses of joy in the joyous city:

^14Because the palaces shall be forsaken; the multitude of the city shall be left; the forts and towers shall be for dens for ever, a joy of wild asses, a pasture of flocks;

^15Until the spirit be poured upon us from on high, and the wilderness be a fruitful field, and the fruitful field be counted for a forest.

^16Then judgment shall dwell in the wilderness, and righteousness remain in the fruitful field.

^17And the work of righteousness shall be peace; and the effect of righteousness quietness and assurance for ever.

^18And my people shall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in sure dwellings, and in quiet resting places;

^19When it shall hail, coming down on the forest; and the city shall be low in a low place.

^20Blessed are ye that sow beside all waters, that send forth thither the feet of the ox and the ass.

Isaiah 33

33^1Woe to thee that spoilest, and thou wast not spoiled; and dealest treacherously, and they dealt not treacherously with thee! when thou shalt cease to spoil, thou shalt be spoiled; and when thou shalt make an end to deal treacherously, they shall deal treacherously with thee.

^2O Lord, be gracious unto us; we have waited for thee: be thou their arm every morning, our salvation also in the time of trouble.

^3At the noise of the tumult the people fled; at the lifting up of thyself the nations were scattered.

^4And your spoil shall be gathered like the gathering of the caterpiller: as the running to and fro of locusts shall he run upon them.

^5The Lord is exalted; for he dwelleth on high: he hath filled Zion with judgment and righteousness.

^6And wisdom and knowledge shall be the stability of thy times, and strength of salvation: the fear of the Lord is his treasure.

^7Behold, their valiant ones shall cry without: the ambassadors of peace shall weep bitterly.

^8The highways lie waste, the wayfaring man ceaseth: he hath broken the covenant, he hath despised the cities, he regardeth no man.

^9The earth mourneth and languisheth: Lebanon is ashamed and hewn down: Sharon is like a wilderness; and Bashan and Carmel shake off their fruits.

^10Now will I rise, saith the Lord; now will I be exalted; now will I lift up myself.

^11Ye shall conceive chaff, ye shall bring forth stubble: your breath, as fire, shall devour you.

^12And the people shall be as the burnings of lime: as thorns cut up shall they be burned in the fire.

^13Hear, ye that are far off, what I have done; and, ye that are near, acknowledge my might.

^14The sinners in Zion are afraid; fearfulness hath surprised the hypocrites. Who among us shall dwell with the devouring fire? who among us shall dwell with everlasting burnings?

^15He that walketh righteously, and speaketh uprightly; he that despiseth the gain of oppressions, that shaketh his hands from holding of bribes, that stoppeth his ears from hearing of blood, and shutteth his eyes from seeing evil;

^16He shall dwell on high: his place of defence shall be the munitions of rocks: bread shall be given him; his waters shall be sure.

^17Thine eyes shall see the king in his beauty: they shall behold the land that is very far off.

^18Thine heart shall meditate terror. Where is the scribe? where is the receiver? where is he that counted the towers?

^19Thou shalt not see a fierce people, a people of a deeper speech than thou canst perceive; of a stammering tongue, that thou canst not understand.

^20Look upon Zion, the city of our solemnities: thine eyes shall see Jerusalem a quiet habitation, a tabernacle that shall not be taken down; not one of the stakes thereof shall ever be removed, neither shall any of the cords thereof be broken.

^21But there the glorious Lord will be unto us a place of broad rivers and streams; wherein shall go no galley with oars, neither shall gallant ship pass thereby.

^22For the Lord is our judge, the Lord is our lawgiver, the Lord is our king; he will save us.

^23Thy tacklings are loosed; they could not well strengthen their mast, they could not spread the sail: then is the prey of a great spoil divided; the lame take the prey.

^24And the inhabitant shall not say, I am sick: the people that dwell therein shall be forgiven their iniquity.

Isaiah 34

34^1Come near, ye nations, to hear; and hearken, ye people: let the earth hear, and all that is therein; the world, and all things that come forth of it.

^2For the indignation of the Lord is upon all nations, and his fury upon all their armies: he hath utterly destroyed them, he hath delivered them to the slaughter.

^3Their slain also shall be cast out, and their stink shall come up out of their carcases, and the mountains shall be melted with their blood.

^4And all the host of heaven shall be dissolved, and the heavens shall be rolled together as a scroll: and all their host shall fall down, as the leaf falleth off from the vine, and as a falling fig from the fig tree.

^5For my sword shall be bathed in heaven: behold, it shall come down upon Idumea, and upon the people of my curse, to judgment.

^6The sword of the Lord is filled with blood, it is made fat with fatness, and with the blood of lambs and goats, with the fat of the kidneys of rams: for the Lord hath a sacrifice in Bozrah, and a great slaughter in the land of Idumea.

^7And the unicorns shall come down with them, and the bullocks with the bulls; and their land shall be soaked with blood, and their dust made fat with fatness.

^8For it is the day of the Lord’s vengeance, and the year of recompences for the controversy of Zion.

^9And the streams thereof shall be turned into pitch, and the dust thereof into brimstone, and the land thereof shall become burning pitch.

^10It shall not be quenched night nor day; the smoke thereof shall go up for ever: from generation to generation it shall lie waste; none shall pass through it for ever and ever.

^11But the cormorant and the bittern shall possess it; the owl also and the raven shall dwell in it: and he shall stretch out upon it the line of confusion, and the stones of emptiness.

^12They shall call the nobles thereof to the kingdom, but none shall be there, and all her princes shall be nothing.

^13And thorns shall come up in her palaces, nettles and brambles in the fortresses thereof: and it shall be an habitation of dragons, and a court for owls.

^14The wild beasts of the desert shall also meet with the wild beasts of the island, and the satyr shall cry to his fellow; the screech owl also shall rest there, and find for herself a place of rest.

^15There shall the great owl make her nest, and lay, and hatch, and gather under her shadow: there shall the vultures also be gathered, every one with her mate.

^16Seek ye out of the book of the Lord, and read: no one of these shall fail, none shall want her mate: for my mouth it hath commanded, and his spirit it hath gathered them.

^17And he hath cast the lot for them, and his hand hath divided it unto them by line: they shall possess it for ever, from generation to generation shall they dwell therein.

Isaiah 35

35^1The wilderness and the solitary place shall be glad for them; and the desert shall rejoice, and blossom as the rose.

^2It shall blossom abundantly, and rejoice even with joy and singing: the glory of Lebanon shall be given unto it, the excellency of Carmel and Sharon, they shall see the glory of the Lord, and the excellency of our God.

^3Strengthen ye the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees.

^4Say to them that are of a fearful heart, Be strong, fear not: behold, your God will come with vengeance, even God with a recompence; he will come and save you.

^5Then the eyes of the blind shall be opened, and the ears of the deaf shall be unstopped.

^6Then shall the lame man leap as an hart, and the tongue of the dumb sing: for in the wilderness shall waters break out, and streams in the desert.

^7And the parched ground shall become a pool, and the thirsty land springs of water: in the habitation of dragons, where each lay, shall be grass with reeds and rushes.

^8And an highway shall be there, and a way, and it shall be called The way of holiness; the unclean shall not pass over it; but it shall be for those: the wayfaring men, though fools, shall not err therein.

^9No lion shall be there, nor any ravenous beast shall go up thereon, it shall not be found there; but the redeemed shall walk there:

^10And the ransomed of the Lord shall return, and come to Zion with songs and everlasting joy upon their heads: they shall obtain joy and gladness, and sorrow and sighing shall flee away.

Isaiah 36

36^1Now it came to pass in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, that Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the defenced cities of Judah, and took them.

^2And the king of Assyria sent Rabshakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem unto king Hezekiah with a great army. And he stood by the conduit of the upper pool in the highway of the fuller’s field.

^3Then came forth unto him Eliakim, Hilkiah’s son, which was over the house, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, Asaph’s son, the recorder.

^4And Rabshakeh said unto them, Say ye now to Hezekiah, Thus saith the great king, the king of Assyria, What confidence is this wherein thou trustest?

^5I say, sayest thou, (but they are but vain words) I have counsel and strength for war: now on whom dost thou trust, that thou rebellest against me?

^6Lo, thou trustest in the staff of this broken reed, on Egypt; whereon if a man lean, it will go into his hand, and pierce it: so is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all that trust in him.

^7But if thou say to me, We trust in the Lord our God: is it not he, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah hath taken away, and said to Judah and to Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar?

^8Now therefore give pledges, I pray thee, to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them.

^9How then wilt thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master’s servants, and put thy trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen?

^10And am I now come up without the Lord against this land to destroy it? the Lord said unto me, Go up against this land, and destroy it.

^11Then said Eliakim and Shebna and Joah unto Rabshakeh, Speak, I pray thee, unto thy servants in the Syrian language; for we understand it: and speak not to us in the Jews’ language, in the ears of the people that are on the wall.

^12But Rabshakeh said, Hath my master sent me to thy master and to thee to speak these words? hath he not sent me to the men that sit upon the wall, that they may eat their own dung, and drink their own piss with you?

^13Then Rabshakeh stood, and cried with a loud voice in the Jews’ language, and said, Hear ye the words of the great king, the king of Assyria.

^14Thus saith the king, Let not Hezekiah deceive you: for he shall not be able to deliver you.

^15Neither let Hezekiah make you trust in the Lord, saying, The Lord will surely deliver us: this city shall not be delivered into the hand of the king of Assyria.

^16Hearken not to Hezekiah: for thus saith the king of Assyria, Make an agreement with me by a present, and come out to me: and eat ye every one of his vine, and every one of his fig tree, and drink ye every one the waters of his own cistern;

^17Until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of corn and wine, a land of bread and vineyards.

^18Beware lest Hezekiah persuade you, saying, the Lord will deliver us. Hath any of the gods of the nations delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria?

^19Where are the gods of Hamath and Arphad? where are the gods of Sepharvaim? and have they delivered Samaria out of my hand?

^20Who are they among all the gods of these lands, that have delivered their land out of my hand, that the Lord should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?

^21But they held their peace, and answered him not a word: for the king’s commandment was, saying, Answer him not.

^22Then came Eliakim, the son of Hilkiah, that was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph, the recorder, to Hezekiah with their clothes rent, and told him the words of Rabshakeh.

Isaiah 37

37^1And it came to pass, when king Hezekiah heard it, that he rent his clothes, and covered himself with sackcloth, and went into the house of the Lord.

^2And he sent Eliakim, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests covered with sackcloth, unto Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz.

^3And they said unto him, Thus saith Hezekiah, This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of blasphemy: for the children are come to the birth, and there is not strength to bring forth.

^4It may be the Lord thy God will hear the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of Assyria his master hath sent to reproach the living God, and will reprove the words which the Lord thy God hath heard: wherefore lift up thy prayer for the remnant that is left.

^5So the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah.

^6And Isaiah said unto them, Thus shall ye say unto your master, Thus saith the Lord, Be not afraid of the words that thou hast heard, wherewith the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me.

^7Behold, I will send a blast upon him, and he shall hear a rumour, and return to his own land; and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.

^8So Rabshakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah: for he had heard that he was departed from Lachish.

^9And he heard say concerning Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, He is come forth to make war with thee. And when he heard it, he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying,

^10Thus shall ye speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, Let not thy God, in whom thou trustest, deceive thee, saying, Jerusalem shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.

^11Behold, thou hast heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands by destroying them utterly; and shalt thou be delivered?

^12Have the gods of the nations delivered them which my fathers have destroyed, as Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the children of Eden which were in Telassar?

^13Where is the king of Hamath, and the king of Arphad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivah?

^14And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers, and read it: and Hezekiah went up unto the house of the Lord, and spread it before the Lord.

^15And Hezekiah prayed unto the Lord, saying,

^16O Lord of hosts, God of Israel, that dwellest between the cherubims, thou art the God, even thou alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth: thou hast made heaven and earth.

^17Incline thine ear, O Lord, and hear; open thine eyes, O Lord, and see: and hear all the words of Sennacherib, which hath sent to reproach the living God.

^18Of a truth, Lord, the kings of Assyria have laid waste all the nations, and their countries,

^19And have cast their gods into the fire: for they were no gods, but the work of men’s hands, wood and stone: therefore they have destroyed them.

^20Now therefore, O Lord our God, save us from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that thou art the Lord, even thou only.

^21Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent unto Hezekiah, saying, Thus saith the Lord God of Israel, Whereas thou hast prayed to me against Sennacherib king of Assyria:

^22This is the word which the Lord hath spoken concerning him; The virgin, the daughter of Zion, hath despised thee, and laughed thee to scorn; the daughter of Jerusalem hath shaken her head at thee.

^23Whom hast thou reproached and blasphemed? and against whom hast thou exalted thy voice, and lifted up thine eyes on high? even against the Holy One of Israel.

^24By thy servants hast thou reproached the Lord, and hast said, By the multitude of my chariots am I come up to the height of the mountains, to the sides of Lebanon; and I will cut down the tall cedars thereof, and the choice fir trees thereof: and I will enter into the height of his border, and the forest of his Carmel.

^25I have digged, and drunk water; and with the sole of my feet have I dried up all the rivers of the besieged places.

^26Hast thou not heard long ago, how I have done it; and of ancient times, that I have formed it? now have I brought it to pass, that thou shouldest be to lay waste defenced cities into ruinous heaps.

^27Therefore their inhabitants were of small power, they were dismayed and confounded: they were as the grass of the field, and as the green herb, as the grass on the housetops, and as corn blasted before it be grown up.

^28But I know thy abode, and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy rage against me.

^29Because thy rage against me, and thy tumult, is come up into mine ears, therefore will I put my hook in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I will turn thee back by the way by which thou camest.

^30And this shall be a sign unto thee, Ye shall eat this year such as groweth of itself; and the second year that which springeth of the same: and in the third year sow ye, and reap, and plant vineyards, and eat the fruit thereof.

^31And the remnant that is escaped of the house of Judah shall again take root downward, and bear fruit upward:

^32For out of Jerusalem shall go forth a remnant, and they that escape out of mount Zion: the zeal of the Lord of hosts shall do this.

^33Therefore thus saith the Lord concerning the king of Assyria, He shall not come into this city, nor shoot an arrow there, nor come before it with shields, nor cast a bank against it.

^34By the way that he came, by the same shall he return, and shall not come into this city, saith the Lord.

^35For I will defend this city to save it for mine own sake, and for my servant David’s sake.

^36Then the angel of the Lord went forth, and smote in the camp of the Assyrians a hundred and fourscore and five thousand: and when they arose early in the morning, behold, they were all dead corpses.

^37So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and dwelt at Nineveh.

^38And it came to pass, as he was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that Adrammelech and Sharezer his sons smote him with the sword; and they escaped into the land of Armenia: and Esarhaddon his son reigned in his stead.

Isaiah 38

38^1In those days was Hezekiah sick unto death. And Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz came unto him, and said unto him, Thus saith the Lord, Set thine house in order: for thou shalt die, and not live.

^2Then Hezekiah turned his face toward the wall, and prayed unto the Lord,

^3And said, Remember now, O Lord, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept sore.

^4Then came the word of the Lord to Isaiah, saying,

^5Go, and say to Hezekiah, Thus saith the Lord, the God of David thy father, I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will add unto thy days fifteen years.

^6And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria: and I will defend this city.

^7And this shall be a sign unto thee from the Lord, that the Lord will do this thing that he hath spoken;

^8Behold, I will bring again the shadow of the degrees, which is gone down in the sun dial of Ahaz, ten degrees backward. So the sun returned ten degrees, by which degrees it was gone down.

^9The writing of Hezekiah king of Judah, when he had been sick, and was recovered of his sickness:

^10I said in the cutting off of my days, I shall go to the gates of the grave: I am deprived of the residue of my years.

^11I said, I shall not see the Lord, even the Lord, in the land of the living: I shall behold man no more with the inhabitants of the world.

^12Mine age is departed, and is removed from me as a shepherd’s tent: I have cut off like a weaver my life: he will cut me off with pining sickness: from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me.

^13I reckoned till morning, that, as a lion, so will he break all my bones: from day even to night wilt thou make an end of me.

^14Like a crane or a swallow, so did I chatter: I did mourn as a dove: mine eyes fail with looking upward: O Lord, I am oppressed; undertake for me.

^15What shall I say? he hath both spoken unto me, and himself hath done it: I shall go softly all my years in the bitterness of my soul.

^16O Lord, by these things men live, and in all these things is the life of my spirit: so wilt thou recover me, and make me to live.

^17Behold, for peace I had great bitterness: but thou hast in love to my soul delivered it from the pit of corruption: for thou hast cast all my sins behind thy back.

^18For the grave cannot praise thee, death can not celebrate thee: they that go down into the pit cannot hope for thy truth.

^19The living, the living, he shall praise thee, as I do this day: the father to the children shall make known thy truth.

^20The Lord was ready to save me: therefore we will sing my songs to the stringed instruments all the days of our life in the house of the Lord.

^21For Isaiah had said, Let them take a lump of figs, and lay it for a plaister upon the boil, and he shall recover.

^22Hezekiah also had said, What is the sign that I shall go up to the house of the Lord?

Isaiah 39

39^1At that time Merodachbaladan, the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah: for he had heard that he had been sick, and was recovered.

^2And Hezekiah was glad of them, and shewed them the house of his precious things, the silver, and the gold, and the spices, and the precious ointment, and all the house of his armour, and all that was found in his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah shewed them not.

^3Then came Isaiah the prophet unto king Hezekiah, and said unto him, What said these men? and from whence came they unto thee? And Hezekiah said, They are come from a far country unto me, even from Babylon.

^4Then said he, What have they seen in thine house? And Hezekiah answered, All that is in mine house have they seen: there is nothing among my treasures that I have not shewed them.

^5Then said Isaiah to Hezekiah, Hear the word of the Lord of hosts:

^6Behold, the days come, that all that is in thine house, and that which thy fathers have laid up in store until this day, shall be carried to Babylon: nothing shall be left, saith the Lord.

^7And of thy sons that shall issue from thee, which thou shalt beget, shall they take away; and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.

^8Then said Hezekiah to Isaiah, Good is the word of the Lord which thou hast spoken. He said moreover, For there shall be peace and truth in my days.

Isaiah 40

40^1Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, saith your God.

^2Speak ye comfortably to Jerusalem, and cry unto her, that her warfare is accomplished, that her iniquity is pardoned: for she hath received of the Lord’s hand double for all her sins.

^3The voice of him that crieth in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make straight in the desert a highway for our God.

^4Every valley shall be exalted, and every mountain and hill shall be made low: and the crooked shall be made straight, and the rough places plain:

^5And the glory of the Lord shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see it together: for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.

^6The voice said, Cry. And he said, What shall I cry? All flesh is grass, and all the goodliness thereof is as the flower of the field:

^7The grass withereth, the flower fadeth: because the spirit of the Lord bloweth upon it: surely the people is grass.

^8The grass withereth, the flower fadeth: but the word of our God shall stand for ever.

^9O Zion, that bringest good tidings, get thee up into the high mountain; O Jerusalem, that bringest good tidings, lift up thy voice with strength; lift it up, be not afraid; say unto the cities of Judah, Behold your God!

^10Behold, the Lord God will come with strong hand, and his arm shall rule for him: behold, his reward is with him, and his work before him.

^11He shall feed his flock like a shepherd: he shall gather the lambs with his arm, and carry them in his bosom, and shall gently lead those that are with young.

^12Who hath measured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out heaven with the span, and comprehended the dust of the earth in a measure, and weighed the mountains in scales, and the hills in a balance?

^13Who hath directed the Spirit of the Lord, or being his counsellor hath taught him?

^14With whom took he counsel, and who instructed him, and taught him in the path of judgment, and taught him knowledge, and shewed to him the way of understanding?

^15Behold, the nations are as a drop of a bucket, and are counted as the small dust of the balance: behold, he taketh up the isles as a very little thing.

^16And Lebanon is not sufficient to burn, nor the beasts thereof sufficient for a burnt offering.

^17All nations before him are as nothing; and they are counted to him less than nothing, and vanity.

^18To whom then will ye liken God? or what likeness will ye compare unto him?

^19The workman melteth a graven image, and the goldsmith spreadeth it over with gold, and casteth silver chains.

^20He that is so impoverished that he hath no oblation chooseth a tree that will not rot; he seeketh unto him a cunning workman to prepare a graven image, that shall not be moved.

^21Have ye not known? have ye not heard? hath it not been told you from the beginning? have ye not understood from the foundations of the earth?

^22It is he that sitteth upon the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof are as grasshoppers; that stretcheth out the heavens as a curtain, and spreadeth them out as a tent to dwell in:

^23That bringeth the princes to nothing; he maketh the judges of the earth as vanity.

^24Yea, they shall not be planted; yea, they shall not be sown: yea, their stock shall not take root in the earth: and he shall also blow upon them, and they shall wither, and the whirlwind shall take them away as stubble.

^25To whom then will ye liken me, or shall I be equal? saith the Holy One.

^26Lift up your eyes on high, and behold who hath created these things, that bringeth out their host by number: he calleth them all by names by the greatness of his might, for that he is strong in power; not one faileth.

^27Why sayest thou, O Jacob, and speakest, O Israel, My way is hid from the Lord, and my judgment is passed over from my God?

^28Hast thou not known? hast thou not heard, that the everlasting God, the Lord, the Creator of the ends of the earth, fainteth not, neither is weary? there is no searching of his understanding.

^29He giveth power to the faint; and to them that have no might he increaseth strength.

^30Even the youths shall faint and be weary, and the young men shall utterly fall:

^31But they that wait upon the Lord shall renew their strength; they shall mount up with wings as eagles; they shall run, and not be weary; and they shall walk, and not faint.

Isaiah 41

41^1Keep silence before me, O islands; and let the people renew their strength: let them come near; then let them speak: let us come near together to judgment.

^2Who raised up the righteous man from the east, called him to his foot, gave the nations before him, and made him rule over kings? he gave them as the dust to his sword, and as driven stubble to his bow.

^3He pursued them, and passed safely; even by the way that he had not gone with his feet.

^4Who hath wrought and done it, calling the generations from the beginning? I the Lord, the first, and with the last; I am he.

^5The isles saw it, and feared; the ends of the earth were afraid, drew near, and came.

^6They helped every one his neighbour; and every one said to his brother, Be of good courage.

^7So the carpenter encouraged the goldsmith, and he that smootheth with the hammer him that smote the anvil, saying, It is ready for the sodering: and he fastened it with nails, that it should not be moved.

^8But thou, Israel, art my servant, Jacob whom I have chosen, the seed of Abraham my friend.

^9Thou whom I have taken from the ends of the earth, and called thee from the chief men thereof, and said unto thee, Thou art my servant; I have chosen thee, and not cast thee away.

^10Fear thou not; for I am with thee: be not dismayed; for I am thy God: I will strengthen thee; yea, I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteousness.

^11Behold, all they that were incensed against thee shall be ashamed and confounded: they shall be as nothing; and they that strive with thee shall perish.

^12Thou shalt seek them, and shalt not find them, even them that contended with thee: they that war against thee shall be as nothing, and as a thing of nought.

^13For I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand, saying unto thee, Fear not; I will help thee.

^14Fear not, thou worm Jacob, and ye men of Israel; I will help thee, saith the Lord, and thy redeemer, the Holy One of Israel.

^15Behold, I will make thee a new sharp threshing instrument having teeth: thou shalt thresh the mountains, and beat them small, and shalt make the hills as chaff.

^16Thou shalt fan them, and the wind shall carry them away, and the whirlwind shall scatter them: and thou shalt rejoice in the Lord, and shalt glory in the Holy One of Israel.

^17When the poor and needy seek water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirst, I the Lord will hear them, I the God of Israel will not forsake them.

^18I will open rivers in high places, and fountains in the midst of the valleys: I will make the wilderness a pool of water, and the dry land springs of water.

^19I will plant in the wilderness the cedar, the shittah tree, and the myrtle, and the oil tree; I will set in the desert the fir tree, and the pine, and the box tree together:

^20That they may see, and know, and consider, and understand together, that the hand of the Lord hath done this, and the Holy One of Israel hath created it.

^21Produce your cause, saith the Lord; bring forth your strong reasons, saith the King of Jacob.

^22Let them bring them forth, and shew us what shall happen: let them shew the former things, what they be, that we may consider them, and know the latter end of them; or declare us things for to come.

^23Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are gods: yea, do good, or do evil, that we may be dismayed, and behold it together.

^24Behold, ye are of nothing, and your work of nought: an abomination is he that chooseth you.

^25I have raised up one from the north, and he shall come: from the rising of the sun shall he call upon my name: and he shall come upon princes as upon morter, and as the potter treadeth clay.

^26Who hath declared from the beginning, that we may know? and beforetime, that we may say, He is righteous? yea, there is none that sheweth, yea, there is none that declareth, yea, there is none that heareth your words.

^27The first shall say to Zion, Behold, behold them: and I will give to Jerusalem one that bringeth good tidings.

^28For I beheld, and there was no man; even among them, and there was no counsellor, that, when I asked of them, could answer a word.

^29Behold, they are all vanity; their works are nothing: their molten images are wind and confusion.

Isaiah 42

42^1Behold my servant, whom I uphold; mine elect, in whom my soul delighteth; I have put my spirit upon him: he shall bring forth judgment to the Gentiles.

^2He shall not cry, nor lift up, nor cause his voice to be heard in the street.

^3A bruised reed shall he not break, and the smoking flax shall he not quench: he shall bring forth judgment unto truth.

^4He shall not fail nor be discouraged, till he have set judgment in the earth: and the isles shall wait for his law.

^5Thus saith God the Lord, he that created the heavens, and stretched them out; he that spread forth the earth, and that which cometh out of it; he that giveth breath unto the people upon it, and spirit to them that walk therein:

^6I the Lord have called thee in righteousness, and will hold thine hand, and will keep thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, for a light of the Gentiles;

^7To open the blind eyes, to bring out the prisoners from the prison, and them that sit in darkness out of the prison house.

^8I am the Lord: that is my name: and my glory will I not give to another, neither my praise to graven images.

^9Behold, the former things are come to pass, and new things do I declare: before they spring forth I tell you of them.

^10Sing unto the Lord a new song, and his praise from the end of the earth, ye that go down to the sea, and all that is therein; the isles, and the inhabitants thereof.

^11Let the wilderness and the cities thereof lift up their voice, the villages that Kedar doth inhabit: let the inhabitants of the rock sing, let them shout from the top of the mountains.

^12Let them give glory unto the Lord, and declare his praise in the islands.

^13The Lord shall go forth as a mighty man, he shall stir up jealousy like a man of war: he shall cry, yea, roar; he shall prevail against his enemies.

^14I have long time holden my peace; I have been still, and refrained myself: now will I cry like a travailing woman; I will destroy and devour at once.

^15I will make waste mountains and hills, and dry up all their herbs; and I will make the rivers islands, and I will dry up the pools.

^16And I will bring the blind by a way that they knew not; I will lead them in paths that they have not known: I will make darkness light before them, and crooked things straight. These things will I do unto them, and not forsake them.

^17They shall be turned back, they shall be greatly ashamed, that trust in graven images, that say to the molten images, Ye are our gods.

^18Hear, ye deaf; and look, ye blind, that ye may see.

^19Who is blind, but my servant? or deaf, as my messenger that I sent? who is blind as he that is perfect, and blind as the Lord’s servant?

^20Seeing many things, but thou observest not; opening the ears, but he heareth not.

^21The Lord is well pleased for his righteousness’ sake; he will magnify the law, and make it honourable.

^22But this is a people robbed and spoiled; they are all of them snared in holes, and they are hid in prison houses: they are for a prey, and none delivereth; for a spoil, and none saith, Restore.

^23Who among you will give ear to this? who will hearken and hear for the time to come?

^24Who gave Jacob for a spoil, and Israel to the robbers? did not the Lord, he against whom we have sinned? for they would not walk in his ways, neither were they obedient unto his law.

^25Therefore he hath poured upon him the fury of his anger, and the strength of battle: and it hath set him on fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him, yet he laid it not to heart.

Isaiah 43

43^1But now thus saith the Lord that created thee, O Jacob, and he that formed thee, O Israel, Fear not: for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name; thou art mine.

^2When thou passest through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the rivers, they shall not overflow thee: when thou walkest through the fire, thou shalt not be burned; neither shall the flame kindle upon thee.

^3For I am the Lord thy God, the Holy One of Israel, thy Saviour: I gave Egypt for thy ransom, Ethiopia and Seba for thee.

^4Since thou wast precious in my sight, thou hast been honourable, and I have loved thee: therefore will I give men for thee, and people for thy life.

^5Fear not: for I am with thee: I will bring thy seed from the east, and gather thee from the west;

^6I will say to the north, Give up; and to the south, Keep not back: bring my sons from far, and my daughters from the ends of the earth;

^7Even every one that is called by my name: for I have created him for my glory, I have formed him; yea, I have made him.

^8Bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf that have ears.

^9Let all the nations be gathered together, and let the people be assembled: who among them can declare this, and shew us former things? let them bring forth their witnesses, that they may be justified: or let them hear, and say, It is truth.

^10Ye are my witnesses, saith the Lord, and my servant whom I have chosen: that ye may know and believe me, and understand that I am he: before me there was no God formed, neither shall there be after me.

^11I, even I, am the Lord; and beside me there is no saviour.

^12I have declared, and have saved, and I have shewed, when there was no strange god among you: therefore ye are my witnesses, saith the Lord, that I am God.

^13Yea, before the day was I am he; and there is none that can deliver out of my hand: I will work, and who shall let it?

^14Thus saith the Lord, your redeemer, the Holy One of Israel; For your sake I have sent to Babylon, and have brought down all their nobles, and the Chaldeans, whose cry is in the ships.

^15I am the Lord, your Holy One, the creator of Israel, your King.

^16Thus saith the Lord, which maketh a way in the sea, and a path in the mighty waters;

^17Which bringeth forth the chariot and horse, the army and the power; they shall lie down together, they shall not rise: they are extinct, they are quenched as tow.

^18Remember ye not the former things, neither consider the things of old.

^19Behold, I will do a new thing; now it shall spring forth; shall ye not know it? I will even make a way in the wilderness, and rivers in the desert.

^20The beast of the field shall honour me, the dragons and the owls: because I give waters in the wilderness, and rivers in the desert, to give drink to my people, my chosen.

^21This people have I formed for myself; they shall shew forth my praise.

^22But thou hast not called upon me, O Jacob; but thou hast been weary of me, O Israel.

^23Thou hast not brought me the small cattle of thy burnt offerings; neither hast thou honoured me with thy sacrifices. I have not caused thee to serve with an offering, nor wearied thee with incense.

^24Thou hast bought me no sweet cane with money, neither hast thou filled me with the fat of thy sacrifices: but thou hast made me to serve with thy sins, thou hast wearied me with thine iniquities.

^25I, even I, am he that blotteth out thy transgressions for mine own sake, and will not remember thy sins.

^26Put me in remembrance: let us plead together: declare thou, that thou mayest be justified.

^27Thy first father hath sinned, and thy teachers have transgressed against me.

^28Therefore I have profaned the princes of the sanctuary, and have given Jacob to the curse, and Israel to reproaches.

Isaiah 44

44^1Yet now hear, O Jacob my servant; and Israel, whom I have chosen:

^2Thus saith the Lord that made thee, and formed thee from the womb, which will help thee; Fear not, O Jacob, my servant; and thou, Jesurun, whom I have chosen.

^3For I will pour water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground: I will pour my spirit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine offspring:

^4And they shall spring up as among the grass, as willows by the water courses.

^5One shall say, I am the Lord’s; and another shall call himself by the name of Jacob; and another shall subscribe with his hand unto the Lord, and surname himself by the name of Israel.

^6Thus saith the Lord the King of Israel, and his redeemer the Lord of hosts; I am the first, and I am the last; and beside me there is no God.

^7And who, as I, shall call, and shall declare it, and set it in order for me, since I appointed the ancient people? and the things that are coming, and shall come, let them shew unto them.

^8Fear ye not, neither be afraid: have not I told thee from that time, and have declared it? ye are even my witnesses. Is there a God beside me? yea, there is no God; I know not any.

^9They that make a graven image are all of them vanity; and their delectable things shall not profit; and they are their own witnesses; they see not, nor know; that they may be ashamed.

^10Who hath formed a god, or molten a graven image that is profitable for nothing?

^11Behold, all his fellows shall be ashamed: and the workmen, they are of men: let them all be gathered together, let them stand up; yet they shall fear, and they shall be ashamed together.

^12The smith with the tongs both worketh in the coals, and fashioneth it with hammers, and worketh it with the strength of his arms: yea, he is hungry, and his strength faileth: he drinketh no water, and is faint.

^13The carpenter stretcheth out his rule; he marketh it out with a line; he fitteth it with planes, and he marketh it out with the compass, and maketh it after the figure of a man, according to the beauty of a man; that it may remain in the house.

^14He heweth him down cedars, and taketh the cypress and the oak, which he strengtheneth for himself among the trees of the forest: he planteth an ash, and the rain doth nourish it.

^15Then shall it be for a man to burn: for he will take thereof, and warm himself; yea, he kindleth it, and baketh bread; yea, he maketh a god, and worshippeth it; he maketh it a graven image, and falleth down thereto.

^16He burneth part thereof in the fire; with part thereof he eateth flesh; he roasteth roast, and is satisfied: yea, he warmeth himself, and saith, Aha, I am warm, I have seen the fire:

^17And the residue thereof he maketh a god, even his graven image: he falleth down unto it, and worshippeth it, and prayeth unto it, and saith, Deliver me; for thou art my god.

^18They have not known nor understood: for he hath shut their eyes, that they cannot see; and their hearts, that they cannot understand.

^19And none considereth in his heart, neither is there knowledge nor understanding to say, I have burned part of it in the fire; yea, also I have baked bread upon the coals thereof; I have roasted flesh, and eaten it: and shall I make the residue thereof an abomination? shall I fall down to the stock of a tree?

^20He feedeth on ashes: a deceived heart hath turned him aside, that he cannot deliver his soul, nor say, Is there not a lie in my right hand?

^21Remember these, O Jacob and Israel; for thou art my servant: I have formed thee; thou art my servant: O Israel, thou shalt not be forgotten of me.

^22I have blotted out, as a thick cloud, thy transgressions, and, as a cloud, thy sins: return unto me; for I have redeemed thee.

^23Sing, O ye heavens; for the Lord hath done it: shout, ye lower parts of the earth: break forth into singing, ye mountains, O forest, and every tree therein: for the Lord hath redeemed Jacob, and glorified himself in Israel.

^24Thus saith the Lord, thy redeemer, and he that formed thee from the womb, I am the Lord that maketh all things; that stretcheth forth the heavens alone; that spreadeth abroad the earth by myself;

^25That frustrateth the tokens of the liars, and maketh diviners mad; that turneth wise men backward, and maketh their knowledge foolish;

^26That confirmeth the word of his servant, and performeth the counsel of his messengers; that saith to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be inhabited; and to the cities of Judah, Ye shall be built, and I will raise up the decayed places thereof:

^27That saith to the deep, Be dry, and I will dry up thy rivers:

^28That saith of Cyrus, He is my shepherd, and shall perform all my pleasure: even saying to Jerusalem, Thou shalt be built; and to the temple, Thy foundation shall be laid.

Isaiah 45

45^1Thus saith the Lord to his anointed, to Cyrus, whose right hand I have holden, to subdue nations before him; and I will loose the loins of kings, to open before him the two leaved gates; and the gates shall not be shut;

^2I will go before thee, and make the crooked places straight: I will break in pieces the gates of brass, and cut in sunder the bars of iron:

^3And I will give thee the treasures of darkness, and hidden riches of secret places, that thou mayest know that I, the Lord, which call thee by thy name, am the God of Israel.

^4For Jacob my servant’s sake, and Israel mine elect, I have even called thee by thy name: I have surnamed thee, though thou hast not known me.

^5I am the Lord, and there is none else, there is no God beside me: I girded thee, though thou hast not known me:

^6That they may know from the rising of the sun, and from the west, that there is none beside me. I am the Lord, and there is none else.

^7I form the light, and create darkness: I make peace, and create evil: I the Lord do all these things.

^8Drop down, ye heavens, from above, and let the skies pour down righteousness: let the earth open, and let them bring forth salvation, and let righteousness spring up together; I the Lord have created it.

^9Woe unto him that striveth with his Maker! Let the potsherd strive with the potsherds of the earth. Shall the clay say to him that fashioneth it, What makest thou? or thy work, He hath no hands?

^10Woe unto him that saith unto his father, What begettest thou? or to the woman, What hast thou brought forth?

^11Thus saith the Lord, the Holy One of Israel, and his Maker, Ask me of things to come concerning my sons, and concerning the work of my hands command ye me.

^12I have made the earth, and created man upon it: I, even my hands, have stretched out the heavens, and all their host have I commanded.

^13I have raised him up in righteousness, and I will direct all his ways: he shall build my city, and he shall let go my captives, not for price nor reward, saith the Lord of hosts.

^14Thus saith the Lord, The labour of Egypt, and merchandise of Ethiopia and of the Sabeans, men of stature, shall come over unto thee, and they shall be thine: they shall come after thee; in chains they shall come over, and they shall fall down unto thee, they shall make supplication unto thee, saying, Surely God is in thee; and there is none else, there is no God.

^15Verily thou art a God that hidest thyself, O God of Israel, the Saviour.

^16They shall be ashamed, and also confounded, all of them: they shall go to confusion together that are makers of idols.

^17But Israel shall be saved in the Lord with an everlasting salvation: ye shall not be ashamed nor confounded world without end.

^18For thus saith the Lord that created the heavens; God himself that formed the earth and made it; he hath established it, he created it not in vain, he formed it to be inhabited: I am the Lord; and there is none else.

^19I have not spoken in secret, in a dark place of the earth: I said not unto the seed of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain: I the Lord speak righteousness, I declare things that are right.

^20Assemble yourselves and come; draw near together, ye that are escaped of the nations: they have no knowledge that set up the wood of their graven image, and pray unto a god that cannot save.

^21Tell ye, and bring them near; yea, let them take counsel together: who hath declared this from ancient time? who hath told it from that time? have not I the Lord? and there is no God else beside me; a just God and a Saviour; there is none beside me.

^22Look unto me, and be ye saved, all the ends of the earth: for I am God, and there is none else.

^23I have sworn by myself, the word is gone out of my mouth in righteousness, and shall not return, That unto me every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear.

^24Surely, shall one say, in the Lord have I righteousness and strength: even to him shall men come; and all that are incensed against him shall be ashamed.

^25In the Lord shall all the seed of Israel be justified, and shall glory.

Isaiah 46

46^1Bel boweth down, Nebo stoopeth, their idols were upon the beasts, and upon the cattle: your carriages were heavy loaden; they are a burden to the weary beast.

^2They stoop, they bow down together; they could not deliver the burden, but themselves are gone into captivity.

^3Hearken unto me, O house of Jacob, and all the remnant of the house of Israel, which are borne by me from the belly, which are carried from the womb:

^4And even to your old age I am he; and even to hoar hairs will I carry you: I have made, and I will bear; even I will carry, and will deliver you.

^5To whom will ye liken me, and make me equal, and compare me, that we may be like?

^6They lavish gold out of the bag, and weigh silver in the balance, and hire a goldsmith; and he maketh it a god: they fall down, yea, they worship.

^7They bear him upon the shoulder, they carry him, and set him in his place, and he standeth; from his place shall he not remove: yea, one shall cry unto him, yet can he not answer, nor save him out of his trouble.

^8Remember this, and shew yourselves men: bring it again to mind, O ye transgressors.

^9Remember the former things of old: for I am God, and there is none else; I am God, and there is none like me,

^10Declaring the end from the beginning, and from ancient times the things that are not yet done, saying, My counsel shall stand, and I will do all my pleasure:

^11Calling a ravenous bird from the east, the man that executeth my counsel from a far country: yea, I have spoken it, I will also bring it to pass; I have purposed it, I will also do it.

^12Hearken unto me, ye stouthearted, that are far from righteousness:

^13I bring near my righteousness; it shall not be far off, and my salvation shall not tarry: and I will place salvation in Zion for Israel my glory.

Isaiah 47

47^1Come down, and sit in the dust, O virgin daughter of Babylon, sit on the ground: there is no throne, O daughter of the Chaldeans: for thou shalt no more be called tender and delicate.

^2Take the millstones, and grind meal: uncover thy locks, make bare the leg, uncover the thigh, pass over the rivers.

^3Thy nakedness shall be uncovered, yea, thy shame shall be seen: I will take vengeance, and I will not meet thee as a man.

^4As for our redeemer, the Lord of hosts is his name, the Holy One of Israel.

^5Sit thou silent, and get thee into darkness, O daughter of the Chaldeans: for thou shalt no more be called, The lady of kingdoms.

^6I was wroth with my people, I have polluted mine inheritance, and given them into thine hand: thou didst shew them no mercy; upon the ancient hast thou very heavily laid thy yoke.

^7And thou saidst, I shall be a lady for ever: so that thou didst not lay these things to thy heart, neither didst remember the latter end of it.

^8Therefore hear now this, thou that art given to pleasures, that dwellest carelessly, that sayest in thine heart, I am, and none else beside me; I shall not sit as a widow, neither shall I know the loss of children:

^9But these two things shall come to thee in a moment in one day, the loss of children, and widowhood: they shall come upon thee in their perfection for the multitude of thy sorceries, and for the great abundance of thine enchantments.

^10For thou hast trusted in thy wickedness: thou hast said, None seeth me. Thy wisdom and thy knowledge, it hath perverted thee; and thou hast said in thine heart, I am, and none else beside me.

^11Therefore shall evil come upon thee; thou shalt not know from whence it riseth: and mischief shall fall upon thee; thou shalt not be able to put it off: and desolation shall come upon thee suddenly, which thou shalt not know.

^12Stand now with thine enchantments, and with the multitude of thy sorceries, wherein thou hast laboured from thy youth; if so be thou shalt be able to profit, if so be thou mayest prevail.

^13Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy counsels. Let now the astrologers, the stargazers, the monthly prognosticators, stand up, and save thee from these things that shall come upon thee.

^14Behold, they shall be as stubble; the fire shall burn them; they shall not deliver themselves from the power of the flame: there shall not be a coal to warm at, nor fire to sit before it.

^15Thus shall they be unto thee with whom thou hast laboured, even thy merchants, from thy youth: they shall wander every one to his quarter; none shall save thee.

Isaiah 48

48^1Hear ye this, O house of Jacob, which are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah, which swear by the name of the Lord, and make mention of the God of Israel, but not in truth, nor in righteousness.

^2For they call themselves of the holy city, and stay themselves upon the God of Israel; The Lord of hosts is his name.

^3I have declared the former things from the beginning; and they went forth out of my mouth, and I shewed them; I did them suddenly, and they came to pass.

^4Because I knew that thou art obstinate, and thy neck is an iron sinew, and thy brow brass;

^5I have even from the beginning declared it to thee; before it came to pass I shewed it thee: lest thou shouldest say, Mine idol hath done them, and my graven image, and my molten image, hath commanded them.

^6Thou hast heard, see all this; and will not ye declare it? I have shewed thee new things from this time, even hidden things, and thou didst not know them.

^7They are created now, and not from the beginning; even before the day when thou heardest them not; lest thou shouldest say, Behold, I knew them.

^8Yea, thou heardest not; yea, thou knewest not; yea, from that time that thine ear was not opened: for I knew that thou wouldest deal very treacherously, and wast called a transgressor from the womb.

^9For my name’s sake will I defer mine anger, and for my praise will I refrain for thee, that I cut thee not off.

^10Behold, I have refined thee, but not with silver; I have chosen thee in the furnace of affliction.

^11For mine own sake, even for mine own sake, will I do it: for how should my name be polluted? and I will not give my glory unto another.

^12Hearken unto me, O Jacob and Israel, my called; I am he; I am the first, I also am the last.

^13Mine hand also hath laid the foundation of the earth, and my right hand hath spanned the heavens: when I call unto them, they stand up together.

^14All ye, assemble yourselves, and hear; which among them hath declared these things? The Lord hath loved him: he will do his pleasure on Babylon, and his arm shall be on the Chaldeans.

^15I, even I, have spoken; yea, I have called him: I have brought him, and he shall make his way prosperous.

^16Come ye near unto me, hear ye this; I have not spoken in secret from the beginning; from the time that it was, there am I: and now the Lord God, and his Spirit, hath sent me.

^17Thus saith the Lord, thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel; I am the Lord thy God which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way that thou shouldest go.

^18O that thou hadst hearkened to my commandments! then had thy peace been as a river, and thy righteousness as the waves of the sea:

^19Thy seed also had been as the sand, and the offspring of thy bowels like the gravel thereof; his name should not have been cut off nor destroyed from before me.

^20Go ye forth of Babylon, flee ye from the Chaldeans, with a voice of singing declare ye, tell this, utter it even to the end of the earth; say ye, The Lord hath redeemed his servant Jacob.

^21And they thirsted not when he led them through the deserts: he caused the waters to flow out of the rock for them: he clave the rock also, and the waters gushed out.

^22There is no peace, saith the Lord, unto the wicked.

Isaiah 49

49^1Listen, O isles, unto me; and hearken, ye people, from far; The Lord hath called me from the womb; from the bowels of my mother hath he made mention of my name.

^2And he hath made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand hath he hid me, and made me a polished shaft; in his quiver hath he hid me;

^3And said unto me, Thou art my servant, O Israel, in whom I will be glorified.

^4Then I said, I have laboured in vain, I have spent my strength for nought, and in vain: yet surely my judgment is with the Lord, and my work with my God.

^5And now, saith the Lord that formed me from the womb to be his servant, to bring Jacob again to him, Though Israel be not gathered, yet shall I be glorious in the eyes of the Lord, and my God shall be my strength.

^6And he said, It is a light thing that thou shouldest be my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob, and to restore the preserved of Israel: I will also give thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayest be my salvation unto the end of the earth.

^7Thus saith the Lord, the Redeemer of Israel, and his Holy One, to him whom man despiseth, to him whom the nation abhorreth, to a servant of rulers, Kings shall see and arise, princes also shall worship, because of the Lord that is faithful, and the Holy One of Israel, and he shall choose thee.

^8Thus saith the Lord, In an acceptable time have I heard thee, and in a day of salvation have I helped thee: and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, to establish the earth, to cause to inherit the desolate heritages;

^9That thou mayest say to the prisoners, Go forth; to them that are in darkness, Shew yourselves. They shall feed in the ways, and their pastures shall be in all high places.

^10They shall not hunger nor thirst; neither shall the heat nor sun smite them: for he that hath mercy on them shall lead them, even by the springs of water shall he guide them.

^11And I will make all my mountains a way, and my highways shall be exalted.

^12Behold, these shall come from far: and, lo, these from the north and from the west; and these from the land of Sinim.

^13Sing, O heavens; and be joyful, O earth; and break forth into singing, O mountains: for the Lord hath comforted his people, and will have mercy upon his afflicted.

^14But Zion said, The Lord hath forsaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me.

^15Can a woman forget her sucking child, that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb? yea, they may forget, yet will I not forget thee.

^16Behold, I have graven thee upon the palms of my hands; thy walls are continually before me.

^17Thy children shall make haste; thy destroyers and they that made thee waste shall go forth of thee.

^18Lift up thine eyes round about, and behold: all these gather themselves together, and come to thee. As I live, saith the Lord, thou shalt surely clothe thee with them all, as with an ornament, and bind them on thee, as a bride doeth.

^19For thy waste and thy desolate places, and the land of thy destruction, shall even now be too narrow by reason of the inhabitants, and they that swallowed thee up shall be far away.

^20The children which thou shalt have, after thou hast lost the other, shall say again in thine ears, The place is too strait for me: give place to me that I may dwell.

^21Then shalt thou say in thine heart, Who hath begotten me these, seeing I have lost my children, and am desolate, a captive, and removing to and fro? and who hath brought up these? Behold, I was left alone; these, where had they been?

^22Thus saith the Lord God, Behold, I will lift up mine hand to the Gentiles, and set up my standard to the people: and they shall bring thy sons in their arms, and thy daughters shall be carried upon their shoulders.

^23And kings shall be thy nursing fathers, and their queens thy nursing mothers: they shall bow down to thee with their face toward the earth, and lick up the dust of thy feet; and thou shalt know that I am the Lord: for they shall not be ashamed that wait for me.

^24Shall the prey be taken from the mighty, or the lawful captive delivered?

^25But thus saith the Lord, Even the captives of the mighty shall be taken away, and the prey of the terrible shall be delivered: for I will contend with him that contendeth with thee, and I will save thy children.

^26And I will feed them that oppress thee with their own flesh; and they shall be drunken with their own blood, as with sweet wine: and all flesh shall know that I the Lord am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the mighty One of Jacob.

Isaiah 50

50^1Thus saith the Lord, Where is the bill of your mother’s divorcement, whom I have put away? or which of my creditors is it to whom I have sold you? Behold, for your iniquities have ye sold yourselves, and for your transgressions is your mother put away.

^2Wherefore, when I came, was there no man? when I called, was there none to answer? Is my hand shortened at all, that it cannot redeem? or have I no power to deliver? behold, at my rebuke I dry up the sea, I make the rivers a wilderness: their fish stinketh, because there is no water, and dieth for thirst.

^3I clothe the heavens with blackness, and I make sackcloth their covering.

^4The Lord God hath given me the tongue of the learned, that I should know how to speak a word in season to him that is weary: he wakeneth morning by morning, he wakeneth mine ear to hear as the learned.

^5The Lord God hath opened mine ear, and I was not rebellious, neither turned away back.

^6I gave my back to the smiters, and my cheeks to them that plucked off the hair: I hid not my face from shame and spitting.

^7For the Lord God will help me; therefore shall I not be confounded: therefore have I set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall not be ashamed.

^8He is near that justifieth me; who will contend with me? let us stand together: who is mine adversary? let him come near to me.

^9Behold, the Lord God will help me; who is he that shall condemn me? lo, they all shall wax old as a garment; the moth shall eat them up.

^10Who is among you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voice of his servant, that walketh in darkness, and hath no light? let him trust in the name of the Lord, and stay upon his God.

^11Behold, all ye that kindle a fire, that compass yourselves about with sparks: walk in the light of your fire, and in the sparks that ye have kindled. This shall ye have of mine hand; ye shall lie down in sorrow.

Isaiah 51

51^1Hearken to me, ye that follow after righteousness, ye that seek the Lord: look unto the rock whence ye are hewn, and to the hole of the pit whence ye are digged.

^2Look unto Abraham your father, and unto Sarah that bare you: for I called him alone, and blessed him, and increased him.

^3For the Lord shall comfort Zion: he will comfort all her waste places; and he will make her wilderness like Eden, and her desert like the garden of the Lord; joy and gladness shall be found therein, thanksgiving, and the voice of melody.

^4Hearken unto me, my people; and give ear unto me, O my nation: for a law shall proceed from me, and I will make my judgment to rest for a light of the people.

^5My righteousness is near; my salvation is gone forth, and mine arms shall judge the people; the isles shall wait upon me, and on mine arm shall they trust.

^6Lift up your eyes to the heavens, and look upon the earth beneath: for the heavens shall vanish away like smoke, and the earth shall wax old like a garment, and they that dwell therein shall die in like manner: but my salvation shall be for ever, and my righteousness shall not be abolished.

^7Hearken unto me, ye that know righteousness, the people in whose heart is my law; fear ye not the reproach of men, neither be ye afraid of their revilings.

^8For the moth shall eat them up like a garment, and the worm shall eat them like wool: but my righteousness shall be for ever, and my salvation from generation to generation.

^9Awake, awake, put on strength, O arm of the Lord; awake, as in the ancient days, in the generations of old. Art thou not it that hath cut Rahab, and wounded the dragon?

^10Art thou not it which hath dried the sea, the waters of the great deep; that hath made the depths of the sea a way for the ransomed to pass over?

^11Therefore the redeemed of the Lord shall return, and come with singing unto Zion; and everlasting joy shall be upon their head: they shall obtain gladness and joy; and sorrow and mourning shall flee away.

^12I, even I, am he that comforteth you: who art thou, that thou shouldest be afraid of a man that shall die, and of the son of man which shall be made as grass;

^13And forgettest the Lord thy maker, that hath stretched forth the heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth; and hast feared continually every day because of the fury of the oppressor, as if he were ready to destroy? and where is the fury of the oppressor?

^14The captive exile hasteneth that he may be loosed, and that he should not die in the pit, nor that his bread should fail.

^15But I am the Lord thy God, that divided the sea, whose waves roared: The Lord of hosts is his name.

^16And I have put my words in thy mouth, and I have covered thee in the shadow of mine hand, that I may plant the heavens, and lay the foundations of the earth, and say unto Zion, Thou art my people.

^17Awake, awake, stand up, O Jerusalem, which hast drunk at the hand of the Lord the cup of his fury; thou hast drunken the dregs of the cup of trembling, and wrung them out.

^18There is none to guide her among all the sons whom she hath brought forth; neither is there any that taketh her by the hand of all the sons that she hath brought up.

^19These two things are come unto thee; who shall be sorry for thee? desolation, and destruction, and the famine, and the sword: by whom shall I comfort thee?

^20Thy sons have fainted, they lie at the head of all the streets, as a wild bull in a net: they are full of the fury of the Lord, the rebuke of thy God.

^21Therefore hear now this, thou afflicted, and drunken, but not with wine:

^22Thus saith thy Lord the Lord, and thy God that pleadeth the cause of his people, Behold, I have taken out of thine hand the cup of trembling, even the dregs of the cup of my fury; thou shalt no more drink it again:

^23But I will put it into the hand of them that afflict thee; which have said to thy soul, Bow down, that we may go over: and thou hast laid thy body as the ground, and as the street, to them that went over.

Isaiah 52

52^1Awake, awake; put on thy strength, O Zion; put on thy beautiful garments, O Jerusalem, the holy city: for henceforth there shall no more come into thee the uncircumcised and the unclean.

^2Shake thyself from the dust; arise, and sit down, O Jerusalem: loose thyself from the bands of thy neck, O captive daughter of Zion.

^3For thus saith the Lord, Ye have sold yourselves for nought; and ye shall be redeemed without money.

^4For thus saith the Lord God, My people went down aforetime into Egypt to sojourn there; and the Assyrian oppressed them without cause.

^5Now therefore, what have I here, saith the Lord, that my people is taken away for nought? they that rule over them make them to howl, saith the Lord; and my name continually every day is blasphemed.

^6Therefore my people shall know my name: therefore they shall know in that day that I am he that doth speak: behold, it is I.

^7How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace; that bringeth good tidings of good, that publisheth salvation; that saith unto Zion, Thy God reigneth!

^8Thy watchmen shall lift up the voice; with the voice together shall they sing: for they shall see eye to eye, when the Lord shall bring again Zion.

^9Break forth into joy, sing together, ye waste places of Jerusalem: for the Lord hath comforted his people, he hath redeemed Jerusalem.

^10The Lord hath made bare his holy arm in the eyes of all the nations; and all the ends of the earth shall see the salvation of our God.

^11Depart ye, depart ye, go ye out from thence, touch no unclean thing; go ye out of the midst of her; be ye clean, that bear the vessels of the Lord.

^12For ye shall not go out with haste, nor go by flight: for the Lord will go before you; and the God of Israel will be your rereward.

^13Behold, my servant shall deal prudently, he shall be exalted and extolled, and be very high.

^14As many were astonied at thee; his visage was so marred more than any man, and his form more than the sons of men:

^15So shall he sprinkle many nations; the kings shall shut their mouths at him: for that which had not been told them shall they see; and that which they had not heard shall they consider.

Isaiah 53

53^1Who hath believed our report? and to whom is the arm of the Lord revealed?

^2For he shall grow up before him as a tender plant, and as a root out of a dry ground: he hath no form nor comeliness; and when we shall see him, there is no beauty that we should desire him.

^3He is despised and rejected of men; a man of sorrows, and acquainted with grief: and we hid as it were our faces from him; he was despised, and we esteemed him not.

^4Surely he hath borne our griefs, and carried our sorrows: yet we did esteem him stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted.

^5But he was wounded for our transgressions, he was bruised for our iniquities: the chastisement of our peace was upon him; and with his stripes we are healed.

^6All we like sheep have gone astray; we have turned every one to his own way; and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all.

^7He was oppressed, and he was afflicted, yet he opened not his mouth: he is brought as a lamb to the slaughter, and as a sheep before her shearers is dumb, so he openeth not his mouth.

^8He was taken from prison and from judgment: and who shall declare his generation? for he was cut off out of the land of the living: for the transgression of my people was he stricken.

^9And he made his grave with the wicked, and with the rich in his death; because he had done no violence, neither was any deceit in his mouth.

^10Yet it pleased the Lord to bruise him; he hath put him to grief: when thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin, he shall see his seed, he shall prolong his days, and the pleasure of the Lord shall prosper in his hand.

^11He shall see of the travail of his soul, and shall be satisfied: by his knowledge shall my righteous servant justify many; for he shall bear their iniquities.

^12Therefore will I divide him a portion with the great, and he shall divide the spoil with the strong; because he hath poured out his soul unto death: and he was numbered with the transgressors; and he bare the sin of many, and made intercession for the transgressors.

Isaiah 54

54^1Sing, O barren, thou that didst not bear; break forth into singing, and cry aloud, thou that didst not travail with child: for more are the children of the desolate than the children of the married wife, saith the Lord.

^2Enlarge the place of thy tent, and let them stretch forth the curtains of thine habitations: spare not, lengthen thy cords, and strengthen thy stakes;

^3For thou shalt break forth on the right hand and on the left; and thy seed shall inherit the Gentiles, and make the desolate cities to be inhabited.

^4Fear not; for thou shalt not be ashamed: neither be thou confounded; for thou shalt not be put to shame: for thou shalt forget the shame of thy youth, and shalt not remember the reproach of thy widowhood any more.

^5For thy Maker is thine husband; the Lord of hosts is his name; and thy Redeemer the Holy One of Israel; The God of the whole earth shall he be called.

^6For the Lord hath called thee as a woman forsaken and grieved in spirit, and a wife of youth, when thou wast refused, saith thy God.

^7For a small moment have I forsaken thee; but with great mercies will I gather thee.

^8In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment; but with everlasting kindness will I have mercy on thee, saith the Lord thy Redeemer.

^9For this is as the waters of Noah unto me: for as I have sworn that the waters of Noah should no more go over the earth; so have I sworn that I would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee.

^10For the mountains shall depart, and the hills be removed; but my kindness shall not depart from thee, neither shall the covenant of my peace be removed, saith the Lord that hath mercy on thee.

^11O thou afflicted, tossed with tempest, and not comforted, behold, I will lay thy stones with fair colours, and lay thy foundations with sapphires.

^12And I will make thy windows of agates, and thy gates of carbuncles, and all thy borders of pleasant stones.

^13And all thy children shall be taught of the Lord; and great shall be the peace of thy children.

^14In righteousness shalt thou be established: thou shalt be far from oppression; for thou shalt not fear: and from terror; for it shall not come near thee.

^15Behold, they shall surely gather together, but not by me: whosoever shall gather together against thee shall fall for thy sake.

^16Behold, I have created the smith that bloweth the coals in the fire, and that bringeth forth an instrument for his work; and I have created the waster to destroy.

^17No weapon that is formed against thee shall prosper; and every tongue that shall rise against thee in judgment thou shalt condemn. This is the heritage of the servants of the Lord, and their righteousness is of me, saith the Lord.

Isaiah 55

55^1Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money; come ye, buy, and eat; yea, come, buy wine and milk without money and without price.

^2Wherefore do ye spend money for that which is not bread? and your labour for that which satisfieth not? hearken diligently unto me, and eat ye that which is good, and let your soul delight itself in fatness.

^3Incline your ear, and come unto me: hear, and your soul shall live; and I will make an everlasting covenant with you, even the sure mercies of David.

^4Behold, I have given him for a witness to the people, a leader and commander to the people.

^5Behold, thou shalt call a nation that thou knowest not, and nations that knew not thee shall run unto thee because of the Lord thy God, and for the Holy One of Israel; for he hath glorified thee.

^6Seek ye the Lord while he may be found, call ye upon him while he is near:

^7Let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts: and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.

^8For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways, saith the Lord.

^9For as the heavens are higher than the earth, so are my ways higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts.

^10For as the rain cometh down, and the snow from heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud, that it may give seed to the sower, and bread to the eater:

^11So shall my word be that goeth forth out of my mouth: it shall not return unto me void, but it shall accomplish that which I please, and it shall prosper in the thing whereto I sent it.

^12For ye shall go out with joy, and be led forth with peace: the mountains and the hills shall break forth before you into singing, and all the trees of the field shall clap their hands.

^13Instead of the thorn shall come up the fir tree, and instead of the brier shall come up the myrtle tree: and it shall be to the Lord for a name, for an everlasting sign that shall not be cut off.

Isaiah 56

56^1Thus saith the Lord, Keep ye judgment, and do justice: for my salvation is near to come, and my righteousness to be revealed.

^2Blessed is the man that doeth this, and the son of man that layeth hold on it; that keepeth the sabbath from polluting it, and keepeth his hand from doing any evil.

^3Neither let the son of the stranger, that hath joined himself to the Lord, speak, saying, The Lord hath utterly separated me from his people: neither let the eunuch say, Behold, I am a dry tree.

^4For thus saith the Lord unto the eunuchs that keep my sabbaths, and choose the things that please me, and take hold of my covenant;

^5Even unto them will I give in mine house and within my walls a place and a name better than of sons and of daughters: I will give them an everlasting name, that shall not be cut off.

^6Also the sons of the stranger, that join themselves to the Lord, to serve him, and to love the name of the Lord, to be his servants, every one that keepeth the sabbath from polluting it, and taketh hold of my covenant;

^7Even them will I bring to my holy mountain, and make them joyful in my house of prayer: their burnt offerings and their sacrifices shall be accepted upon mine altar; for mine house shall be called an house of prayer for all people.

^8The Lord God, which gathereth the outcasts of Israel saith, Yet will I gather others to him, beside those that are gathered unto him.

^9All ye beasts of the field, come to devour, yea, all ye beasts in the forest.

^10His watchmen are blind: they are all ignorant, they are all dumb dogs, they cannot bark; sleeping, lying down, loving to slumber.

^11Yea, they are greedy dogs which can never have enough, and they are shepherds that cannot understand: they all look to their own way, every one for his gain, from his quarter.

^12Come ye, say they, I will fetch wine, and we will fill ourselves with strong drink; and to morrow shall be as this day, and much more abundant.

Isaiah 57

57^1The righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart: and merciful men are taken away, none considering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.

^2He shall enter into peace: they shall rest in their beds, each one walking in his uprightness.

^3But draw near hither, ye sons of the sorceress, the seed of the adulterer and the whore.

^4Against whom do ye sport yourselves? against whom make ye a wide mouth, and draw out the tongue? are ye not children of transgression, a seed of falsehood.

^5Enflaming yourselves with idols under every green tree, slaying the children in the valleys under the clifts of the rocks?

^6Among the smooth stones of the stream is thy portion; they, they are thy lot: even to them hast thou poured a drink offering, thou hast offered a meat offering. Should I receive comfort in these?

^7Upon a lofty and high mountain hast thou set thy bed: even thither wentest thou up to offer sacrifice.

^8Behind the doors also and the posts hast thou set up thy remembrance: for thou hast discovered thyself to another than me, and art gone up; thou hast enlarged thy bed, and made thee a covenant with them; thou lovedst their bed where thou sawest it.

^9And thou wentest to the king with ointment, and didst increase thy perfumes, and didst send thy messengers far off, and didst debase thyself even unto hell.

^10Thou art wearied in the greatness of thy way; yet saidst thou not, There is no hope: thou hast found the life of thine hand; therefore thou wast not grieved.

^11And of whom hast thou been afraid or feared, that thou hast lied, and hast not remembered me, nor laid it to thy heart? have not I held my peace even of old, and thou fearest me not?

^12I will declare thy righteousness, and thy works; for they shall not profit thee.

^13When thou criest, let thy companies deliver thee; but the wind shall carry them all away; vanity shall take them: but he that putteth his trust in me shall possess the land, and shall inherit my holy mountain;

^14And shall say, Cast ye up, cast ye up, prepare the way, take up the stumblingblock out of the way of my people.

^15For thus saith the high and lofty One that inhabiteth eternity, whose name is Holy; I dwell in the high and holy place, with him also that is of a contrite and humble spirit, to revive the spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.

^16For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth: for the spirit should fail before me, and the souls which I have made.

^17For the iniquity of his covetousness was I wroth, and smote him: I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on frowardly in the way of his heart.

^18I have seen his ways, and will heal him: I will lead him also, and restore comforts unto him and to his mourners.

^19I create the fruit of the lips; Peace, peace to him that is far off, and to him that is near, saith the Lord; and I will heal him.

^20But the wicked are like the troubled sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast up mire and dirt.

^21There is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked.

Isaiah 58

58^1Cry aloud, spare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and shew my people their transgression, and the house of Jacob their sins.

^2Yet they seek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a nation that did righteousness, and forsook not the ordinance of their God: they ask of me the ordinances of justice; they take delight in approaching to God.

^3Wherefore have we fasted, say they, and thou seest not? wherefore have we afflicted our soul, and thou takest no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your fast ye find pleasure, and exact all your labours.

^4Behold, ye fast for strife and debate, and to smite with the fist of wickedness: ye shall not fast as ye do this day, to make your voice to be heard on high.

^5Is it such a fast that I have chosen? a day for a man to afflict his soul? is it to bow down his head as a bulrush, and to spread sackcloth and ashes under him? wilt thou call this a fast, and an acceptable day to the Lord?

^6Is not this the fast that I have chosen? to loose the bands of wickedness, to undo the heavy burdens, and to let the oppressed go free, and that ye break every yoke?

^7Is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are cast out to thy house? when thou seest the naked, that thou cover him; and that thou hide not thyself from thine own flesh?

^8Then shall thy light break forth as the morning, and thine health shall spring forth speedily: and thy righteousness shall go before thee; the glory of the Lord shall be thy rereward.

^9Then shalt thou call, and the Lord shall answer; thou shalt cry, and he shall say, Here I am. If thou take away from the midst of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger, and speaking vanity;

^10And if thou draw out thy soul to the hungry, and satisfy the afflicted soul; then shall thy light rise in obscurity, and thy darkness be as the noon day:

^11And the Lord shall guide thee continually, and satisfy thy soul in drought, and make fat thy bones: and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a spring of water, whose waters fail not.

^12And they that shall be of thee shall build the old waste places: thou shalt raise up the foundations of many generations; and thou shalt be called, The repairer of the breach, The restorer of paths to dwell in.

^13If thou turn away thy foot from the sabbath, from doing thy pleasure on my holy day; and call the sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord, honourable; and shalt honour him, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleasure, nor speaking thine own words:

^14Then shalt thou delight thyself in the Lord; and I will cause thee to ride upon the high places of the earth, and feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father: for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.

Isaiah 59

59^1Behold, the Lord’s hand is not shortened, that it cannot save; neither his ear heavy, that it cannot hear:

^2But your iniquities have separated between you and your God, and your sins have hid his face from you, that he will not hear.

^3For your hands are defiled with blood, and your fingers with iniquity; your lips have spoken lies, your tongue hath muttered perverseness.

^4None calleth for justice, nor any pleadeth for truth: they trust in vanity, and speak lies; they conceive mischief, and bring forth iniquity.

^5They hatch cockatrice’ eggs, and weave the spider’s web: he that eateth of their eggs dieth, and that which is crushed breaketh out into a viper.

^6Their webs shall not become garments, neither shall they cover themselves with their works: their works are works of iniquity, and the act of violence is in their hands.

^7Their feet run to evil, and they make haste to shed innocent blood: their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity; wasting and destruction are in their paths.

^8The way of peace they know not; and there is no judgment in their goings: they have made them crooked paths: whosoever goeth therein shall not know peace.

^9Therefore is judgment far from us, neither doth justice overtake us: we wait for light, but behold obscurity; for brightness, but we walk in darkness.

^10We grope for the wall like the blind, and we grope as if we had no eyes: we stumble at noon day as in the night; we are in desolate places as dead men.

^11We roar all like bears, and mourn sore like doves: we look for judgment, but there is none; for salvation, but it is far off from us.

^12For our transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our sins testify against us: for our transgressions are with us; and as for our iniquities, we know them;

^13In transgressing and lying against the Lord, and departing away from our God, speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the heart words of falsehood.

^14And judgment is turned away backward, and justice standeth afar off: for truth is fallen in the street, and equity cannot enter.

^15Yea, truth faileth; and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a prey: and the Lord saw it, and it displeased him that there was no judgment.

^16And he saw that there was no man, and wondered that there was no intercessor: therefore his arm brought salvation unto him; and his righteousness, it sustained him.

^17For he put on righteousness as a breastplate, and an helmet of salvation upon his head; and he put on the garments of vengeance for clothing, and was clad with zeal as a cloak.

^18According to their deeds, accordingly he will repay, fury to his adversaries, recompence to his enemies; to the islands he will repay recompence.

^19So shall they fear the name of the Lord from the west, and his glory from the rising of the sun. When the enemy shall come in like a flood, the Spirit of the Lord shall lift up a standard against him.

^20And the Redeemer shall come to Zion, and unto them that turn from transgression in Jacob, saith the Lord.

^21As for me, this is my covenant with them, saith the Lord; My spirit that is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy seed, nor out of the mouth of thy seed’s seed, saith the Lord, from henceforth and for ever.

Isaiah 60

60^1Arise, shine; for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is risen upon thee.

^2For, behold, the darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the people: but the Lord shall arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen upon thee.

^3And the Gentiles shall come to thy light, and kings to the brightness of thy rising.

^4Lift up thine eyes round about, and see: all they gather themselves together, they come to thee: thy sons shall come from far, and thy daughters shall be nursed at thy side.

^5Then thou shalt see, and flow together, and thine heart shall fear, and be enlarged; because the abundance of the sea shall be converted unto thee, the forces of the Gentiles shall come unto thee.

^6The multitude of camels shall cover thee, the dromedaries of Midian and Ephah; all they from Sheba shall come: they shall bring gold and incense; and they shall shew forth the praises of the Lord.

^7All the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered together unto thee, the rams of Nebaioth shall minister unto thee: they shall come up with acceptance on mine altar, and I will glorify the house of my glory.

^8Who are these that fly as a cloud, and as the doves to their windows?

^9Surely the isles shall wait for me, and the ships of Tarshish first, to bring thy sons from far, their silver and their gold with them, unto the name of the Lord thy God, and to the Holy One of Israel, because he hath glorified thee.

^10And the sons of strangers shall build up thy walls, and their kings shall minister unto thee: for in my wrath I smote thee, but in my favour have I had mercy on thee.

^11Therefore thy gates shall be open continually; they shall not be shut day nor night; that men may bring unto thee the forces of the Gentiles, and that their kings may be brought.

^12For the nation and kingdom that will not serve thee shall perish; yea, those nations shall be utterly wasted.

^13The glory of Lebanon shall come unto thee, the fir tree, the pine tree, and the box together, to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I will make the place of my feet glorious.

^14The sons also of them that afflicted thee shall come bending unto thee; and all they that despised thee shall bow themselves down at the soles of thy feet; and they shall call thee; The city of the Lord, The Zion of the Holy One of Israel.

^15Whereas thou has been forsaken and hated, so that no man went through thee, I will make thee an eternal excellency, a joy of many generations.

^16Thou shalt also suck the milk of the Gentiles, and shalt suck the breast of kings: and thou shalt know that I the Lord am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the mighty One of Jacob.

^17For brass I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring silver, and for wood brass, and for stones iron: I will also make thy officers peace, and thine exactors righteousness.

^18Violence shall no more be heard in thy land, wasting nor destruction within thy borders; but thou shalt call thy walls Salvation, and thy gates Praise.

^19The sun shall be no more thy light by day; neither for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee: but the Lord shall be unto thee an everlasting light, and thy God thy glory.

^20Thy sun shall no more go down; neither shall thy moon withdraw itself: for the Lord shall be thine everlasting light, and the days of thy mourning shall be ended.

^21Thy people also shall be all righteous: they shall inherit the land for ever, the branch of my planting, the work of my hands, that I may be glorified.

^22A little one shall become a thousand, and a small one a strong nation: I the Lord will hasten it in his time.

Isaiah 61

61^1The Spirit of the Lord God is upon me; because the Lord hath anointed me to preach good tidings unto the meek; he hath sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the opening of the prison to them that are bound;

^2To proclaim the acceptable year of the Lord, and the day of vengeance of our God; to comfort all that mourn;

^3To appoint unto them that mourn in Zion, to give unto them beauty for ashes, the oil of joy for mourning, the garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness; that they might be called trees of righteousness, the planting of the Lord, that he might be glorified.

^4And they shall build the old wastes, they shall raise up the former desolations, and they shall repair the waste cities, the desolations of many generations.

^5And strangers shall stand and feed your flocks, and the sons of the alien shall be your plowmen and your vinedressers.

^6But ye shall be named the Priests of the Lord: men shall call you the Ministers of our God: ye shall eat the riches of the Gentiles, and in their glory shall ye boast yourselves.

^7For your shame ye shall have double; and for confusion they shall rejoice in their portion: therefore in their land they shall possess the double: everlasting joy shall be unto them.

^8For I the Lord love judgment, I hate robbery for burnt offering; and I will direct their work in truth, and I will make an everlasting covenant with them.

^9And their seed shall be known among the Gentiles, and their offspring among the people: all that see them shall acknowledge them, that they are the seed which the Lord hath blessed.

^10I will greatly rejoice in the Lord, my soul shall be joyful in my God; for he hath clothed me with the garments of salvation, he hath covered me with the robe of righteousness, as a bridegroom decketh himself with ornaments, and as a bride adorneth herself with her jewels.

^11For as the earth bringeth forth her bud, and as the garden causeth the things that are sown in it to spring forth; so the Lord God will cause righteousness and praise to spring forth before all the nations.

Isaiah 62

62^1For Zion’s sake will I not hold my peace, and for Jerusalem’s sake I will not rest, until the righteousness thereof go forth as brightness, and the salvation thereof as a lamp that burneth.

^2And the Gentiles shall see thy righteousness, and all kings thy glory: and thou shalt be called by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord shall name.

^3Thou shalt also be a crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royal diadem in the hand of thy God.

^4Thou shalt no more be termed Forsaken; neither shall thy land any more be termed Desolate: but thou shalt be called Hephzibah, and thy land Beulah: for the Lord delighteth in thee, and thy land shall be married.

^5For as a young man marrieth a virgin, so shall thy sons marry thee: and as the bridegroom rejoiceth over the bride, so shall thy God rejoice over thee.

^6I have set watchmen upon thy walls, O Jerusalem, which shall never hold their peace day nor night: ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not silence,

^7And give him no rest, till he establish, and till he make Jerusalem a praise in the earth.

^8The Lord hath sworn by his right hand, and by the arm of his strength, Surely I will no more give thy corn to be meat for thine enemies; and the sons of the stranger shall not drink thy wine, for the which thou hast laboured:

^9But they that have gathered it shall eat it, and praise the Lord; and they that have brought it together shall drink it in the courts of my holiness.

^10Go through, go through the gates; prepare ye the way of the people; cast up, cast up the highway; gather out the stones; lift up a standard for the people.

^11Behold, the Lord hath proclaimed unto the end of the world, Say ye to the daughter of Zion, Behold, thy salvation cometh; behold, his reward is with him, and his work before him.

^12And they shall call them, The holy people, The redeemed of the Lord: and thou shalt be called, Sought out, A city not forsaken.

Isaiah 63

63^1Who is this that cometh from Edom, with dyed garments from Bozrah? this that is glorious in his apparel, travelling in the greatness of his strength? I that speak in righteousness, mighty to save.

^2Wherefore art thou red in thine apparel, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the winefat?

^3I have trodden the winepress alone; and of the people there was none with me: for I will tread them in mine anger, and trample them in my fury; and their blood shall be sprinkled upon my garments, and I will stain all my raiment.

^4For the day of vengeance is in mine heart, and the year of my redeemed is come.

^5And I looked, and there was none to help; and I wondered that there was none to uphold: therefore mine own arm brought salvation unto me; and my fury, it upheld me.

^6And I will tread down the people in mine anger, and make them drunk in my fury, and I will bring down their strength to the earth.

^7I will mention the lovingkindnesses of the Lord, and the praises of the Lord, according to all that the Lord hath bestowed on us, and the great goodness toward the house of Israel, which he hath bestowed on them according to his mercies, and according to the multitude of his lovingkindnesses.

^8For he said, Surely they are my people, children that will not lie: so he was their Saviour.

^9In all their affliction he was afflicted, and the angel of his presence saved them: in his love and in his pity he redeemed them; and he bare them, and carried them all the days of old.

^10But they rebelled, and vexed his holy Spirit: therefore he was turned to be their enemy, and he fought against them.

^11Then he remembered the days of old, Moses, and his people, saying, Where is he that brought them up out of the sea with the shepherd of his flock? where is he that put his holy Spirit within him?

^12That led them by the right hand of Moses with his glorious arm, dividing the water before them, to make himself an everlasting name?

^13That led them through the deep, as an horse in the wilderness, that they should not stumble?

^14As a beast goeth down into the valley, the Spirit of the Lord caused him to rest: so didst thou lead thy people, to make thyself a glorious name.

^15Look down from heaven, and behold from the habitation of thy holiness and of thy glory: where is thy zeal and thy strength, the sounding of thy bowels and of thy mercies toward me? are they restrained?

^16Doubtless thou art our father, though Abraham be ignorant of us, and Israel acknowledge us not: thou, O Lord, art our father, our redeemer; thy name is from everlasting.

^17O Lord, why hast thou made us to err from thy ways, and hardened our heart from thy fear? Return for thy servants’ sake, the tribes of thine inheritance.

^18The people of thy holiness have possessed it but a little while: our adversaries have trodden down thy sanctuary.

^19We are thine: thou never barest rule over them; they were not called by thy name.

Isaiah 64

64^1Oh that thou wouldest rend the heavens, that thou wouldest come down, that the mountains might flow down at thy presence,

^2As when the melting fire burneth, the fire causeth the waters to boil, to make thy name known to thine adversaries, that the nations may tremble at thy presence!

^3When thou didst terrible things which we looked not for, thou camest down, the mountains flowed down at thy presence.

^4For since the beginning of the world men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye seen, O God, beside thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him.

^5Thou meetest him that rejoiceth and worketh righteousness, those that remember thee in thy ways: behold, thou art wroth; for we have sinned: in those is continuance, and we shall be saved.

^6But we are all as an unclean thing, and all our righteousnesses are as filthy rags; and we all do fade as a leaf; and our iniquities, like the wind, have taken us away.

^7And there is none that calleth upon thy name, that stirreth up himself to take hold of thee: for thou hast hid thy face from us, and hast consumed us, because of our iniquities.

^8But now, O Lord, thou art our father; we are the clay, and thou our potter; and we all are the work of thy hand.

^9Be not wroth very sore, O Lord, neither remember iniquity for ever: behold, see, we beseech thee, we are all thy people.

^10Thy holy cities are a wilderness, Zion is a wilderness, Jerusalem a desolation.

^11Our holy and our beautiful house, where our fathers praised thee, is burned up with fire: and all our pleasant things are laid waste.

^12Wilt thou refrain thyself for these things, O Lord? wilt thou hold thy peace, and afflict us very sore?

Isaiah 65

65^1I am sought of them that asked not for me; I am found of them that sought me not: I said, Behold me, behold me, unto a nation that was not called by my name.

^2I have spread out my hands all the day unto a rebellious people, which walketh in a way that was not good, after their own thoughts;

^3A people that provoketh me to anger continually to my face; that sacrificeth in gardens, and burneth incense upon altars of brick;

^4Which remain among the graves, and lodge in the monuments, which eat swine’s flesh, and broth of abominable things is in their vessels;

^5Which say, Stand by thyself, come not near to me; for I am holier than thou. These are a smoke in my nose, a fire that burneth all the day.

^6Behold, it is written before me: I will not keep silence, but will recompense, even recompense into their bosom,

^7Your iniquities, and the iniquities of your fathers together, saith the Lord, which have burned incense upon the mountains, and blasphemed me upon the hills: therefore will I measure their former work into their bosom.

^8Thus saith the Lord, As the new wine is found in the cluster, and one saith, Destroy it not; for a blessing is in it: so will I do for my servants’ sakes, that I may not destroy them all.

^9And I will bring forth a seed out of Jacob, and out of Judah an inheritor of my mountains: and mine elect shall inherit it, and my servants shall dwell there.

^10And Sharon shall be a fold of flocks, and the valley of Achor a place for the herds to lie down in, for my people that have sought me.

^11But ye are they that forsake the Lord, that forget my holy mountain, that prepare a table for that troop, and that furnish the drink offering unto that number.

^12Therefore will I number you to the sword, and ye shall all bow down to the slaughter: because when I called, ye did not answer; when I spake, ye did not hear; but did evil before mine eyes, and did choose that wherein I delighted not.

^13Therefore thus saith the Lord God, Behold, my servants shall eat, but ye shall be hungry: behold, my servants shall drink, but ye shall be thirsty: behold, my servants shall rejoice, but ye shall be ashamed:

^14Behold, my servants shall sing for joy of heart, but ye shall cry for sorrow of heart, and shall howl for vexation of spirit.

^15And ye shall leave your name for a curse unto my chosen: for the Lord God shall slay thee, and call his servants by another name:

^16That he who blesseth himself in the earth shall bless himself in the God of truth; and he that sweareth in the earth shall swear by the God of truth; because the former troubles are forgotten, and because they are hid from mine eyes.

^17For, behold, I create new heavens and a new earth: and the former shall not be remembered, nor come into mind.

^18But be ye glad and rejoice for ever in that which I create: for, behold, I create Jerusalem a rejoicing, and her people a joy.

^19And I will rejoice in Jerusalem, and joy in my people: and the voice of weeping shall be no more heard in her, nor the voice of crying.

^20There shall be no more thence an infant of days, nor an old man that hath not filled his days: for the child shall die an hundred years old; but the sinner being an hundred years old shall be accursed.

^21And they shall build houses, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of them.

^22They shall not build, and another inhabit; they shall not plant, and another eat: for as the days of a tree are the days of my people, and mine elect shall long enjoy the work of their hands.

^23They shall not labour in vain, nor bring forth for trouble; for they are the seed of the blessed of the Lord, and their offspring with them.

^24And it shall come to pass, that before they call, I will answer; and while they are yet speaking, I will hear.

^25The wolf and the lamb shall feed together, and the lion shall eat straw like the bullock: and dust shall be the serpent’s meat. They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain, saith the Lord.

Isaiah 66

66^1Thus saith the Lord, The heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool: where is the house that ye build unto me? and where is the place of my rest?

^2For all those things hath mine hand made, and all those things have been, saith the Lord: but to this man will I look, even to him that is poor and of a contrite spirit, and trembleth at my word.

^3He that killeth an ox is as if he slew a man; he that sacrificeth a lamb, as if he cut off a dog’s neck; he that offereth an oblation, as if he offered swine’s blood; he that burneth incense, as if he blessed an idol. Yea, they have chosen their own ways, and their soul delighteth in their abominations.

^4I also will choose their delusions, and will bring their fears upon them; because when I called, none did answer; when I spake, they did not hear: but they did evil before mine eyes, and chose that in which I delighted not.

^5Hear the word of the Lord, ye that tremble at his word; Your brethren that hated you, that cast you out for my name’s sake, said, Let the Lord be glorified: but he shall appear to your joy, and they shall be ashamed.

^6A voice of noise from the city, a voice from the temple, a voice of the Lord that rendereth recompence to his enemies.

^7Before she travailed, she brought forth; before her pain came, she was delivered of a man child.

^8Who hath heard such a thing? who hath seen such things? Shall the earth be made to bring forth in one day? or shall a nation be born at once? for as soon as Zion travailed, she brought forth her children.

^9Shall I bring to the birth, and not cause to bring forth? saith the Lord: shall I cause to bring forth, and shut the womb? saith thy God.

^10Rejoice ye with Jerusalem, and be glad with her, all ye that love her: rejoice for joy with her, all ye that mourn for her:

^11That ye may suck, and be satisfied with the breasts of her consolations; that ye may milk out, and be delighted with the abundance of her glory.

^12For thus saith the Lord, Behold, I will extend peace to her like a river, and the glory of the Gentiles like a flowing stream: then shall ye suck, ye shall be borne upon her sides, and be dandled upon her knees.

^13As one whom his mother comforteth, so will I comfort you; and ye shall be comforted in Jerusalem.

^14And when ye see this, your heart shall rejoice, and your bones shall flourish like an herb: and the hand of the Lord shall be known toward his servants, and his indignation toward his enemies.

^15For, behold, the Lord will come with fire, and with his chariots like a whirlwind, to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of fire.

^16For by fire and by his sword will the Lord plead with all flesh: and the slain of the Lord shall be many.

^17They that sanctify themselves, and purify themselves in the gardens behind one tree in the midst, eating swine’s flesh, and the abomination, and the mouse, shall be consumed together, saith the Lord.

^18For I know their works and their thoughts: it shall come, that I will gather all nations and tongues; and they shall come, and see my glory.

^19And I will set a sign among them, and I will send those that escape of them unto the nations, to Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, that draw the bow, to Tubal, and Javan, to the isles afar off, that have not heard my fame, neither have seen my glory; and they shall declare my glory among the Gentiles.

^20And they shall bring all your brethren for an offering unto the Lord out of all nations upon horses, and in chariots, and in litters, and upon mules, and upon swift beasts, to my holy mountain Jerusalem, saith the Lord, as the children of Israel bring an offering in a clean vessel into the house of the Lord.

^21And I will also take of them for priests and for Levites, saith the Lord.

^22For as the new heavens and the new earth, which I will make, shall remain before me, saith the Lord, so shall your seed and your name remain.

^23And it shall come to pass, that from one new moon to another, and from one sabbath to another, shall all flesh come to worship before me, saith the Lord.

^24And they shall go forth, and look upon the carcases of the men that have transgressed against me: for their worm shall not die, neither shall their fire be quenched; and they shall be an abhorring unto all flesh.

Book 25 Lamentations

25:001:001 How doth the city sit solitary, that was full of people! how is she become as a widow! she that was great among the nations, and princess among the provinces, how is she become tributary!

25:001:002 She weepeth sore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks: among all her lovers she hath none to comfort her: all her friends have dealt treacherously with her, they are become her enemies.

25:001:003 Judah is gone into captivity because of affliction, and because of great servitude: she dwelleth among the heathen, she findeth no rest: all her persecutors overtook her between the straits.

25:001:004 The ways of Zion do mourn, because none come to the solemn feasts: all her gates are desolate: her priests sigh, her virgins are afflicted, and she is in bitterness.

25:001:005 Her adversaries are the chief, her enemies prosper; for the LORD hath afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions: her children are gone into captivity before the enemy.

25:001:006 And from the daughter of Zion all her beauty is departed: her princes are become like harts that find no pasture, and they are gone without strength before the pursuer.

25:001:007 Jerusalem remembered in the days of her affliction and of her miseries all her pleasant things that she had in the days of old, when her people fell into the hand of the enemy, and none did help her: the adversaries saw her, and did mock at her sabbaths.

25:001:008 Jerusalem hath grievously sinned; therefore she is removed: all that honoured her despise her, because they have seen her nakedness: yea, she sigheth, and turneth backward.

25:001:009 Her filthiness is in her skirts; she remembereth not her last end; therefore she came down wonderfully: she had no comforter. O LORD, behold my affliction: for the enemy hath magnified himself.

25:001:010 The adversary hath spread out his hand upon all her pleasant things: for she hath seen that the heathen entered into her sanctuary, whom thou didst command that they should not enter into thy congregation.

25:001:011 All her people sigh, they seek bread; they have given their pleasant things for meat to relieve the soul: see, O LORD, and consider; for I am become vile.

25:001:012 Is it nothing to you, all ye that pass by? behold, and see if there be any sorrow like unto my sorrow, which is done unto me, wherewith the LORD hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger.

25:001:013 From above hath he sent fire into my bones, and it prevaileth against them: he hath spread a net for my feet, he hath turned me back: he hath made me desolate and faint all the day.

25:001:014 The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand: they are wreathed, and come up upon my neck: he hath made my strength to fall, the LORD hath delivered me into their hands, from whom I am not able to rise up.

25:001:015 The LORD hath trodden under foot all my mighty men in the midst of me: he hath called an assembly against me to crush my young men: the LORD hath trodden the virgin, the daughter of Judah, as in a winepress.

25:001:016 For these things I weep; mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water, because the comforter that should relieve my soul is far from me: my children are desolate, because the enemy prevailed.

25:001:017 Zion spreadeth forth her hands, and there is none to comfort her: the LORD hath commanded concerning Jacob, that his adversaries should be round about him: Jerusalem is as a menstruous woman among them.

25:001:018 The LORD is righteous; for I have rebelled against his commandment: hear, I pray you, all people, and behold my sorrow: my virgins and my young men are gone into captivity.

25:001:019 I called for my lovers, but they deceived me: my priests and mine elders gave up the ghost in the city, while they sought their meat to relieve their souls.

25:001:020 Behold, O LORD; for I am in distress: my bowels are troubled; mine heart is turned within me; for I have grievously rebelled: abroad the sword bereaveth, at home there is as death.

25:001:021 They have heard that I sigh: there is none to comfort me: all mine enemies have heard of my trouble; they are glad that thou hast done it: thou wilt bring the day that thou hast called, and they shall be like unto me.

25:001:022 Let all their wickedness come before thee; and do unto them, as thou hast done unto me for all my transgressions: for my sighs are many, and my heart is faint.

25:002:001 How hath the LORD covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in his anger, and cast down from heaven unto the earth the beauty of Israel, and remembered not his footstool in the day of his anger!

25:002:002 The LORD hath swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob, and hath not pitied: he hath thrown down in his wrath the strong holds of the daughter of Judah; he hath brought them down to the ground: he hath polluted the kingdom and the princes thereof.

25:002:003 He hath cut off in his fierce anger all the horn of Israel: he hath drawn back his right hand from before the enemy, and he burned against Jacob like a flaming fire, which devoureth round about.

25:002:004 He hath bent his bow like an enemy: he stood with his right hand as an adversary, and slew all that were pleasant to the eye in the tabernacle of the daughter of Zion: he poured out his fury like fire.

25:002:005 The LORD was as an enemy: he hath swallowed up Israel, he hath swallowed up all her palaces: he hath destroyed his strong holds, and hath increased in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation.

25:002:006 And he hath violently taken away his tabernacle, as if it were of a garden: he hath destroyed his places of the assembly: the LORD hath caused the solemn feasts and sabbaths to be forgotten in Zion, and hath despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest.

25:002:007 The LORD hath cast off his altar, he hath abhorred his sanctuary, he hath given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces; they have made a noise in the house of the LORD, as in the day of a solemn feast.

25:002:008 The LORD hath purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion: he hath stretched out a line, he hath not withdrawn his hand from destroying: therefore he made the rampart and the wall to lament; they languished together.

25:002:009 Her gates are sunk into the ground; he hath destroyed and broken her bars: her king and her princes are among the Gentiles: the law is no more; her prophets also find no vision from the LORD.

25:002:010 The elders of the daughter of Zion sit upon the ground, and keep silence: they have cast up dust upon their heads; they have girded themselves with sackcloth: the virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.

25:002:011 Mine eyes do fail with tears, my bowels are troubled, my liver is poured upon the earth, for the destruction of the daughter of my people; because the children and the sucklings swoon in the streets of the city.

25:002:012 They say to their mothers, Where is corn and wine? when they swooned as the wounded in the streets of the city, when their soul was poured out into their mothers' bosom.

25:002:013 What thing shall I take to witness for thee? what thing shall I liken to thee, O daughter of Jerusalem? what shall I equal to thee, that I may comfort thee, O virgin daughter of Zion? for thy breach is great like the sea: who can heal thee?

25:002:014 Thy prophets have seen vain and foolish things for thee: and they have not discovered thine iniquity, to turn away thy captivity; but have seen for thee false burdens and causes of banishment.

25:002:015 All that pass by clap their hands at thee; they hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, saying, Is this the city that men call The perfection of beauty, The joy of the whole earth?

25:002:016 All thine enemies have opened their mouth against thee: they hiss and gnash the teeth: they say, We have swallowed her up: certainly this is the day that we looked for; we have found, we have seen it.

25:002:017 The LORD hath done that which he had devised; he hath fulfilled his word that he had commanded in the days of old: he hath thrown down, and hath not pitied: and he hath caused thine enemy to rejoice over thee, he hath set up the horn of thine adversaries.

25:002:018 Their heart cried unto the LORD, O wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears run down like a river day and night: give thyself no rest; let not the apple of thine eye cease.

25:002:019 Arise, cry out in the night: in the beginning of the watches pour out thine heart like water before the face of the LORD: lift up thy hands toward him for the life of thy young children, that faint for hunger in the top of every street.

25:002:020 Behold, O LORD, and consider to whom thou hast done this. Shall the women eat their fruit, and children of a span long? shall the priest and the prophet be slain in the sanctuary of the Lord?

25:002:021 The young and the old lie on the ground in the streets: my virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword; thou hast slain them in the day of thine anger; thou hast killed, and not pitied.

25:002:022 Thou hast called as in a solemn day my terrors round about, so that in the day of the LORD's anger none escaped nor remained: those that I have swaddled and brought up hath mine enemy consumed.

25:003:001 I AM the man that hath seen affliction by the rod of his wrath.

25:003:002 He hath led me, and brought me into darkness, but not into light.

25:003:003 Surely against me is he turned; he turneth his hand against me all the day.

25:003:004 My flesh and my skin hath he made old; he hath broken my bones.

25:003:005 He hath builded against me, and compassed me with gall and travail.

25:003:006 He hath set me in dark places, as they that be dead of old.

25:003:007 He hath hedged me about, that I cannot get out: he hath made my chain heavy.

25:003:008 Also when I cry and shout, he shutteth out my prayer.

25:003:009 He hath inclosed my ways with hewn stone, he hath made my paths crooked.

25:003:010 He was unto me as a bear lying in wait, and as a lion in secret places.

25:003:011 He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces: he hath made me desolate.

25:003:012 He hath bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow.

25:003:013 He hath caused the arrows of his quiver to enter into my reins.

25:003:014 I was a derision to all my people; and their song all the day.

25:003:015 He hath filled me with bitterness, he hath made me drunken with wormwood.

25:003:016 He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones, he hath covered me with ashes.

25:003:017 And thou hast removed my soul far off from peace: I forgat prosperity.

25:003:018 And I said, My strength and my hope is perished from the LORD:

25:003:019 Remembering mine affliction and my misery, the wormwood and the gall.

25:003:020 My soul hath them still in remembrance, and is humbled in me.

25:003:021 This I recall to my mind, therefore have I hope.

25:003:022 It is of the LORD's mercies that we are not consumed, because his compassions fail not.

25:003:023 They are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness.

25:003:024 The LORD is my portion, saith my soul; therefore will I hope in him.

25:003:025 The LORD is good unto them that wait for him, to the soul that seeketh him.

25:003:026 It is good that a man should both hope and quietly wait for the salvation of the LORD.

25:003:027 It is good for a man that he bear the yoke of his youth.

25:003:028 He sitteth alone and keepeth silence, because he hath borne it upon him.

25:003:029 He putteth his mouth in the dust; if so be there may be hope.

25:003:030 He giveth his cheek to him that smiteth him: he is filled full with reproach.

25:003:031 For the LORD will not cast off for ever:

25:003:032 But though he cause grief, yet will he have compassion according to the multitude of his mercies.

25:003:033 For he doth not afflict willingly nor grieve the children of men.

25:003:034 To crush under his feet all the prisoners of the earth.

25:003:035 To turn aside the right of a man before the face of the most High,

25:003:036 To subvert a man in his cause, the LORD approveth not.

25:003:037 Who is he that saith, and it cometh to pass, when the Lord commandeth it not?

25:003:038 Out of the mouth of the most High proceedeth not evil and good?

25:003:039 Wherefore doth a living man complain, a man for the punishment of his sins?

25:003:040 Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to the LORD.

25:003:041 Let us lift up our heart with our hands unto God in the heavens.

25:003:042 We have transgressed and have rebelled: thou hast not pardoned.

25:003:043 Thou hast covered with anger, and persecuted us: thou hast slain, thou hast not pitied.

25:003:044 Thou hast covered thyself with a cloud, that our prayer should not pass through.

25:003:045 Thou hast made us as the offscouring and refuse in the midst of the people.

25:003:046 All our enemies have opened their mouths against us.

25:003:047 Fear and a snare is come upon us, desolation and destruction.

25:003:048 Mine eye runneth down with rivers of water for the destruction of the daughter of my people.

25:003:049 Mine eye trickleth down, and ceaseth not, without any intermission.

25:003:050 Till the LORD look down, and behold from heaven.

25:003:051 Mine eye affecteth mine heart because of all the daughters of my city.

25:003:052 Mine enemies chased me sore, like a bird, without cause.

25:003:053 They have cut off my life in the dungeon, and cast a stone upon me.

25:003:054 Waters flowed over mine head; then I said, I am cut off.

25:003:055 I called upon thy name, O LORD, out of the low dungeon.

25:003:056 Thou hast heard my voice: hide not thine ear at my breathing, at my cry.

25:003:057 Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon thee: thou saidst, Fear not.

25:003:058 O LORD, thou hast pleaded the causes of my soul; thou hast redeemed my life.

25:003:059 O LORD, thou hast seen my wrong: judge thou my cause.

25:003:060 Thou hast seen all their vengeance and all their imaginations against me.

25:003:061 Thou hast heard their reproach, O LORD, and all their imaginations against me;

25:003:062 The lips of those that rose up against me, and their device against me all the day.

25:003:063 Behold their sitting down, and their rising up; I am their musick.

25:003:064 Render unto them a recompence, O LORD, according to the work of their hands.

25:003:065 Give them sorrow of heart, thy curse unto them.

25:003:066 Persecute and destroy them in anger from under the heavens of the LORD.

25:004:001 How is the gold become dim! how is the most fine gold changed! the stones of the sanctuary are poured out in the top of every street.

25:004:002 The precious sons of Zion, comparable to fine gold, how are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter!

25:004:003 Even the sea monsters draw out the breast, they give suck to their young ones: the daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the wilderness.

25:004:004 The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth to the roof of his mouth for thirst: the young children ask bread, and no man breaketh it unto them.

25:004:005 They that did feed delicately are desolate in the streets: they that were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills.

25:004:006 For the punishment of the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the punishment of the sin of Sodom, that was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands stayed on her.

25:004:007 Her Nazarites were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk, they were more ruddy in body than rubies, their polishing was of sapphire:

25:004:008 Their visage is blacker than a coal; they are not known in the streets: their skin cleaveth to their bones; it is withered, it is become like a stick.

25:004:009 They that be slain with the sword are better than they that be slain with hunger: for these pine away, stricken through for want of the fruits of the field.

25:004:010 The hands of the pitiful women have sodden their own children: they were their meat in the destruction of the daughter of my people.

25:004:011 The LORD hath accomplished his fury; he hath poured out his fierce anger, and hath kindled a fire in Zion, and it hath devoured the foundations thereof.

25:004:012 The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, would not have believed that the adversary and the enemy should have entered into the gates of Jerusalem.

25:004:013 For the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, that have shed the blood of the just in the midst of her,

25:004:014 They have wandered as blind men in the streets, they have polluted themselves with blood, so that men could not touch their garments.

25:004:015 They cried unto them, Depart ye; it is unclean; depart, depart, touch not: when they fled away and wandered, they said among the heathen, They shall no more sojourn there.

25:004:016 The anger of the LORD hath divided them; he will no more regard them: they respected not the persons of the priests, they favoured not the elders.

25:004:017 As for us, our eyes as yet failed for our vain help: in our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save us.

25:004:018 They hunt our steps, that we cannot go in our streets: our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come.

25:004:019 Our persecutors are swifter than the eagles of the heaven: they pursued us upon the mountains, they laid wait for us in the wilderness.

25:004:020 The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of the LORD, was taken in their pits, of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the heathen.

25:004:021 Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom, that dwellest in the land of Uz; the cup also shall pass through unto thee: thou shalt be drunken, and shalt make thyself naked.

25:004:022 The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion; he will no more carry thee away into captivity: he will visit thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he will discover thy sins.

25:005:001 Remember, O LORD, what is come upon us: consider, and behold our reproach.

25:005:002 Our inheritance is turned to strangers, our houses to aliens.

25:005:003 We are orphans and fatherless, our mothers are as widows.

25:005:004 We have drunken our water for money; our wood is sold unto us.

25:005:005 Our necks are under persecution: we labour, and have no rest.

25:005:006 We have given the hand to the Egyptians, and to the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread.

25:005:007 Our fathers have sinned, and are not; and we have borne their iniquities.

25:005:008 Servants have ruled over us: there is none that doth deliver us out of their hand.

25:005:009 We gat our bread with the peril of our lives because of the sword of the wilderness.

25:005:010 Our skin was black like an oven because of the terrible famine.

25:005:011 They ravished the women in Zion, and the maids in the cities of Judah.

25:005:012 Princes are hanged up by their hand: the faces of elders were not honoured.

25:005:013 They took the young men to grind, and the children fell under the wood.

25:005:014 The elders have ceased from the gate, the young men from their musick.

25:005:015 The joy of our heart is ceased; our dance is turned into mourning.

25:005:016 The crown is fallen from our head: woe unto us, that we have sinned!

25:005:017 For this our heart is faint; for these things our eyes are dim.

25:005:018 Because of the mountain of Zion, which is desolate, the foxes walk upon it.

25:005:019 Thou, O LORD, remainest for ever; thy throne from generation to generation.

25:005:020 Wherefore dost thou forget us for ever, and forsake us so long time?

25:005:021 Turn thou us unto thee, O LORD, and we shall be turned; renew our days as of old.

25:005:022 But thou hast utterly rejected us; thou art very wroth against us.

Daniel

The Book of

Daniel

I

1^1In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah came Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon unto Jerusalem, and besieged it.

^2And the Lord gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with part of the vessels of the house of God: which he carried into the land of Shinar to the house of his god; and he brought the vessels into the treasure house of his god.

^3And the king spake unto Ashpenaz the master of his eunuchs, that he should bring certain of the children of Israel, and of the king’s seed, and of the princes;

^4Children in whom was no blemish, but well favoured, and skilful in all wisdom, and cunning in knowledge, and understanding science, and such as had ability in them to stand in the king’s palace, and whom they might teach the learning and the tongue of the Chaldeans.

^5And the king appointed them a daily provision of the king’s meat, and of the wine which he drank: so nourishing them three years, that at the end thereof they might stand before the king.

^6Now among these were of the children of Judah, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah:

^7Unto whom the prince of the eunuchs gave names: for he gave unto Daniel the name of Belteshazzar; and to Hananiah, of Shadrach; and to Mishael, of Meshach; and to Azariah, of Abednego.

^8But Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself with the portion of the king’s meat, nor with the wine which he drank: therefore he requested of the prince of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself.

^9Now God had brought Daniel into favour and tender love with the prince of the eunuchs.

^10And the prince of the eunuchs said unto Daniel, I fear my lord the king, who hath appointed your meat and your drink: for why should he see your faces worse liking than the children which are of your sort? then shall ye make me endanger my head to the king.

^11Then said Daniel to Melzar, whom the prince of the eunuchs had set over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,

^12Prove thy servants, I beseech thee, ten days; and let them give us pulse to eat, and water to drink.

^13Then let our countenances be looked upon before thee, and the countenance of the children that eat of the portion of the king’s meat: and as thou seest, deal with thy servants.

^14So he consented to them in this matter, and proved them ten days.

^15And at the end of ten days their countenances appeared fairer and fatter in flesh than all the children which did eat the portion of the king’s meat.

^16Thus Melzar took away the portion of their meat, and the wine that they should drink; and gave them pulse.

^17As for these four children, God gave them knowledge and skill in all learning and wisdom: and Daniel had understanding in all visions and dreams.

^18Now at the end of the days that the king had said he should bring them in, then the prince of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar.

^19And the king communed with them; and among them all was found none like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: therefore stood they before the king.

^20And in all matters of wisdom and understanding, that the king enquired of them, he found them ten times better than all the magicians and astrologers that were in all his realm.

^21And Daniel continued even unto the first year of king Cyrus.

II

2^1And in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams, wherewith his spirit was troubled, and his sleep brake from him.

^2Then the king commanded to call the magicians, and the astrologers, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, for to shew the king his dreams. So they came and stood before the king.

^3And the king said unto them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit was troubled to know the dream.

^4Then spake the Chaldeans to the king in Syriack, O king, live for ever: tell thy servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation.

^5The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The thing is gone from me: if ye will not make known unto me the dream, with the interpretation thereof, ye shall be cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made a dunghill.

^6But if ye shew the dream, and the interpretation thereof, ye shall receive of me gifts and rewards and great honour: therefore shew me the dream, and the interpretation thereof.

^7They answered again and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation of it.

^8The king answered and said, I know of certainty that ye would gain the time, because ye see the thing is gone from me.

^9But if ye will not make known unto me the dream, there is but one decree for you: for ye have prepared lying and corrupt words to speak before me, till the time be changed: therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that ye can shew me the interpretation thereof.

^10The Chaldeans answered before the king, and said, There is not a man upon the earth that can shew the king’s matter: therefore there is no king, lord, nor ruler, that asked such things at any magician, or astrologer, or Chaldean.

^11And it is a rare thing that the king requireth, and there is none other that can shew it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh.

^12For this cause the king was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon.

^13And the decree went forth that the wise men should be slain; and they sought Daniel and his fellows to be slain.

^14Then Daniel answered with counsel and wisdom to Arioch the captain of the king’s guard, which was gone forth to slay the wise men of Babylon:

^15He answered and said to Arioch the king’s captain, Why is the decree so hasty from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel.

^16Then Daniel went in, and desired of the king that he would give him time, and that he would shew the king the interpretation.

^17Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions:

^18That they would desire mercies of the God of heaven concerning this secret; that Daniel and his fellows should not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon.

^19Then was the secret revealed unto Daniel in a night vision. Then Daniel blessed the God of heaven.

^20Daniel answered and said, Blessed be the name of God for ever and ever: for wisdom and might are his:

^21And he changeth the times and the seasons: he removeth kings, and setteth up kings: he giveth wisdom unto the wise, and knowledge to them that know understanding:

^22He revealeth the deep and secret things: he knoweth what is in the darkness, and the light dwelleth with him.

^23I thank thee, and praise thee, O thou God of my fathers, who hast given me wisdom and might, and hast made known unto me now what we desired of thee: for thou hast now made known unto us the king’s matter.

^24Therefore Daniel went in unto Arioch, whom the king had ordained to destroy the wise men of Babylon: he went and said thus unto him; Destroy not the wise men of Babylon: bring me in before the king, and I will shew unto the king the interpretation.

^25Then Arioch brought in Daniel before the king in haste, and said thus unto him, I have found a man of the captives of Judah, that will make known unto the king the interpretation.

^26The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, Art thou able to make known unto me the dream which I have seen, and the interpretation thereof?

^27Daniel answered in the presence of the king, and said, The secret which the king hath demanded cannot the wise men, the astrologers, the magicians, the soothsayers, shew unto the king;

^28But there is a God in heaven that revealeth secrets, and maketh known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Thy dream, and the visions of thy head upon thy bed, are these;

^29As for thee, O king, thy thoughts came into thy mind upon thy bed, what should come to pass hereafter: and he that revealeth secrets maketh known to thee what shall come to pass.

^30But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for any wisdom that I have more than any living, but for their sakes that shall make known the interpretation to the king, and that thou mightest know the thoughts of thy heart.

^31Thou, O king, sawest, and behold a great image. This great image, whose brightness was excellent, stood before thee; and the form thereof was terrible.

^32This image’s head was of fine gold, his breast and his arms of silver, his belly and his thighs of brass,

^33His legs of iron, his feet part of iron and part of clay.

^34Thou sawest till that a stone was cut out without hands, which smote the image upon his feet that were of iron and clay, and brake them to pieces.

^35Then was the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold, broken to pieces together, and became like the chaff of the summer threshingfloors; and the wind carried them away, that no place was found for them: and the stone that smote the image became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth.

^36This is the dream; and we will tell the interpretation thereof before the king.

^37Thou, O king, art a king of kings: for the God of heaven hath given thee a kingdom, power, and strength, and glory.

^38And wheresoever the children of men dwell, the beasts of the field and the fowls of the heaven hath he given into thine hand, and hath made thee ruler over them all. Thou art this head of gold.

^39And after thee shall arise another kingdom inferior to thee, and another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear rule over all the earth.

^40And the fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron: forasmuch as iron breaketh in pieces and subdueth all things: and as iron that breaketh all these, shall it break in pieces and bruise.

^41And whereas thou sawest the feet and toes, part of potters’ clay, and part of iron, the kingdom shall be divided; but there shall be in it of the strength of the iron, forasmuch as thou sawest the iron mixed with miry clay.

^42And as the toes of the feet were part of iron, and part of clay, so the kingdom shall be partly strong, and partly broken.

^43And whereas thou sawest iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mingle themselves with the seed of men: but they shall not cleave one to another, even as iron is not mixed with clay.

^44And in the days of these kings shall the God of heaven set up a kingdom, which shall never be destroyed: and the kingdom shall not be left to other people, but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it shall stand for ever.

^45Forasmuch as thou sawest that the stone was cut out of the mountain without hands, and that it brake in pieces the iron, the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold; the great God hath made known to the king what shall come to pass hereafter: and the dream is certain, and the interpretation thereof sure.

^46Then the king Nebuchadnezzar fell upon his face, and worshipped Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an oblation and sweet odours unto him.

^47The king answered unto Daniel, and said, Of a truth it is, that your God is a God of gods, and a Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, seeing thou couldest reveal this secret.

^48Then the king made Daniel a great man, and gave him many great gifts, and made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon, and chief of the governors over all the wise men of Babylon.

^49Then Daniel requested of the king, and he set Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, over the affairs of the province of Babylon: but Daniel sat in the gate of the king.

III

3^1Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof six cubits: he set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon.

^2Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the princes, the governors, and the captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.

^3Then the princes, the governors, and captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together unto the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up.

^4Then an herald cried aloud, To you it is commanded, O people, nations, and languages,

^5That at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, ye fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath set up:

^6And whoso falleth not down and worshippeth shall the same hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.

^7Therefore at that time, when all the people heard the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and all kinds of musick, all the people, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshipped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.

^8Wherefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and accused the Jews.

^9They spake and said to the king Nebuchadnezzar, O king, live for ever.

^10Thou, O king, hast made a decree, that every man that shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, shall fall down and worship the golden image:

^11And whoso falleth not down and worshippeth, that he should be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.

^12There are certain Jews whom thou hast set over the affairs of the province of Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego; these men, O king, have not regarded thee: they serve not thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.

^13Then Nebuchadnezzar in his rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. Then they brought these men before the king.

^14Nebuchadnezzar spake and said unto them, Is it true, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, do not ye serve my gods, nor worship the golden image which I have set up?

^15Now if ye be ready that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, ye fall down and worship the image which I have made; well: but if ye worship not, ye shall be cast the same hour into the midst of a burning fiery furnace; and who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hands?

^16Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we are not careful to answer thee in this matter.

^17If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thine hand, O king.

^18But if not, be it known unto thee, O king, that we will not serve thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.

^19Then was Nebuchadnezzar full of fury, and the form of his visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego: therefore he spake, and commanded that they should heat the furnace one seven times more than it was wont to be heated.

^20And he commanded the most mighty men that were in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace.

^21Then these men were bound in their coats, their hosen, and their hats, and their other garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.

^22Therefore because the king’s commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the flames of the fire slew those men that took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego.

^23And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.

^24Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonied, and rose up in haste, and spake, and said unto his counsellors, Did not we cast three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said unto the king, True, O king.

^25He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and they have no hurt; and the form of the fourth is like the Son of God.

^26Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the mouth of the burning fiery furnace, and spake, and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, ye servants of the most high God, come forth, and come hither. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, came forth of the midst of the fire.

^27And the princes, governors, and captains, and the king’s counsellors, being gathered together, saw these men, upon whose bodies the fire had no power, nor was an hair of their head singed, neither were their coats changed, nor the smell of fire had passed on them.

^28Then Nebuchadnezzar spake, and said, Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, who hath sent his angel, and delivered his servants that trusted in him, and have changed the king’s word, and yielded their bodies, that they might not serve nor worship any god, except their own God.

^29Therefore I make a decree, That every people, nation, and language, which speak any thing amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, shall be cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill: because there is no other God that can deliver after this sort.

^30Then the king promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, in the province of Babylon.

IV

4^1Nebuchadnezzar the king, unto all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth; Peace be multiplied unto you.

^2I thought it good to shew the signs and wonders that the high God hath wrought toward me.

^3How great are his signs! and how mighty are his wonders! his kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from generation to generation.

^4I Nebuchadnezzar was at rest in mine house, and flourishing in my palace:

^5I saw a dream which made me afraid, and the thoughts upon my bed and the visions of my head troubled me.

^6Therefore made I a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known unto me the interpretation of the dream.

^7Then came in the magicians, the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers: and I told the dream before them; but they did not make known unto me the interpretation thereof.

^8But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name was Belteshazzar, according to the name of my God, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods: and before him I told the dream, saying,

^9O Belteshazzar, master of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret troubleth thee, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and the interpretation thereof.

^10Thus were the visions of mine head in my bed; I saw, and behold a tree in the midst of the earth, and the height thereof was great.

^11The tree grew, and was strong, and the height thereof reached unto heaven, and the sight thereof to the end of all the earth:

^12The leaves thereof were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all: the beasts of the field had shadow under it, and the fowls of the heaven dwelt in the boughs thereof, and all flesh was fed of it.

^13I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and, behold, a watcher and an holy one came down from heaven;

^14He cried aloud, and said thus, Hew down the tree, and cut off his branches, shake off his leaves, and scatter his fruit: let the beasts get away from under it, and the fowls from his branches:

^15Nevertheless leave the stump of his roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth:

^16Let his heart be changed from man’s, and let a beast’s heart be given unto him; and let seven times pass over him.

^17This matter is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones: to the intent that the living may know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the basest of men.

^18This dream I king Nebuchadnezzar have seen. Now thou, O Belteshazzar, declare the interpretation thereof, forasmuch as all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known unto me the interpretation: but thou art able; for the spirit of the holy gods is in thee.

^19Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was astonied for one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. The king spake, and said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, or the interpretation thereof, trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the dream be to them that hate thee, and the interpretation thereof to thine enemies.

^20The tree that thou sawest, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached unto the heaven, and the sight thereof to all the earth;

^21Whose leaves were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all; under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and upon whose branches the fowls of the heaven had their habitation:

^22It is thou, O king, that art grown and become strong: for thy greatness is grown, and reacheth unto heaven, and thy dominion to the end of the earth.

^23And whereas the king saw a watcher and an holy one coming down from heaven, and saying, Hew the tree down, and destroy it; yet leave the stump of the roots thereof in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts of the field, till seven times pass over him;

^24This is the interpretation, O king, and this is the decree of the most High, which is come upon my lord the king:

^25That they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field, and they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and they shall wet thee with the dew of heaven, and seven times shall pass over thee, till thou know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will.

^26And whereas they commanded to leave the stump of the tree roots; thy kingdom shall be sure unto thee, after that thou shalt have known that the heavens do rule.

^27Wherefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities by shewing mercy to the poor; if it may be a lengthening of thy tranquillity.

^28All this came upon the king Nebuchadnezzar.

^29At the end of twelve months he walked in the palace of the kingdom of Babylon.

^30The king spake, and said, Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for the house of the kingdom by the might of my power, and for the honour of my majesty?

^31While the word was in the king’s mouth, there fell a voice from heaven, saying, O king Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken; The kingdom is departed from thee.

^32And they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field: they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will.

^33The same hour was the thing fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar: and he was driven from men, and did eat grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, till his hairs were grown like eagles’ feathers, and his nails like birds’ claws.

^34And at the end of the days I Nebuchadnezzar lifted up mine eyes unto heaven, and mine understanding returned unto me, and I blessed the most High, and I praised and honoured him that liveth for ever, whose dominion is an everlasting dominion, and his kingdom is from generation to generation:

^35And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing: and he doeth according to his will in the army of heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth: and none can stay his hand, or say unto him, What doest thou?

^36At the same time my reason returned unto me; and for the glory of my kingdom, mine honour and brightness returned unto me; and my counsellors and my lords sought unto me; and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent majesty was added unto me.

^37Now I Nebuchadnezzar praise and extol and honour the King of heaven, all whose works are truth, and his ways judgment: and those that walk in pride he is able to abase.

V

5^1Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand.

^2Belshazzar, whiles he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which his father Nebuchadnezzar had taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem; that the king, and his princes, his wives, and his concubines, might drink therein.

^3Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of the house of God which was at Jerusalem; and the king, and his princes, his wives, and his concubines, drank in them.

^4They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone.

^5In the same hour came forth fingers of a man’s hand, and wrote over against the candlestick upon the plaister of the wall of the king’s palace: and the king saw the part of the hand that wrote.

^6Then the king’s countenance was changed, and his thoughts troubled him, so that the joints of his loins were loosed, and his knees smote one against another.

^7The king cried aloud to bring in the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. And the king spake, and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whosoever shall read this writing, and shew me the interpretation thereof, shall be clothed with scarlet, and have a chain of gold about his neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom.

^8Then came in all the king’s wise men: but they could not read the writing, nor make known to the king the interpretation thereof.

^9Then was king Belshazzar greatly troubled, and his countenance was changed in him, and his lords were astonied.

^10Now the queen by reason of the words of the king and his lords came into the banquet house: and the queen spake and said, O king, live for ever: let not thy thoughts trouble thee, nor let thy countenance be changed:

^11There is a man in thy kingdom, in whom is the spirit of the holy gods; and in the days of thy father light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, was found in him; whom the king Nebuchadnezzar thy father, the king, I say, thy father, made master of the magicians, astrologers, Chaldeans, and soothsayers;

^12Forasmuch as an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, interpreting of dreams, and shewing of hard sentences, and dissolving of doubts, were found in the same Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar: now let Daniel be called, and he will shew the interpretation.

^13Then was Daniel brought in before the king. And the king spake and said unto Daniel, Art thou that Daniel, which art of the children of the captivity of Judah, whom the king my father brought out of Jewry?

^14I have even heard of thee, that the spirit of the gods is in thee, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom is found in thee.

^15And now the wise men, the astrologers, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing, and make known unto me the interpretation thereof: but they could not shew the interpretation of the thing:

^16And I have heard of thee, that thou canst make interpretations, and dissolve doubts: now if thou canst read the writing, and make known to me the interpretation thereof, thou shalt be clothed with scarlet, and have a chain of gold about thy neck, and shalt be the third ruler in the kingdom.

^17Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let thy gifts be to thyself, and give thy rewards to another; yet I will read the writing unto the king, and make known to him the interpretation.

^18O thou king, the most high God gave Nebuchadnezzar thy father a kingdom, and majesty, and glory, and honour:

^19And for the majesty that he gave him, all people, nations, and languages, trembled and feared before him: whom he would he slew; and whom he would he kept alive; and whom he would he set up; and whom he would he put down.

^20But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardened in pride, he was deposed from his kingly throne, and they took his glory from him:

^21And he was driven from the sons of men; and his heart was made like the beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild asses: they fed him with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven; till he knew that the most high God ruled in the kingdom of men, and that he appointeth over it whomsoever he will.

^22And thou his son, O Belshazzar, hast not humbled thine heart, though thou knewest all this;

^23But hast lifted up thyself against the Lord of heaven; and they have brought the vessels of his house before thee, and thou, and thy lords, thy wives, and thy concubines, have drunk wine in them; and thou hast praised the gods of silver, and gold, of brass, iron, wood, and stone, which see not, nor hear, nor know: and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and whose are all thy ways, hast thou not glorified:

^24Then was the part of the hand sent from him; and this writing was written.

^25And this is the writing that was written, Mene, Mene, Tekel, Upharsin.

^26This is the interpretation of the thing: Mene; God hath numbered thy kingdom, and finished it.

^27Tekel; Thou art weighed in the balances, and art found wanting.

^28Peres; Thy kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and Persians.

^29Then commanded Belshazzar, and they clothed Daniel with scarlet, and put a chain of gold about his neck, and made a proclamation concerning him, that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.

^30In that night was Belshazzar the king of the Chaldeans slain.

^31And Darius the Median took the kingdom, being about threescore and two years old.

VI

6^1It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom an hundred and twenty princes, which should be over the whole kingdom;

^2And over these three presidents; of whom Daniel was first: that the princes might give accounts unto them, and the king should have no damage.

^3Then this Daniel was preferred above the presidents and princes, because an excellent spirit was in him; and the king thought to set him over the whole realm.

^4Then the presidents and princes sought to find occasion against Daniel concerning the kingdom; but they could find none occasion nor fault; forasmuch as he was faithful, neither was there any error or fault found in him.

^5Then said these men, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel, except we find it against him concerning the law of his God.

^6Then these presidents and princes assembled together to the king, and said thus unto him, King Darius, live for ever.

^7All the presidents of the kingdom, the governors, and the princes, the counsellors, and the captains, have consulted together to establish a royal statute, and to make a firm decree, that whosoever shall ask a petition of any God or man for thirty days, save of thee, O king, he shall be cast into the den of lions.

^8Now, O king, establish the decree, and sign the writing, that it be not changed, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not.

^9Wherefore king Darius signed the writing and the decree.

^10Now when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went into his house; and his windows being open in his chamber toward Jerusalem, he kneeled upon his knees three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he did aforetime.

^11Then these men assembled, and found Daniel praying and making supplication before his God.

^12Then they came near, and spake before the king concerning the king’s decree; Hast thou not signed a decree, that every man that shall ask a petition of any God or man within thirty days, save of thee, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions? The king answered and said, The thing is true, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not.

^13Then answered they and said before the king, That Daniel, which is of the children of the captivity of Judah, regardeth not thee, O king, nor the decree that thou hast signed, but maketh his petition three times a day.

^14Then the king, when he heard these words, was sore displeased with himself, and set his heart on Daniel to deliver him: and he laboured till the going down of the sun to deliver him.

^15Then these men assembled unto the king, and said unto the king, Know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians is, That no decree nor statute which the king establisheth may be changed.

^16Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast him into the den of lions. Now the king spake and said unto Daniel, Thy God whom thou servest continually, he will deliver thee.

^17And a stone was brought, and laid upon the mouth of the den; and the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords; that the purpose might not be changed concerning Daniel.

^18Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night fasting: neither were instruments of musick brought before him: and his sleep went from him.

^19Then the king arose very early in the morning, and went in haste unto the den of lions.

^20And when he came to the den, he cried with a lamentable voice unto Daniel: and the king spake and said to Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, is thy God, whom thou servest continually, able to deliver thee from the lions?

^21Then said Daniel unto the king, O king, live for ever.

^22My God hath sent his angel, and hath shut the lions’ mouths, that they have not hurt me: forasmuch as before him innocency was found in me; and also before thee, O king, have I done no hurt.

^23Then was the king exceedingly glad for him, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no manner of hurt was found upon him, because he believed in his God.

^24And the king commanded, and they brought those men which had accused Daniel, and they cast them into the den of lions, them, their children, and their wives; and the lions had the mastery of them, and brake all their bones in pieces or ever they came at the bottom of the den.

^25Then king Darius wrote unto all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth; Peace be multiplied unto you.

^26I make a decree, That in every dominion of my kingdom men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel: for he is the living God, and stedfast for ever, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed, and his dominion shall be even unto the end.

^27He delivereth and rescueth, and he worketh signs and wonders in heaven and in earth, who hath delivered Daniel from the power of the lions.

^28So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of Cyrus the Persian.

VII

7^1In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon Daniel had a dream and visions of his head upon his bed: then he wrote the dream, and told the sum of the matters.

^2Daniel spake and said, I saw in my vision by night, and, behold, the four winds of the heaven strove upon the great sea.

^3And four great beasts came up from the sea, diverse one from another.

^4The first was like a lion, and had eagle’s wings: I beheld till the wings thereof were plucked, and it was lifted up from the earth, and made stand upon the feet as a man, and a man’s heart was given to it.

^5And behold another beast, a second, like to a bear, and it raised up itself on one side, and it had three ribs in the mouth of it between the teeth of it: and they said thus unto it, Arise, devour much flesh.

^6After this I beheld, and lo another, like a leopard, which had upon the back of it four wings of a fowl; the beast had also four heads; and dominion was given to it.

^7After this I saw in the night visions, and behold a fourth beast, dreadful and terrible, and strong exceedingly; and it had great iron teeth: it devoured and brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with the feet of it: and it was diverse from all the beasts that were before it; and it had ten horns.

^8I considered the horns, and, behold, there came up among them another little horn, before whom there were three of the first horns plucked up by the roots: and, behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of man, and a mouth speaking great things.

^9I beheld till the thrones were cast down, and the Ancient of days did sit, whose garment was white as snow, and the hair of his head like the pure wool: his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheels as burning fire.

^10A fiery stream issued and came forth from before him: thousand thousands ministered unto him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him: the judgment was set, and the books were opened.

^11I beheld then because of the voice of the great words which the horn spake: I beheld even till the beast was slain, and his body destroyed, and given to the burning flame.

^12As concerning the rest of the beasts, they had their dominion taken away: yet their lives were prolonged for a season and time.

^13I saw in the night visions, and, behold, one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of days, and they brought him near before him.

^14And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, that all people, nations, and languages, should serve him: his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed.

^15I Daniel was grieved in my spirit in the midst of my body, and the visions of my head troubled me.

^16I came near unto one of them that stood by, and asked him the truth of all this. So he told me, and made me know the interpretation of the things.

^17These great beasts, which are four, are four kings, which shall arise out of the earth.

^18But the saints of the most High shall take the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever.

^19Then I would know the truth of the fourth beast, which was diverse from all the others, exceeding dreadful, whose teeth were of iron, and his nails of brass; which devoured, brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with his feet;

^20And of the ten horns that were in his head, and of the other which came up, and before whom three fell; even of that horn that had eyes, and a mouth that spake very great things, whose look was more stout than his fellows.

^21I beheld, and the same horn made war with the saints, and prevailed against them;

^22Until the Ancient of days came, and judgment was given to the saints of the most High; and the time came that the saints possessed the kingdom.

^23Thus he said, The fourth beast shall be the fourth kingdom upon earth, which shall be diverse from all kingdoms, and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and break it in pieces.

^24And the ten horns out of this kingdom are ten kings that shall arise: and another shall rise after them; and he shall be diverse from the first, and he shall subdue three kings.

^25And he shall speak great words against the most High, and shall wear out the saints of the most High, and think to change times and laws: and they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and the dividing of time.

^26But the judgment shall sit, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume and to destroy it unto the end.

^27And the kingdom and dominion, and the greatness of the kingdom under the whole heaven, shall be given to the people of the saints of the most High, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall serve and obey him.

^28Hitherto is the end of the matter. As for me Daniel, my cogitations much troubled me, and my countenance changed in me: but I kept the matter in my heart.

VIII

8^1In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared unto me, even unto me Daniel, after that which appeared unto me at the first.

^2And I saw in a vision; and it came to pass, when I saw, that I was at Shushan in the palace, which is in the province of Elam; and I saw in a vision, and I was by the river of Ulai.

^3Then I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns: and the two horns were high; but one was higher than the other, and the higher came up last.

^4I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward; so that no beasts might stand before him, neither was there any that could deliver out of his hand; but he did according to his will, and became great.

^5And as I was considering, behold, an he goat came from the west on the face of the whole earth, and touched not the ground: and the goat had a notable horn between his eyes.

^6And he came to the ram that had two horns, which I had seen standing before the river, and ran unto him in the fury of his power.

^7And I saw him come close unto the ram, and he was moved with choler against him, and smote the ram, and brake his two horns: and there was no power in the ram to stand before him, but he cast him down to the ground, and stamped upon him: and there was none that could deliver the ram out of his hand.

^8Therefore the he goat waxed very great: and when he was strong, the great horn was broken; and for it came up four notable ones toward the four winds of heaven.

^9And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which waxed exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the pleasant land.

^10And it waxed great, even to the host of heaven; and it cast down some of the host and of the stars to the ground, and stamped upon them.

^11Yea, he magnified himself even to the prince of the host, and by him the daily sacrifice was taken away, and the place of the sanctuary was cast down.

^12And an host was given him against the daily sacrifice by reason of transgression, and it cast down the truth to the ground; and it practised, and prospered.

^13Then I heard one saint speaking, and another saint said unto that certain saint which spake, How long shall be the vision concerning the daily sacrifice, and the transgression of desolation, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trodden under foot?

^14And he said unto me, Unto two thousand and three hundred days; then shall the sanctuary be cleansed.

^15And it came to pass, when I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, and sought for the meaning, then, behold, there stood before me as the appearance of a man.

^16And I heard a man’s voice between the banks of Ulai, which called, and said, Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision.

^17So he came near where I stood: and when he came, I was afraid, and fell upon my face: but he said unto me, Understand, O son of man: for at the time of the end shall be the vision.

^18Now as he was speaking with me, I was in a deep sleep on my face toward the ground: but he touched me, and set me upright.

^19And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be in the last end of the indignation: for at the time appointed the end shall be.

^20The ram which thou sawest having two horns are the kings of Media and Persia.

^21And the rough goat is the king of Grecia: and the great horn that is between his eyes is the first king.

^22Now that being broken, whereas four stood up for it, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not in his power.

^23And in the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors are come to the full, a king of fierce countenance, and understanding dark sentences, shall stand up.

^24And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power: and he shall destroy wonderfully, and shall prosper, and practise, and shall destroy the mighty and the holy people.

^25And through his policy also he shall cause craft to prosper in his hand; and he shall magnify himself in his heart, and by peace shall destroy many: he shall also stand up against the Prince of princes; but he shall be broken without hand.

^26And the vision of the evening and the morning which was told is true: wherefore shut thou up the vision; for it shall be for many days.

^27And I Daniel fainted, and was sick certain days; afterward I rose up, and did the king’s business; and I was astonished at the vision, but none understood it.

IX

9^1In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes, which was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans;

^2In the first year of his reign I Daniel understood by books the number of the years, whereof the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah the prophet, that he would accomplish seventy years in the desolations of Jerusalem.

^3And I set my face unto the Lord God, to seek by prayer and supplications, with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes:

^4And I prayed unto the Lord my God, and made my confession, and said, O Lord, the great and dreadful God, keeping the covenant and mercy to them that love him, and to them that keep his commandments;

^5We have sinned, and have committed iniquity, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even by departing from thy precepts and from thy judgments:

^6Neither have we hearkened unto thy servants the prophets, which spake in thy name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land.

^7O Lord, righteousness belongeth unto thee, but unto us confusion of faces, as at this day; to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and unto all Israel, that are near, and that are far off, through all the countries whither thou hast driven them, because of their trespass that they have trespassed against thee.

^8O Lord, to us belongeth confusion of face, to our kings, to our princes, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against thee.

^9To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgivenesses, though we have rebelled against him;

^10Neither have we obeyed the voice of the Lord our God, to walk in his laws, which he set before us by his servants the prophets.

^11Yea, all Israel have transgressed thy law, even by departing, that they might not obey thy voice; therefore the curse is poured upon us, and the oath that is written in the law of Moses the servant of God, because we have sinned against him.

^12And he hath confirmed his words, which he spake against us, and against our judges that judged us, by bringing upon us a great evil: for under the whole heaven hath not been done as hath been done upon Jerusalem.

^13As it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil is come upon us: yet made we not our prayer before the Lord our God, that we might turn from our iniquities, and understand thy truth.

^14Therefore hath the Lord watched upon the evil, and brought it upon us: for the Lord our God is righteous in all his works which he doeth: for we obeyed not his voice.

^15And now, O Lord our God, that hast brought thy people forth out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and hast gotten thee renown, as at this day; we have sinned, we have done wickedly.

^16O Lord, according to all thy righteousness, I beseech thee, let thine anger and thy fury be turned away from thy city Jerusalem, thy holy mountain: because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and thy people are become a reproach to all that are about us.

^17Now therefore, O our God, hear the prayer of thy servant, and his supplications, and cause thy face to shine upon thy sanctuary that is desolate, for the Lord’s sake.

^18O my God, incline thine ear, and hear; open thine eyes, and behold our desolations, and the city which is called by thy name: for we do not present our supplications before thee for our righteousnesses, but for thy great mercies.

^19O Lord, hear; O Lord, forgive; O Lord, hearken and do; defer not, for thine own sake, O my God: for thy city and thy people are called by thy name.

^20And whiles I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before the Lord my God for the holy mountain of my God;

^21Yea, whiles I was speaking in prayer, even the man Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly swiftly, touched me about the time of the evening oblation.

^22And he informed me, and talked with me, and said, O Daniel, I am now come forth to give thee skill and understanding.

^23At the beginning of thy supplications the commandment came forth, and I am come to shew thee; for thou art greatly beloved: therefore understand the matter, and consider the vision.

^24Seventy weeks are determined upon thy people and upon thy holy city, to finish the transgression, and to make an end of sins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up the vision and prophecy, and to anoint the most Holy.

^25Know therefore and understand, that from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem unto the Messiah the Prince shall be seven weeks, and threescore and two weeks: the street shall be built again, and the wall, even in troublous times.

^26And after threescore and two weeks shall Messiah be cut off, but not for himself: and the people of the prince that shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary; and the end thereof shall be with a flood, and unto the end of the war desolations are determined.

^27And he shall confirm the covenant with many for one week: and in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease, and for the overspreading of abominations he shall make it desolate, even until the consummation, and that determined shall be poured upon the desolate.

X

10^1In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed unto Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and the thing was true, but the time appointed was long: and he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision.

^2In those days I Daniel was mourning three full weeks.

^3I ate no pleasant bread, neither came flesh nor wine in my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, till three whole weeks were fulfilled.

^4And in the four and twentieth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which is Hiddekel;

^5Then I lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and behold a certain man clothed in linen, whose loins were girded with fine gold of Uphaz:

^6His body also was like the beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as lamps of fire, and his arms and his feet like in colour to polished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude.

^7And I Daniel alone saw the vision: for the men that were with me saw not the vision; but a great quaking fell upon them, so that they fled to hide themselves.

^8Therefore I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me: for my comeliness was turned in me into corruption, and I retained no strength.

^9Yet heard I the voice of his words: and when I heard the voice of his words, then was I in a deep sleep on my face, and my face toward the ground.

^10And, behold, an hand touched me, which set me upon my knees and upon the palms of my hands.

^11And he said unto me, O Daniel, a man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak unto thee, and stand upright: for unto thee am I now sent. And when he had spoken this word unto me, I stood trembling.

^12Then said he unto me, Fear not, Daniel: for from the first day that thou didst set thine heart to understand, and to chasten thyself before thy God, thy words were heard, and I am come for thy words.

^13But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me one and twenty days: but, lo, Michael, one of the chief princes, came to help me; and I remained there with the kings of Persia.

^14Now I am come to make thee understand what shall befall thy people in the latter days: for yet the vision is for many days.

^15And when he had spoken such words unto me, I set my face toward the ground, and I became dumb.

^16And, behold, one like the similitude of the sons of men touched my lips: then I opened my mouth, and spake, and said unto him that stood before me, O my lord, by the vision my sorrows are turned upon me, and I have retained no strength.

^17For how can the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? for as for me, straightway there remained no strength in me, neither is there breath left in me.

^18Then there came again and touched me one like the appearance of a man, and he strengthened me,

^19And said, O man greatly beloved, fear not: peace be unto thee, be strong, yea, be strong. And when he had spoken unto me, I was strengthened, and said, Let my lord speak; for thou hast strengthened me.

^20Then said he, Knowest thou wherefore I come unto thee? and now will I return to fight with the prince of Persia: and when I am gone forth, lo, the prince of Grecia shall come.

^21But I will shew thee that which is noted in the scripture of truth: and there is none that holdeth with me in these things, but Michael your prince.

XI

11^1Also I in the first year of Darius the Mede, even I, stood to confirm and to strengthen him.

^2And now will I shew thee the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia; and the fourth shall be far richer than they all: and by his strength through his riches he shall stir up all against the realm of Grecia.

^3And a mighty king shall stand up, that shall rule with great dominion, and do according to his will.

^4And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken, and shall be divided toward the four winds of heaven; and not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion which he ruled: for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even for others beside those.

^5And the king of the south shall be strong, and one of his princes; and he shall be strong above him, and have dominion; his dominion shall be a great dominion.

^6And in the end of years they shall join themselves together; for the king’s daughter of the south shall come to the king of the north to make an agreement: but she shall not retain the power of the arm; neither shall he stand, nor his arm: but she shall be given up, and they that brought her, and he that begat her, and he that strengthened her in these times.

^7But out of a branch of her roots shall one stand up in his estate, which shall come with an army, and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them, and shall prevail:

^8And shall also carry captives into Egypt their gods, with their princes, and with their precious vessels of silver and of gold; and he shall continue more years than the king of the north.

^9So the king of the south shall come into his kingdom, and shall return into his own land.

^10But his sons shall be stirred up, and shall assemble a multitude of great forces: and one shall certainly come, and overflow, and pass through: then shall he return, and be stirred up, even to his fortress.

^11And the king of the south shall be moved with choler, and shall come forth and fight with him, even with the king of the north: and he shall set forth a great multitude; but the multitude shall be given into his hand.

^12And when he hath taken away the multitude, his heart shall be lifted up; and he shall cast down many ten thousands: but he shall not be strengthened by it.

^13For the king of the north shall return, and shall set forth a multitude greater than the former, and shall certainly come after certain years with a great army and with much riches.

^14And in those times there shall many stand up against the king of the south: also the robbers of thy people shall exalt themselves to establish the vision; but they shall fall.

^15So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mount, and take the most fenced cities: and the arms of the south shall not withstand, neither his chosen people, neither shall there be any strength to withstand.

^16But he that cometh against him shall do according to his own will, and none shall stand before him: and he shall stand in the glorious land, which by his hand shall be consumed.

^17He shall also set his face to enter with the strength of his whole kingdom, and upright ones with him; thus shall he do: and he shall give him the daughter of women, corrupting her: but she shall not stand on his side, neither be for him.

^18After this shall he turn his face unto the isles, and shall take many: but a prince for his own behalf shall cause the reproach offered by him to cease; without his own reproach he shall cause it to turn upon him.

^19Then he shall turn his face toward the fort of his own land: but he shall stumble and fall, and not be found.

^20Then shall stand up in his estate a raiser of taxes in the glory of the kingdom: but within few days he shall be destroyed, neither in anger, nor in battle.

^21And in his estate shall stand up a vile person, to whom they shall not give the honour of the kingdom: but he shall come in peaceably, and obtain the kingdom by flatteries.

^22And with the arms of a flood shall they be overflown from before him, and shall be broken; yea, also the prince of the covenant.

^23And after the league made with him he shall work deceitfully: for he shall come up, and shall become strong with a small people.

^24He shall enter peaceably even upon the fattest places of the province; and he shall do that which his fathers have not done, nor his fathers’ fathers; he shall scatter among them the prey, and spoil, and riches: yea, and he shall forecast his devices against the strong holds, even for a time.

^25And he shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the south with a great army; and the king of the south shall be stirred up to battle with a very great and mighty army; but he shall not stand: for they shall forecast devices against him.

^26Yea, they that feed of the portion of his meat shall destroy him, and his army shall overflow: and many shall fall down slain.

^27And both of these kings’ hearts shall be to do mischief, and they shall speak lies at one table; but it shall not prosper: for yet the end shall be at the time appointed.

^28Then shall he return into his land with great riches; and his heart shall be against the holy covenant; and he shall do exploits, and return to his own land.

^29At the time appointed he shall return, and come toward the south; but it shall not be as the former, or as the latter.

^30For the ships of Chittim shall come against him: therefore he shall be grieved, and return, and have indignation against the holy covenant: so shall he do; he shall even return, and have intelligence with them that forsake the holy covenant.

^31And arms shall stand on his part, and they shall pollute the sanctuary of strength, and shall take away the daily sacrifice, and they shall place the abomination that maketh desolate.

^32And such as do wickedly against the covenant shall he corrupt by flatteries: but the people that do know their God shall be strong, and do exploits.

^33And they that understand among the people shall instruct many: yet they shall fall by the sword, and by flame, by captivity, and by spoil, many days.

^34Now when they shall fall, they shall be holpen with a little help: but many shall cleave to them with flatteries.

^35And some of them of understanding shall fall, to try them, and to purge, and to make them white, even to the time of the end: because it is yet for a time appointed.

^36And the king shall do according to his will; and he shall exalt himself, and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvellous things against the God of gods, and shall prosper till the indignation be accomplished: for that that is determined shall be done.

^37Neither shall he regard the God of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god: for he shall magnify himself above all.

^38But in his estate shall he honour the God of forces: and a god whom his fathers knew not shall he honour with gold, and silver, and with precious stones, and pleasant things.

^39Thus shall he do in the most strong holds with a strange god, whom he shall acknowledge and increase with glory: and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for gain.

^40And at the time of the end shall the king of the south push at him: and the king of the north shall come against him like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with many ships; and he shall enter into the countries, and shall overflow and pass over.

^41He shall enter also into the glorious land, and many countries shall be overthrown: but these shall escape out of his hand, even Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the children of Ammon.

^42He shall stretch forth his hand also upon the countries: and the land of Egypt shall not escape.

^43But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt: and the Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps.

^44But tidings out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him: therefore he shall go forth with great fury to destroy, and utterly to make away many.

^45And he shall plant the tabernacles of his palace between the seas in the glorious holy mountain; yet he shall come to his end, and none shall help him.

XII

12^1And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince which standeth for the children of thy people: and there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation even to that same time: and at that time thy people shall be delivered, every one that shall be found written in the book.

^2And many of them that sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, and some to shame and everlasting contempt.

^3And they that be wise shall shine as the brightness of the firmament; and they that turn many to righteousness as the stars for ever and ever.

^4But thou, O Daniel, shut up the words, and seal the book, even to the time of the end: many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased.

^5Then I Daniel looked, and, behold, there stood other two, the one on this side of the bank of the river, and the other on that side of the bank of the river.

^6And one said to the man clothed in linen, which was upon the waters of the river, How long shall it be to the end of these wonders?

^7And I heard the man clothed in linen, which was upon the waters of the river, when he held up his right hand and his left hand unto heaven, and sware by him that liveth for ever that it shall be for a time, times, and an half; and when he shall have accomplished to scatter the power of the holy people, all these things shall be finished.

^8And I heard, but I understood not: then said I, O my Lord, what shall be the end of these things?

^9And he said, Go thy way, Daniel: for the words are closed up and sealed till the time of the end.

^10Many shall be purified, and made white, and tried; but the wicked shall do wickedly: and none of the wicked shall understand; but the wise shall understand.

^11And from the time that the daily sacrifice shall be taken away, and the abomination that maketh desolate set up, there shall be a thousand two hundred and ninety days.

^12Blessed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thousand three hundred and five and thirty days.

^13But go thou thy way till the end be: for thou shalt rest, and stand in thy lot at the end of the days.

Hosea

The Book of

Hosea

I

^1The word of the Lord that came unto Hosea, the son of Beeri, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, king of Israel.

^2The beginning of the word of the Lord by Hosea. And the Lord said to Hosea, Go, take unto thee a wife of whoredoms and children of whoredoms: for the land hath committed great whoredom, departing from the Lord.

^3So he went and took Gomer the daughter of Diblaim; which conceived, and bare him a son.

^4And the Lord said unto him, Call his name Jezreel; for yet a little while, and I will avenge the blood of Jezreel upon the house of Jehu, and will cause to cease the kingdom of the house of Israel.

^5And it shall come to pass at that day, that I will break the bow of Israel, in the valley of Jezreel.

^6And she conceived again, and bare a daughter. And God said unto him, Call her name Loruhamah: for I will no more have mercy upon the house of Israel; but I will utterly take them away.

^7But I will have mercy upon the house of Judah, and will save them by the Lord their God, and will not save them by bow, nor by sword, nor by battle, by horses, nor by horsemen.

^8Now when she had weaned Loruhamah, she conceived, and bare a son.

^9Then said God, Call his name Loammi: for ye are not my people, and I will not be your God.

^10Yet the number of the children of Israel shall be as the sand of the sea, which cannot be measured nor numbered; and it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said unto them, Ye are not my people, there it shall be said unto them, Ye are the sons of the living God.

^11Then shall the children of Judah and the children of Israel be gathered together, and appoint themselves one head, and they shall come up out of the land: for great shall be the day of Jezreel.

II

^1Say ye unto your brethren, Ammi; and to your sisters, Ruhamah.

^2Plead with your mother, plead: for she is not my wife, neither am I her husband: let her therefore put away her whoredoms out of her sight, and her adulteries from between her breasts;

^3Lest I strip her naked, and set her as in the day that she was born, and make her as a wilderness, and set her like a dry land, and slay her with thirst.

^4And I will not have mercy upon her children; for they be the children of whoredoms.

^5For their mother hath played the harlot: she that conceived them hath done shamefully: for she said, I will go after my lovers, that give me my bread and my water, my wool and my flax, mine oil and my drink.

^6Therefore, behold, I will hedge up thy way with thorns, and make a wall, that she shall not find her paths.

^7And she shall follow after her lovers, but she shall not overtake them; and she shall seek them, but shall not find them: then shall she say, I will go and return to my first husband; for then was it better with me than now.

^8For she did not know that I gave her corn, and wine, and oil, and multiplied her silver and gold, which they prepared for Baal.

^9Therefore will I return, and take away my corn in the time thereof, and my wine in the season thereof, and will recover my wool and my flax given to cover her nakedness.

^10And now will I discover her lewdness in the sight of her lovers, and none shall deliver her out of mine hand.

^11I will also cause all her mirth to cease, her feast days, her new moons, and her sabbaths, and all her solemn feasts.

^12And I will destroy her vines and her fig trees, whereof she hath said, These are my rewards that my lovers have given me: and I will make them a forest, and the beasts of the field shall eat them.

^13And I will visit upon her the days of Baalim, wherein she burned incense to them, and she decked herself with her earrings and her jewels, and she went after her lovers, and forgat me, saith the Lord.

^14Therefore, behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderness, and speak comfortably unto her.

^15And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a door of hope: and she shall sing there, as in the days of her youth, and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt.

^16And it shall be at that day, saith the Lord, that thou shalt call me Ishi; and shalt call me no more Baali.

^17For I will take away the names of Baalim out of her mouth, and they shall no more be remembered by their name.

^18And in that day will I make a covenant for them with the beasts of the field and with the fowls of heaven, and with the creeping things of the ground: and I will break the bow and the sword and the battle out of the earth, and will make them to lie down safely.

^19And I will betroth thee unto me for ever; yea, I will betroth thee unto me in righteousness, and in judgment, and in lovingkindness, and in mercies.

^20I will even betroth thee unto me in faithfulness: and thou shalt know the Lord.

^21And it shall come to pass in that day, I will hear, saith the Lord, I will hear the heavens, and they shall hear the earth;

^22And the earth shall hear the corn, and the wine, and the oil; and they shall hear Jezreel.

^23And I will sow her unto me in the earth; and I will have mercy upon her that had not obtained mercy; and I will say to them which were not my people, Thou art my people; and they shall say, Thou art my God.

III

^1Then said the Lord unto me, Go yet, love a woman beloved of her friend, yet an adulteress, according to the love of the Lord toward the children of Israel, who look to other gods, and love flagons of wine.

^2So I bought her to me for fifteen pieces of silver, and for an homer of barley, and an half homer of barley:

^3And I said unto her, Thou shalt abide for me many days; thou shalt not play the harlot, and thou shalt not be for another man: so will I also be for thee.

^4For the children of Israel shall abide many days without a king, and without a prince, and without a sacrifice, and without an image, and without an ephod, and without teraphim:

^5Afterward shall the children of Israel return, and seek the Lord their God, and David their king; and shall fear the Lord and his goodness in the latter days.

IV

^1Hear the word of the Lord, ye children of Israel: for the Lord hath a controversy with the inhabitants of the land, because there is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the land.

^2By swearing, and lying, and killing, and stealing, and committing adultery, they break out, and blood toucheth blood.

^3Therefore shall the land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein shall languish, with the beasts of the field, and with the fowls of heaven; yea, the fishes of the sea also shall be taken away.

^4Yet let no man strive, nor reprove another: for thy people are as they that strive with the priest.

^5Therefore shalt thou fall in the day, and the prophet also shall fall with thee in the night, and I will destroy thy mother.

^6My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge: because thou hast rejected knowledge, I will also reject thee, that thou shalt be no priest to me: seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God, I will also forget thy children.

^7As they were increased, so they sinned against me: therefore will I change their glory into shame.

^8They eat up the sin of my people, and they set their heart on their iniquity.

^9And there shall be, like people, like priest: and I will punish them for their ways, and reward them their doings.

^10For they shall eat, and not have enough: they shall commit whoredom, and shall not increase: because they have left off to take heed to the Lord.

^11Whoredom and wine and new wine take away the heart.

^12My people ask counsel at their stocks, and their staff declareth unto them: for the spirit of whoredoms hath caused them to err, and they have gone a whoring from under their God.

^13They sacrifice upon the tops of the mountains, and burn incense upon the hills, under oaks and poplars and elms, because the shadow thereof is good: therefore your daughters shall commit whoredom, and your spouses shall commit adultery.

^14I will not punish your daughters when they commit whoredom, nor your spouses when they commit adultery: for themselves are separated with whores, and they sacrifice with harlots: therefore the people that doth not understand shall fall.

^15Though thou, Israel, play the harlot, yet let not Judah offend; and come not ye unto Gilgal, neither go ye up to Bethaven, nor swear, The Lord liveth.

^16For Israel slideth back as a backsliding heifer: now the Lord will feed them as a lamb in a large place.

^17Ephraim is joined to idols: let him alone.

^18Their drink is sour: they have committed whoredom continually: her rulers with shame do love, Give ye.

^19The wind hath bound her up in her wings, and they shall be ashamed because of their sacrifices.

V

^1Hear ye this, O priests; and hearken, ye house of Israel; and give ye ear, O house of the king; for judgment is toward you, because ye have been a snare on Mizpah, and a net spread upon Tabor.

^2And the revolters are profound to make slaughter, though I have been a rebuker of them all.

^3I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me: for now, O Ephraim, thou committest whoredom, and Israel is defiled.

^4They will not frame their doings to turn unto their God: for the spirit of whoredoms is in the midst of them, and they have not known the Lord.

^5And the pride of Israel doth testify to his face: therefore shall Israel and Ephraim fall in their iniquity: Judah also shall fall with them.

^6They shall go with their flocks and with their herds to seek the Lord; but they shall not find him; he hath withdrawn himself from them.

^7They have dealt treacherously against the Lord: for they have begotten strange children: now shall a month devour them with their portions.

^8Blow ye the cornet in Gibeah, and the trumpet in Ramah: cry aloud at Bethaven, after thee, O Benjamin.

^9Ephraim shall be desolate in the day of rebuke: among the tribes of Israel have I made known that which shall surely be.

^10The princes of Judah were like them that remove the bound: therefore I will pour out my wrath upon them like water.

^11Ephraim is oppressed and broken in judgment, because he willingly walked after the commandment.

^12Therefore will I be unto Ephraim as a moth, and to the house of Judah as rottenness.

^13When Ephraim saw his sickness, and Judah saw his wound, then went Ephraim to the Assyrian, and sent to king Jareb: yet could he not heal you, nor cure you of your wound.

^14For I will be unto Ephraim as a lion, and as a young lion to the house of Judah: I, even I, will tear and go away; I will take away, and none shall rescue him.

^15I will go and return to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and seek my face: in their affliction they will seek me early.

VI

^1Come, and let us return unto the Lord: for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath smitten, and he will bind us up.

^2After two days will he revive us: in the third day he will raise us up, and we shall live in his sight.

^3Then shall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord: his going forth is prepared as the morning; and he shall come unto us as the rain, as the latter and former rain unto the earth.

^4O Ephraim, what shall I do unto thee? O Judah, what shall I do unto thee? for your goodness is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away.

^5Therefore have I hewed them by the prophets; I have slain them by the words of my mouth: and thy judgments are as the light that goeth forth.

^6For I desired mercy, and not sacrifice; and the knowledge of God more than burnt offerings.

^7But they like men have transgressed the covenant: there have they dealt treacherously against me.

^8Gilead is a city of them that work iniquity, and is polluted with blood.

^9And as troops of robbers wait for a man, so the company of priests murder in the way by consent: for they commit lewdness.

^10I have seen an horrible thing in the house of Israel: there is the whoredom of Ephraim, Israel is defiled.

^11Also, O Judah, he hath set an harvest for thee, when I returned the captivity of my people.

VII

^1When I would have healed Israel, then the iniquity of Ephraim was discovered, and the wickedness of Samaria: for they commit falsehood; and the thief cometh in, and the troop of robbers spoileth without.

^2And they consider not in their hearts that I remember all their wickedness: now their own doings have beset them about; they are before my face.

^3They make the king glad with their wickedness, and the princes with their lies.

^4They are all adulterers, as an oven heated by the baker, who ceaseth from raising after he hath kneaded the dough, until it be leavened.

^5In the day of our king the princes have made him sick with bottles of wine; he stretched out his hand with scorners.

^6For they have made ready their heart like an oven, whiles they lie in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night; in the morning it burneth as a flaming fire.

^7They are all hot as an oven, and have devoured their judges; all their kings are fallen: there is none among them that calleth unto me.

^8Ephraim, he hath mixed himself among the people; Ephraim is a cake not turned.

^9Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth it not: yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, yet he knoweth not.

^10And the pride of Israel testifieth to his face: and they do not return to the Lord their God, nor seek him for all this.

^11Ephraim also is like a silly dove without heart: they call to Egypt, they go to Assyria.

^12When they shall go, I will spread my net upon them; I will bring them down as the fowls of the heaven; I will chastise them, as their congregation hath heard.

^13Woe unto them! for they have fled from me: destruction unto them! because they have transgressed against me: though I have redeemed them, yet they have spoken lies against me.

^14And they have not cried unto me with their heart, when they howled upon their beds: they assemble themselves for corn and wine, and they rebel against me.

^15Though I have bound and strengthened their arms, yet do they imagine mischief against me.

^16They return, but not to the most High: they are like a deceitful bow: their princes shall fall by the sword for the rage of their tongue: this shall be their derision in the land of Egypt.

VIII

^1Set the trumpet to thy mouth. He shall come as an eagle against the house of the Lord, because they have transgressed my covenant, and trespassed against my law.

^2Israel shall cry unto me, My God, we know thee.

^3Israel hath cast off the thing that is good: the enemy shall pursue him.

^4They have set up kings, but not by me: they have made princes, and I knew it not: of their silver and their gold have they made them idols, that they may be cut off.

^5Thy calf, O Samaria, hath cast thee off; mine anger is kindled against them: how long will it be ere they attain to innocency?

^6For from Israel was it also: the workman made it; therefore it is not God: but the calf of Samaria shall be broken in pieces.

^7For they have sown the wind, and they shall reap the whirlwind: it hath no stalk; the bud shall yield no meal: if so be it yield, the strangers shall swallow it up.

^8Israel is swallowed up: now shall they be among the Gentiles as a vessel wherein is no pleasure.

^9For they are gone up to Assyria, a wild ass alone by himself: Ephraim hath hired lovers.

^10Yea, though they have hired among the nations, now will I gather them, and they shall sorrow a little for the burden of the king of princes.

^11Because Ephraim hath made many altars to sin, altars shall be unto him to sin.

^12I have written to him the great things of my law, but they were counted as a strange thing.

^13They sacrifice flesh for the sacrifices of mine offerings, and eat it; but the Lord accepteth them not; now will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins: they shall return to Egypt.

^14For Israel hath forgotten his Maker, and buildeth temples; and Judah hath multiplied fenced cities: but I will send a fire upon his cities, and it shall devour the palaces thereof.

IX

^1Rejoice not, O Israel, for joy, as other people: for thou hast gone a whoring from thy God, thou hast loved a reward upon every cornfloor.

^2The floor and the winepress shall not feed them, and the new wine shall fail in her.

^3They shall not dwell in the Lord’s land; but Ephraim shall return to Egypt, and they shall eat unclean things in Assyria.

^4They shall not offer wine offerings to the Lord, neither shall they be pleasing unto him: their sacrifices shall be unto them as the bread of mourners; all that eat thereof shall be polluted: for their bread for their soul shall not come into the house of the Lord.

^5What will ye do in the solemn day, and in the day of the feast of the Lord?

^6For, lo, they are gone because of destruction: Egypt shall gather them up, Memphis shall bury them: the pleasant places for their silver, nettles shall possess them: thorns shall be in their tabernacles.

^7The days of visitation are come, the days of recompence are come; Israel shall know it: the prophet is a fool, the spiritual man is mad, for the multitude of thine iniquity, and the great hatred.

^8The watchman of Ephraim was with my God: but the prophet is a snare of a fowler in all his ways, and hatred in the house of his God.

^9They have deeply corrupted themselves, as in the days of Gibeah: therefore he will remember their iniquity, he will visit their sins.

^10I found Israel like grapes in the wilderness; I saw your fathers as the firstripe in the fig tree at her first time: but they went to Baalpeor, and separated themselves unto that shame; and their abominations were according as they loved.

^11As for Ephraim, their glory shall fly away like a bird, from the birth, and from the womb, and from the conception.

^12Though they bring up their children, yet will I bereave them, that there shall not be a man left: yea, woe also to them when I depart from them!

^13Ephraim, as I saw Tyrus, is planted in a pleasant place: but Ephraim shall bring forth his children to the murderer.

^14Give them, O Lord: what wilt thou give? give them a miscarrying womb and dry breasts.

^15All their wickedness is in Gilgal: for there I hated them: for the wickedness of their doings I will drive them out of mine house, I will love them no more: all their princes are revolters.

^16Ephraim is smitten, their root is dried up, they shall bear no fruit: yea, though they bring forth, yet will I slay even the beloved fruit of their womb.

^17My God will cast them away, because they did not hearken unto him: and they shall be wanderers among the nations.

X

^1Israel is an empty vine, he bringeth forth fruit unto himself: according to the multitude of his fruit he hath increased the altars; according to the goodness of his land they have made goodly images.

^2Their heart is divided; now shall they be found faulty: he shall break down their altars, he shall spoil their images.

^3For now they shall say, We have no king, because we feared not the Lord; what then should a king do to us?

^4They have spoken words, swearing falsely in making a covenant: thus judgment springeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field.

^5The inhabitants of Samaria shall fear because of the calves of Bethaven: for the people thereof shall mourn over it, and the priests thereof that rejoiced on it, for the glory thereof, because it is departed from it.

^6It shall be also carried unto Assyria for a present to king Jareb: Ephraim shall receive shame, and Israel shall be ashamed of his own counsel.

^7As for Samaria, her king is cut off as the foam upon the water.

^8The high places also of Aven, the sin of Israel, shall be destroyed: the thorn and the thistle shall come up on their altars; and they shall say to the mountains, Cover us; and to the hills, Fall on us.

^9O Israel, thou hast sinned from the days of Gibeah: there they stood: the battle in Gibeah against the children of iniquity did not overtake them.

^10It is in my desire that I should chastise them; and the people shall be gathered against them, when they shall bind themselves in their two furrows.

^11And Ephraim is as an heifer that is taught, and loveth to tread out the corn; but I passed over upon her fair neck: I will make Ephraim to ride; Judah shall plow, and Jacob shall break his clods.

^12Sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap in mercy; break up your fallow ground: for it is time to seek the Lord, till he come and rain righteousness upon you.

^13Ye have plowed wickedness, ye have reaped iniquity; ye have eaten the fruit of lies: because thou didst trust in thy way, in the multitude of thy mighty men.

^14Therefore shall a tumult arise among thy people, and all thy fortresses shall be spoiled, as Shalman spoiled Betharbel in the day of battle: the mother was dashed in pieces upon her children.

^15So shall Bethel do unto you because of your great wickedness: in a morning shall the king of Israel utterly be cut off.

XI

^1When Israel was a child, then I loved him, and called my son out of Egypt.

^2As they called them, so they went from them: they sacrificed unto Baalim, and burned incense to graven images.

^3I taught Ephraim also to go, taking them by their arms; but they knew not that I healed them.

^4I drew them with cords of a man, with bands of love: and I was to them as they that take off the yoke on their jaws, and I laid meat unto them.

^5He shall not return into the land of Egypt, and the Assyrian shall be his king, because they refused to return.

^6And the sword shall abide on his cities, and shall consume his branches, and devour them, because of their own counsels.

^7And my people are bent to backsliding from me: though they called them to the most High, none at all would exalt him.

^8How shall I give thee up, Ephraim? how shall I deliver thee, Israel? how shall I make thee as Admah? how shall I set thee as Zeboim? mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together.

^9I will not execute the fierceness of mine anger, I will not return to destroy Ephraim: for I am God, and not man; the Holy One in the midst of thee: and I will not enter into the city.

^10They shall walk after the Lord: he shall roar like a lion: when he shall roar, then the children shall tremble from the west.

^11They shall tremble as a bird out of Egypt, and as a dove out of the land of Assyria: and I will place them in their houses, saith the Lord.

^12Ephraim compasseth me about with lies, and the house of Israel with deceit: but Judah yet ruleth with God, and is faithful with the saints.

XII

^1Ephraim feedeth on wind, and followeth after the east wind: he daily increaseth lies and desolation; and they do make a covenant with the Assyrians, and oil is carried into Egypt.

^2The Lord hath also a controversy with Judah, and will punish Jacob according to his ways; according to his doings will he recompense him.

^3He took his brother by the heel in the womb, and by his strength he had power with God:

^4Yea, he had power over the angel, and prevailed: he wept, and made supplication unto him: he found him in Bethel, and there he spake with us;

^5Even the Lord God of hosts; the Lord is his memorial.

^6Therefore turn thou to thy God: keep mercy and judgment and wait on thy God continually.

^7He is a merchant, the balances of deceit are in his hand: he loveth to oppress.

^8And Ephraim said, Yet I am become rich, I have found me out substance: in all my labours they shall find none iniquity in me that were sin.

^9And I that am the Lord thy God from the land of Egypt will yet make thee to dwell in tabernacles, as in the days of the solemn feast.

^10I have also spoken by the prophets, and I have multiplied visions, and used similitudes, by the ministry of the prophets.

^11Is there iniquity in Gilead? surely they are vanity: they sacrifice bullocks in Gilgal; yea, their altars are as heaps in the furrows of the fields.

^12And Jacob fled into the country of Syria, and Israel served for a wife, and for a wife he kept sheep.

^13And by a prophet the Lord brought Israel out of Egypt, and by a prophet was he preserved.

^14Ephraim provoked him to anger most bitterly: therefore shall he leave his blood upon him, and his reproach shall his Lord return unto him.

XIII

^1When Ephraim spake trembling, he exalted himself in Israel; but when he offended in Baal, he died.

^2And now they sin more and more, and have made them molten images of their silver, and idols according to their own understanding, all of it the work of the craftsmen: they say of them, Let the men that sacrifice kiss the calves.

^3Therefore they shall be as the morning cloud and as the early dew that passeth away, as the chaff that is driven with the whirlwind out of the floor, and as the smoke out of the chimney.

^4Yet I am the Lord thy God from the land of Egypt, and thou shalt know no god but me: for there is no saviour beside me.

^5I did know thee in the wilderness, in the land of great drought.

^6According to their pasture, so were they filled; they were filled, and their heart was exalted; therefore have they forgotten me.

^7Therefore I will be unto them as a lion: as a leopard by the way will I observe them:

^8I will meet them as a bear that is bereaved of her whelps, and will rend the caul of their heart, and there will I devour them like a lion: the wild beast shall tear them.

^9O Israel, thou hast destroyed thyself; but in me is thine help.

^10I will be thy king: where is any other that may save thee in all thy cities? and thy judges of whom thou saidst, Give me a king and princes?

^11I gave thee a king in mine anger, and took him away in my wrath.

^12The iniquity of Ephraim is bound up; his sin is hid.

^13The sorrows of a travailing woman shall come upon him: he is an unwise son; for he should not stay long in the place of the breaking forth of children.

^14I will ransom them from the power of the grave; I will redeem them from death: O death, I will be thy plagues; O grave, I will be thy destruction: repentance shall be hid from mine eyes.

^15Though he be fruitful among his brethren, an east wind shall come, the wind of the Lord shall come up from the wilderness, and his spring shall become dry, and his fountain shall be dried up: he shall spoil the treasure of all pleasant vessels.

^16Samaria shall become desolate; for she hath rebelled against her God: they shall fall by the sword: their infants shall be dashed in pieces, and their women with child shall be ripped up.

XIV

^1O israel, return unto the Lord thy God; for thou hast fallen by thine iniquity.

^2Take with you words, and turn to the Lord: say unto him, Take away all iniquity, and receive us graciously: so will we render the calves of our lips.

^3Asshur shall not save us; we will not ride upon horses: neither will we say any more to the work of our hands, Ye are our gods: for in thee the fatherless findeth mercy.

^4I will heal their backsliding, I will love them freely: for mine anger is turned away from him.

^5I will be as the dew unto Israel: he shall grow as the lily, and cast forth his roots as Lebanon.

^6His branches shall spread, and his beauty shall be as the olive tree, and his smell as Lebanon.

^7They that dwell under his shadow shall return; they shall revive as the corn, and grow as the vine: the scent thereof shall be as the wine of Lebanon.

^8Ephraim shall say, What have I to do any more with idols? I have heard him, and observed him: I am like a green fir tree. From me is thy fruit found.

^9Who is wise, and he shall understand these things? prudent, and he shall know them? for the ways of the Lord are right, and the just shall walk in them: but the transgressors shall fall therein.

Book 29 Joel

29:001:001 The word of the Lord that came to Joel the son of Pethuel.

29:001:002 Hear this, ye old men, and give ear, all ye inhabitants of the land. Hath this been in your days, or even in the days of your fathers?

29:001:003 Tell ye your children of it, and let your children tell their children, and their children another generation.

29:001:004 That which the palmerworm hath left hath the locust eaten; and that which the locust hath left hath the cankerworm eaten; and that which the cankerworm hath left hath the caterpiller eaten.

29:001:005 Awake, ye drunkards, and weep; and howl, all ye drinkers of wine, because of the new wine; for it is cut off from your mouth.

29:001:006 For a nation is come up upon my land, strong, and without number, whose teeth are the teeth of a lion, and he hath the cheek teeth of a great lion.

29:001:007 He hath laid my vine waste, and barked my fig tree: he hath made it clean bare, and cast it away; the branches thereof are made white.

29:001:008 Lament like a virgin girded with sackcloth for the husband of her youth.

29:001:009 The meat offering and the drink offering is cut off from the house of the Lord; the priests, the Lord’s ministers, mourn.

29:001:010 The field is wasted, the land mourneth; for the corn is wasted: the new wine is dried up, the oil languisheth.

29:001:011 Be ye ashamed, O ye husbandmen; howl, O ye vinedressers, for the wheat and for the barley; because the harvest of the field is perished.

29:001:012 The vine is dried up, and the fig tree languisheth; the pomegranate tree, the palm tree also, and the apple tree, even all the trees of the field, are withered: because joy is withered away from the sons of men.

29:001:013 Gird yourselves, and lament, ye priests: howl, ye ministers of the altar: come, lie all night in sackcloth, ye ministers of my God: for the meat offering and the drink offering is withholden from the house of your God.

29:001:014 Sanctify ye a fast, call a solemn assembly, gather the elders and all the inhabitants of the land into the house of the Lord your God, and cry unto the Lord,

29:001:015 Alas for the day! for the day of the Lord is at hand, and as a destruction from the Almighty shall it come.

29:001:016 Is not the meat cut off before our eyes, yea, joy and gladness from the house of our God?

29:001:017 The seed is rotten under their clods, the garners are laid desolate, the barns are broken down; for the corn is withered.

29:001:018 How do the beasts groan! the herds of cattle are perplexed, because they have no pasture; yea, the flocks of sheep are made desolate.

29:001:019 O Lord, to thee will I cry: for the fire hath devoured the pastures of the wilderness, and the flame hath burned all the trees of the field.

29:001:020 The beasts of the field cry also unto thee: for the rivers of waters are dried up, and the fire hath devoured the pastures of the wilderness.

29:002:001 Blow ye the trumpet in Zion, and sound an alarm in my holy mountain: let all the inhabitants of the land tremble: for the day of the Lord cometh, for it is nigh at hand;

29:002:002 A day of darkness and of gloominess, a day of clouds and of thick darkness, as the morning spread upon the mountains: a great people and a strong; there hath not been ever the like, neither shall be any more after it, even to the years of many generations.

29:002:003 A fire devoureth before them; and behind them a flame burneth: the land is as the garden of Eden before them, and behind them a desolate wilderness; yea, and nothing shall escape them.

29:002:004 The appearance of them is as the appearance of horses; and as horsemen, so shall they run.

29:002:005 Like the noise of chariots on the tops of mountains shall they leap, like the noise of a flame of fire that devoureth the stubble, as a strong people set in battle array.

29:002:006 Before their face the people shall be much pained: all faces shall gather blackness.

29:002:007 They shall run like mighty men; they shall climb the wall like men of war; and they shall march every one on his ways, and they shall not break their ranks:

29:002:008 Neither shall one thrust another; they shall walk every one in his path: and when they fall upon the sword, they shall not be wounded.

29:002:009 They shall run to and fro in the city; they shall run upon the wall, they shall climb up upon the houses; they shall enter in at the windows like a thief.

29:002:010 The earth shall quake before them; the heavens shall tremble: the sun and the moon shall be dark, and the stars shall withdraw their shining:

29:002:011 And the Lord shall utter his voice before his army: for his camp is very great: for he is strong that executeth his word: for the day of the Lord is great and very terrible; and who can abide it?

29:002:012 Therefore also now, saith the Lord, turn ye even to me with all your heart, and with fasting, and with weeping, and with mourning:

29:002:013 And rend your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto the Lord your God: for he is gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and repenteth him of the evil.

29:002:014 Who knoweth if he will return and repent, and leave a blessing behind him; even a meat offering and a drink offering unto the Lord your God?

29:002:015 Blow the trumpet in Zion, sanctify a fast, call a solemn assembly:

29:002:016 Gather the people, sanctify the congregation, assemble the elders, gather the children, and those that suck the breasts: let the bridegroom go forth of his chamber, and the bride out of her closet.

29:002:017 Let the priests, the ministers of the Lord, weep between the porch and the altar, and let them say, Spare thy people, O Lord, and give not thine heritage to reproach, that the heathen should rule over them: wherefore should they say among the people, Where is their God?

29:002:018 Then will the Lord be jealous for his land, and pity his people.

29:002:019 Yea, the Lord will answer and say unto his people, Behold, I will send you corn, and wine, and oil, and ye shall be satisfied therewith: and I will no more make you a reproach among the heathen:

29:002:020 But I will remove far off from you the northern army, and will drive him into a land barren and desolate, with his face toward the east sea, and his hinder part toward the utmost sea, and his stink shall come up, and his ill savour shall come up, because he hath done great things.

29:002:021 Fear not, O land; be glad and rejoice: for the Lord will do great things.

29:002:022 Be not afraid, ye beasts of the field: for the pastures of the wilderness do spring, for the tree beareth her fruit, the fig tree and the vine do yield their strength.

29:002:023 Be glad then, ye children of Zion, and rejoice in the Lord your God: for he hath given you the former rain moderately, and he will cause to come down for you the rain, the former rain, and the latter rain in the first month.

29:002:024 And the floors shall be full of wheat, and the vats shall overflow with wine and oil.

29:002:025 And I will restore to you the years that the locust hath eaten, the cankerworm, and the caterpiller, and the palmerworm, my great army which I sent among you.

29:002:026 And ye shall eat in plenty, and be satisfied, and praise the name of the Lord your God, that hath dealt wondrously with you: and my people shall never be ashamed.

29:002:027 And ye shall know that I am in the midst of Israel, and that I am the Lord your God, and none else: and my people shall never be ashamed.

29:002:028 And it shall come to pass afterward, that I will pour out my spirit upon all flesh; and your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, your old men shall dream dreams, your young men shall see visions:

29:002:029 And also upon the servants and upon the handmaids in those days will I pour out my spirit.

29:002:030 And I will shew wonders in the heavens and in the earth, blood, and fire, and pillars of smoke.

29:002:031 The sun shall be turned into darkness, and the moon into blood, before the great and terrible day of the Lord come.

29:002:032 And it shall come to pass, that whosoever shall call on the name of the Lord shall be delivered: for in mount Zion and in Jerusalem shall be deliverance, as the Lord hath said, and in the remnant whom the Lord shall call.

29:003:001 For, behold, in those days, and in that time, when I shall bring again the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem,

29:003:002 I will also gather all nations, and will bring them down into the valley of Jehoshaphat, and will plead with them there for my people and for my heritage Israel, whom they have scattered among the nations, and parted my land.

29:003:003 And they have cast lots for my people; and have given a boy for an harlot, and sold a girl for wine, that they might drink.

29:003:004 Yea, and what have ye to do with me, O Tyre, and Zidon, and all the coasts of Palestine? will ye render me a recompence? and if ye recompense me, swiftly and speedily will I return your recompence upon your own head;

29:003:005 Because ye have taken my silver and my gold, and have carried into your temples my goodly pleasant things:

29:003:006 The children also of Judah and the children of Jerusalem have ye sold unto the Grecians, that ye might remove them far from their border.

29:003:007 Behold, I will raise them out of the place whither ye have sold them, and will return your recompence upon your own head:

29:003:008 And I will sell your sons and your daughters into the hand of the children of Judah, and they shall sell them to the Sabeans, to a people far off: for the Lord hath spoken it.

29:003:009 Proclaim ye this among the Gentiles; Prepare war, wake up the mighty men, let all the men of war draw near; let them come up:

29:003:010 Beat your plowshares into swords and your pruninghooks into spears: let the weak say, I am strong.

29:003:011 Assemble yourselves, and come, all ye heathen, and gather yourselves together round about: thither cause thy mighty ones to come down, O Lord.

29:003:012 Let the heathen be wakened, and come up to the valley of Jehoshaphat: for there will I sit to judge all the heathen round about.

29:003:013 Put ye in the sickle, for the harvest is ripe: come, get you down; for the press is full, the fats overflow; for their wickedness is great.

29:003:014 Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision: for the day of the Lord is near in the valley of decision.

29:003:015 The sun and the moon shall be darkened, and the stars shall withdraw their shining.

29:003:016 The Lord also shall roar out of Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the heavens and the earth shall shake: but the Lord will be the hope of his people, and the strength of the children of Israel.

29:003:017 So shall ye know that I am the Lord your God dwelling in Zion, my holy mountain: then shall Jerusalem be holy, and there shall no strangers pass through her any more.

29:003:018 And it shall come to pass in that day, that the mountains shall drop down new wine, and the hills shall flow with milk, and all the rivers of Judah shall flow with waters, and a fountain shall come forth out of the house of the Lord, and shall water the valley of Shittim.

29:003:019 Egypt shall be a desolation, and Edom shall be a desolate wilderness, for the violence against the children of Judah, because they have shed innocent blood in their land.

29:003:020 But Judah shall dwell for ever, and Jerusalem from generation to generation.

29:003:021 For I will cleanse their blood that I have not cleansed: for the Lord dwelleth in Zion.

Obadiah

The Book of

Obadiah

I

^1The vision of Obadiah. Thus saith the Lord God concerning Edom; We have heard a rumour from the Lord, and an ambassador is sent among the heathen, Arise ye, and let us rise up against her in battle.

^2Behold, I have made thee small among the heathen: thou art greatly despised.

^3The pride of thine heart hath deceived thee, thou that dwellest in the clefts of the rock, whose habitation is high; that saith in his heart, Who shall bring me down to the ground?

^4Though thou exalt thyself as the eagle, and though thou set thy nest among the stars, thence will I bring thee down, saith the Lord.

^5If thieves came to thee, if robbers by night, (how art thou cut off!) would they not have stolen till they had enough? if the grapegatherers came to thee, would they not leave some grapes?

^6How are the things of Esau searched out! how are his hidden things sought up!

^7All the men of thy confederacy have brought thee even to the border: the men that were at peace with thee have deceived thee, and prevailed against thee; that they eat thy bread have laid a wound under thee: there is none understanding in him.

^8Shall I not in that day, saith the Lord, even destroy the wise men out of Edom, and understanding out of the mount of Esau?

^9And thy mighty men, O Teman, shall be dismayed, to the end that every one of the mount of Esau may be cut off by slaughter.

^10For thy violence against thy brother Jacob shame shall cover thee, and thou shalt be cut off for ever.

^11In the day that thou stoodest on the other side, in the day that the strangers carried away captive his forces, and foreigners entered into his gates, and cast lots upon Jerusalem, even thou wast as one of them.

^12But thou shouldest not have looked on the day of thy brother in the day that he became a stranger; neither shouldest thou have rejoiced over the children of Judah in the day of their destruction; neither shouldest thou have spoken proudly in the day of distress.

^13Thou shouldest not have entered into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity; yea, thou shouldest not have looked on their affliction in the day of their calamity, nor have laid hands on their substance in the day of their calamity;

^14Neither shouldest thou have stood in the crossway, to cut off those of his that did escape; neither shouldest thou have delivered up those of his that did remain in the day of distress.

^15For the day of the Lord is near upon all the heathen: as thou hast done, it shall be done unto thee: thy reward shall return upon thine own head.

^16For as ye have drunk upon my holy mountain, so shall all the heathen drink continually, yea, they shall drink, and they shall swallow down, and they shall be as though they had not been.

^17But upon mount Zion shall be deliverance, and there shall be holiness; and the house of Jacob shall possess their possessions.

^18And the house of Jacob shall be a fire, and the house of Joseph a flame, and the house of Esau for stubble, and they shall kindle in them, and devour them; and there shall not be any remaining of the house of Esau; for the Lord hath spoken it.

^19And they of the south shall possess the mount of Esau; and they of the plain the Philistines: and they shall possess the fields of Ephraim, and the fields of Samaria: and Benjamin shall possess Gilead.

^20And the captivity of this host of the children of Israel shall possess that of the Canaanites, even unto Zarephath; and the captivity of Jerusalem, which is in Sepharad, shall possess the cities of the south.

^21And saviours shall come up on mount Zion to judge the mount of Esau; and the kingdom shall be the Lord’s.

Jonah

The Book of

Jonah

I

^1Now the word of the Lord came unto Jonah the son of Amittai, saying, ^2Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and cry against it; for their wickedness is come up before me. ^3But Jonah rose up to flee unto Tarshish from the presence of the Lord, and went down to Joppa; and he found a ship going to Tarshish: so he paid the fare thereof, and went down into it, to go with them unto Tarshish from the presence of the Lord.

^4But the Lord sent out a great wind into the sea, and there was a mighty tempest in the sea, so that the ship was like to be broken. ^5Then the mariners were afraid, and cried every man unto his god, and cast forth the wares that were in the ship into the sea, to lighten it of them. But Jonah was gone down into the sides of the ship; and he lay, and was fast asleep. ^6So the shipmaster came to him, and said unto him, What meanest thou, O sleeper? arise, call upon thy God, if so be that God will think upon us, that we perish not. ^7And they said every one to his fellow, Come, and let us cast lots, that we may know for whose cause this evil is upon us. So they cast lots, and the lot fell upon Jonah. ^8Then said they unto him, Tell us, we pray thee, for whose cause this evil is upon us; What is thine occupation? and whence comest thou? what is thy country? and of what people art thou? ^9And he said unto them, I am an Hebrew; and I fear the Lord, the God of heaven, which hath made the sea and the dry land. ^10Then were the men exceedingly afraid, and said unto him. Why hast thou done this? For the men knew that he fled from the presence of the Lord, because he had told them.

^11Then said they unto him, What shall we do unto thee, that the sea may be calm unto us? for the sea wrought, and was tempestuous. ^12And he said unto them, Take me up, and cast me forth into the sea; so shall the sea be calm unto you: for I know that for my sake this great tempest is upon you. ^13Nevertheless the men rowed hard to bring it to the land; but they could not: for the sea wrought, and was tempestuous against them. ^14Wherefore they cried unto the Lord, and said, We beseech thee, O Lord, we beseech thee, let us not perish for this man’s life, and lay not upon us innocent blood: for thou, O Lord, hast done as it pleased thee. ^15So they look up Jonah, and cast him forth into the sea: and the sea ceased from her raging. ^16Then the men feared the Lord exceedingly, and offered a sacrifice unto the Lord, and made vows.

^17Now the Lord had prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah. And Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights.

II

^1Then Jonah prayed unto the Lord his God out of the fish’s belly, ^2and said,

I cried by reason of mine affliction unto the Lord,
And he heard me;
Out of the belly of hell cried I,
And thou heardest my voice.
^3For thou hadst cast me into the deep, in the midst of the seas;
And the floods compassed me about:
All thy billows and thy waves passed over me.
^4Then I said, I am cast out of thy sight;
Yet I will look again toward thy holy temple.
^5The waters compassed me about, even to the soul:
The depth closed me round about,
The weeds were wrapped about my head.
^6I went down to the bottoms of the mountains;
The earth with her bars was about me for ever:
Yet hast thou brought up my life from corruption, O Lord my God.
^7When my soul fainted within me I remembered the Lord:
And my prayer came in unto thee, into thine holy temple.
^8They that observe lying vanities
Forsake their own mercy.
^9But I will sacrifice unto thee with the voice of thanksgiving;
I will pay that that I have vowed.
Salvation is of the Lord.

^10And the Lord spake unto the fish, and it vomited out Jonah upon the dry land.

III

^1And the word of the Lord came unto Jonah the second time, saying, ^2Arise, go unto Nineveh, that great city, and preach unto it the preaching that I bid thee. ^3So Jonah arose, and went unto Nineveh, according to the word of the Lord. Now Nineveh was an exceeding great city of three days’ journey. ^4And Jonah began to enter into the city a day’s journey, and he cried, and said, Yet forty days, and Nineveh shall be overthrown.

^5So the people of Nineveh believed God, and proclaimed a fast, and put on sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least of them. ^6For word came unto the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne, and he laid his robe from him, and covered him with sackcloth, and sat in ashes. ^7And he caused it to be proclaimed and published through Nineveh by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying, Let neither man nor beast, herd nor flock, taste any thing: let them not feed, nor drink water: ^8but let man and beast be covered with sackcloth, and cry mightily unto God: yea, let them turn every one from his evil way, and from the violence that is in their hands. ^9Who can tell if God will turn and repent, and turn away from his fierce anger, that we perish not?

^10And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way; and God repented of the evil, that he had said that he would do unto them; and he did it not.

IV

^1But it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he was very angry. ^2And he prayed unto the Lord, and said, I pray thee, O Lord, was not this my saying, when I was yet in my country? Therefore I fled before unto Tarshish: for I knew that thou art a gracious God, and merciful, slow to anger, and of great kindness, and repentest thee of the evil. ^3Therefore now, O Lord, take, I beseech thee, my life from me; for it is better for me to die than to live. ^4Then said the Lord, Doest thou well to be angry? ^5So Jonah went out of the city, and sat on the east side of the city, and there made him a booth, and sat under it in the shadow, till he might see what would become of the city.

^6And the Lord God prepared a gourd, and made it to come up over Jonah, that it might be a shadow over his head, to deliver him from his grief. So Jonah was exceeding glad of the gourd. ^7But God prepared a worm when the morning rose the next day, and it smote the gourd that it withered. ^8And it came to pass, when the sun did arise, that God prepared a vehement east wind; and the sun beat upon the head of Jonah, that he fainted, and wished in himself to die, and said, It is better for me to die than to live.

^9And God said to Jonah, Doest thou well to be angry for the gourd? And he said, I do well to be angry, even unto death. ^10Then said the Lord, Thou hast had pity on the gourd, for the which thou hast not laboured, neither madest it grow; which came up in a night, and perished in a night: ^11and should not I spare Nineveh, that great city, wherein are more then sixscore thousand persons that cannot discern between their right hand and their left hand; and also much cattle?

Micah

The Book of

Micah

I

^1The word of the Lord that came to Micah the Morasthite in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem.

^2Hear, all ye people; hearken, O earth, and all that therein is: and let the Lord God be witness against you, the Lord from his holy temple. ^3For, behold, the Lord cometh forth out of his place, and will come down, and tread upon the high places of the earth. ^4And the mountains shall be molten under him, and the valleys shall be cleft, as wax before the fire, and as the waters that are poured down a steep place. ^5For the transgression of Jacob is all this, and for the sins of the house of Israel. What is the transgression of Jacob? is it not Samaria? and what are the high places of Judah? are they not Jerusalem? ^6Therefore I will make Samaria as an heap of the field, and as plantings of a vineyard: and I will pour down the stones thereof into the valley, and I will discover the foundations thereof. ^7And all the graven images thereof shall be beaten to pieces, and all the hires thereof shall be burned with the fire, and all the idols thereof will I lay desolate: for she gathered it of the hire of an harlot, and they shall return to the hire of an harlot. ^8Therefore I will wail and howl, I will go stripped and naked: I will make a wailing like the dragons, and mourning as the owls. ^9For her wound is incurable; for it is come unto Judah; he is come unto the gate of my people, even to Jerusalem.

^10Declare ye it not at Gath, weep ye not at all: in the house of Aphrah roll thyself in the dust. ^11Pass ye away, thou inhabitant of Saphir, having thy shame naked: the inhabitant of Zaanan came not forth in the mourning of Bethezel; he shall receive of you his standing. ^12For the inhabitant of Maroth waited carefully for good: but evil came down from the Lord unto the gate of Jerusalem. ^13O thou inhabitant of Lachish, bind the chariot to the swift beast: she is the beginning of the sin to the daughter of Zion: for the transgressions of Israel were found in thee. ^14Therefore shalt thou give presents to Moreshethgath: the houses of Achzib shall be a lie to the kings of Israel. ^15Yet will I bring an heir unto thee, O inhabitant of Mareshah: he shall come unto Adullam the glory of Israel. ^16Make thee bald, and poll thee for thy delicate children; enlarge thy baldness as the eagle; for they are gone into captivity from thee.

II

^1Woe to them that devise iniquity, and work evil upon their beds! when the morning is light, they practise it, because it is in the power of their hand. ^2And they covet fields, and take them by violence; and houses, and take them away: so they oppress a man and his house, even a man and his heritage. ^3Therefore thus saith the Lord; Behold, against this family do I devise an evil, from which ye shall not remove your necks; neither shall ye go haughtily: for this time is evil.

^4In that day shall one take up a parable against you, and lament with a doleful lamentation, and say, We be utterly spoiled: he hath changed the portion of my people: how hath he removed it from me! turning away he hath divided our fields. ^5Therefore thou shalt have none that shall cast a cord by lot in the congregation of the Lord. ^6Prophesy ye not, say they to them that prophesy: they shall not prophesy to them, that they shall not take shame.

^7O thou that art named the house of Jacob, is the spirit of the Lord straitened? are these his doings? do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly? ^8Even of late my people is risen up as an enemy: ye pull off the robe with the garment from them that pass by securely as men averse from war. ^9The women of my people have ye cast out from their pleasant houses; from their children have ye taken away my glory for ever. ^10Arise ye, and depart; for this is not your rest: because it is polluted, it shall destroy you, even with a sore destruction. ^11If a man walking in the spirit and falsehood do lie, saying, I will prophesy unto thee of wine and of strong drink; he shall even be the prophet of this people.

^12I will surely assemble, O Jacob, all of thee; I will surely gather the remnant of Israel; I will put them together as the sheep of Bozrah, as the flock in the midst of their fold: they shall make great noise by reason of the multitude of men. ^13The breaker is come up before them: they have broken up, and have passed through the gate, and are gone out by it: and their king shall pass before them, and the Lord on the head of them.

III

^1And I said, Hear, I pray you, O heads of Jacob, and ye princes of the house of Israel; Is it not for you to know judgment? ^2Who hate the good, and love the evil; who pluck off their skin from off them, and their flesh from off their bones; ^3who also eat the flesh of my people, and flay their skin from off them; and they break their bones, and chop them in pieces, as for the pot, and as flesh within the caldron. ^4Then shall they cry unto the Lord, but he will not hear them: he will even hide his face from them at that time, as they have behaved themselves ill in their doings.

^5Thus saith the Lord concerning the prophets that make my people err, that bite with their teeth, and cry, Peace; and he that putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare war against him. ^6Therefore night shall be unto you, that ye shall not have a vision; and it shall be dark unto you, that ye shall not divine; and the sun shall go down over the prophets, and the day shall be dark over them. ^7Then shall the seers be ashamed, and the diviners confounded: yea, they shall all cover their lips; for there is no answer of God.

^8But truly I am full of power by the spirit of the Lord, and of judgment, and of might, to declare unto Jacob his transgression, and to Israel his sin.

^9Hear this, I pray you, ye heads of the house of Jacob, and princes of the house of Israel, that abhor judgment, and pervert all equity. ^10They build up Zion with blood, and Jerusalem with iniquity. ^11The heads thereof judge for reward, and the priests thereof teach for hire, and the prophets thereof divine for money: yet will they lean upon the Lord, and say, Is not the Lord among us? none evil can come upon us. ^12Therefore shall Zion for your sake be plowed as a field, and Jerusalem shall become heaps, and the mountain of the house as the high places of the forest.

IV

^1But in the last days it shall come to pass, that the mountain of the house of the Lord shall be established in the top of the mountains, and it shall be exalted above the hills; and people shall flow unto it. ^2And many nations shall come, and say, Come, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, and to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths: for the law shall go forth of Zion, and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem. ^3And he shall judge among many people, and rebuke strong nations afar off; and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruninghooks: nation shall not lift up a sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more. ^4But they shall sit every man under his vine and under his fig tree; and none shall make them afraid: for the mouth of the Lord of hosts hath spoken it. ^5For all people will walk every one in the name of his god, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever and ever.

^6In that day, saith the Lord, will I assemble her that halteth, and I will gather her that is driven out, and her that I have afflicted; ^7and I will make her that halted a remnant, and her that was cast far off a strong nation: and the Lord shall reign over them in mount Zion from henceforth, even for ever. ^8And thou, O tower of the flock, the strong hold of the daughter of Zion, unto thee shall it come, even the first dominion; the kingdom shall come to the daughter of Jerusalem.

^9Now why dost thou cry out aloud? is there no king in thee? is thy counsellor perished? for pangs have taken thee as a woman in travail. ^10Be in pain, and labour to bring forth, O daughter of Zion, like a woman in travail: for now shalt thou go forth out of the city, and thou shalt dwell in the field, and thou shalt go even to Babylon; there shalt thou be delivered; there the Lord shall redeem thee from the hand of thine enemies.

^11Now also many nations are gathered against thee, that say, Let her be defiled, and let our eye look upon Zion. ^12But they know not the thoughts of the Lord, neither understand they his counsel: for he shall gather them as the sheaves into the floor. ^13Arise and thresh, O daughter of Zion: for I will make thine horn iron, and I will make thy hoofs brass: and thou shalt beat in pieces many people: and I will consecrate their gain unto the Lord, and their substance unto the Lord of the whole earth.

V

^1Now gather thyself in troops, O daughter of troops: he hath laid siege against us: they shall smite the judge of Israel with a rod upon the cheek.

^2But thou, Bethlehem Ephratah, though thou be little among the thousands of Judah, yet out of thee shall he come forth unto me that is to be ruler in Israel; whose goings forth have been from of old, from everlasting. ^3Therefore will he give them up, until the time that she which travaileth hath brought forth: then the remnant of his brethren shall return unto the children of Israel. ^4And he shall stand and feed in the strength of the Lord, in the majesty of the name of the Lord his God; and they shall abide: for now shall he be great unto the ends of the earth.

^5And this man shall be the peace, when the Assyrian shall come into our land: and when he shall tread in our palaces, then shall we raise against him seven shepherds, and eight principal men. ^6And they shall waste the land of Assyria with the sword, and the land of Nimrod in the entrances thereof: thus shall he deliver us from the Assyrian, when he cometh into our land, and when he treadeth within our borders.

^7And the remnant of Jacob shall be in the midst of many people as a dew from the Lord, as the showers upon the grass, that tarrieth not for man, nor waiteth for the sons of men. ^8And the remnant of Jacob shall be among the Gentiles in the midst of many people as a lion among the beasts of the forest, as a young lion among the flocks of sheep: who, if he go through, both treadeth down, and teareth in pieces, and none can deliver. ^9Thine hand shall be lifted up upon thine adversaries, and all thine enemies shall be cut off.

^10And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord, that I will cut off thy horses out of the midst of thee, and I will destroy thy chariots: ^11and I will cut off the cities of thy land, and throw down all thy strong holds: ^12and I will cut off witchcrafts out of thine hand; and thou shalt have no more soothsayers: ^13thy graven images also will I cut off, and thy standing images out of the midst of thee; and thou shalt no more worship the work of thine hands. ^14And I will pluck up thy groves out of the midst of thee: so will I destroy thy cities. ^15And I will execute vengeance in anger and fury upon the heathen, such as they have not heard.

VI

^1Hear ye now what the Lord saith; Arise, contend thou before the mountains, and let the hills hear thy voice. ^2Hear ye, O mountains, the Lord’s controversy, and ye strong foundations of the earth: for the Lord hath a controversy with his people, and he will plead with Israel. ^3O my people, what have I done unto thee? and wherein have I wearied thee? testify against me. ^4For I brought thee up out of the land of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the house of servants; and I sent before thee Moses, Aaron, and Miriam. ^5O my people, remember now what Balak king of Moab consulted, and what Balaam the son of Beor answered him from Shittim unto Gilgal; that ye may know the righteousness of the Lord.

^6Wherewith shall I come before the Lord, and bow myself before the high God? shall I come before him with burnt offerings, with calves of a year old? ^7Will the Lord be pleased with thousands of rams, or with ten thousands of rivers of oil? shall I give my firstborn for my transgression, the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul? ^8He hath shewed thee, O man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do justly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?

^9The Lord’s voice crieth unto the city, and the man of wisdom shall see thy name: hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it. ^10Are there yet the treasures of wickedness in the house of the wicked, and the scant measure that is abominable? ^11Shall I count them pure with the wicked balances, and with the bag of deceitful weights? ^12For the rich men thereof are full of violence, and the inhabitants thereof have spoken lies, and their tongue is deceitful in their mouth. ^13Therefore also will I make thee sick in smiting thee, in making thee desolate because of thy sins. ^14Thou shalt eat, but not be satisfied; and thy casting down shall be in the midst of thee; and thou shalt take hold, but shalt not deliver; and that which thou deliverest will I give up to the sword. ^15Thou shalt sow, but thou shalt not reap; thou shalt tread the olives, but thou shalt not anoint thee with oil; and sweet wine, but shalt not drink wine.

^16For the statutes of Omri are kept, and all the works of the house of Ahab, and ye walk in their counsels; that I should make thee a desolation, and the inhabitants thereof an hissing: therefore ye shall bear the reproach of my people.

VII

^1Woe is me! for I am as when they have gathered the summer fruits, as the grapegleanings of the vintage: there is no cluster to eat: my soul desired the firstripe fruit. ^2The good man is perished out of the earth: and there is none upright among men: they all lie in wait for blood; they hunt every man his brother with a net. ^3That they may do evil with both hands earnestly, the prince asketh, and the judge asketh for a reward; and the great man, he uttereth his mischievous desire: so they wrap it up. ^4The best of them is as a brier: the most upright is sharper than a thorn hedge: the day of thy watchmen and thy visitation cometh; now shall be their perplexity. ^5Trust ye not in a friend, put ye not confidence in a guide: keep the doors of thy mouth from her that lieth in thy bosom. ^6For the son dishonoureth the father, the daughter riseth up against her mother, the daughter in law against her mother in law; a man’s enemies are the men of his own house.

^7Therefore I will look unto the Lord; I will wait for the God of my salvation: my God will hear me. ^8Rejoice not against me, O mine enemy: when I fall, I shall arise; when I sit in darkness, the Lord shall be a light unto me. ^9I will bear the indignation of the Lord, because I have sinned against him, until he plead my cause, and execute judgment for me: he will bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his righteousness. ^10Then she that is mine enemy shall see it, and shame shall cover her which said unto me, Where is the Lord thy God? mine eyes shall behold her: now shall she be trodden down as the mire of the streets.

^11In the day that thy walls are to be built, in that day shall the decree be far removed. ^12In that day also he shall come even to thee from Assyria, and from the fortified cities, and from the fortress even to the river, and from sea to sea, and from mountain to mountain. ^13Notwithstanding the land shall be desolate because of them that dwell therein, for the fruit of their doings.

^14Feed thy people with thy rod, the flock of thine heritage, which dwell solitarily in the wood, in the midst of Carmel: let them feed in Bashan and Gilead, as in the days of old. ^15According to the days of thy coming out of the land of Egypt will I shew unto him marvellous things. ^16The nations shall see and be confounded at all their might: they shall lay their hand upon their mouth, their ears shall be deaf. ^17They shall lick the dust like a serpent, they shall move out of their holes like worms of the earth: they shall be afraid of the Lord our God, and shall fear because of thee.

^18Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and passeth by the transgression of the remnant of his heritage? he retaineth not his anger for ever, because he delighteth in mercy. ^19He will turn again, he will have compassion upon us; he will subdue our iniquities; and thou wilt cast all their sins into the depths of the sea. ^20Thou wilt perform the truth to Jacob, and the mercy to Abraham, which thou hast sworn unto our fathers from the days of old.

Nahum

The Book of

Nahum

I

1^1The burden of Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.

^2God is jealous, and the Lord revengeth; the Lord revengeth, and is furious; the Lord will take vengeance on his adversaries, and he reserveth wrath for his enemies.

^3The Lord is slow to anger, and great in power, and will not at all acquit the wicked: the Lord hath his way in the whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds are the dust of his feet.

^4He rebuketh the sea, and maketh it dry, and drieth up all the rivers: Bashan languisheth, and Carmel, and the flower of Lebanon languisheth.

^5The mountains quake at him, and the hills melt, and the earth is burned at his presence, yea, the world, and all that dwell therein.

^6Who can stand before his indignation? and who can abide in the fierceness of his anger? his fury is poured out like fire, and the rocks are thrown down by him.

^7The Lord is good, a strong hold in the day of trouble; and he knoweth them that trust in him.

^8But with an overrunning flood he will make an utter end of the place thereof, and darkness shall pursue his enemies.

^9What do ye imagine against the Lord? he will make an utter end: affliction shall not rise up the second time.

^10For while they be folden together as thorns, and while they are drunken as drunkards, they shall be devoured as stubble fully dry.

^11There is one come out of thee, that imagineth evil against the Lord, a wicked counsellor.

^12Thus saith the Lord; Though they be quiet, and likewise many, yet thus shall they be cut down, when he shall pass through. Though I have afflicted thee, I will afflict thee no more.

^13For now will I break his yoke from off thee, and will burst thy bonds in sunder.

^14And the Lord hath given a commandment concerning thee, that no more of thy name be sown: out of the house of thy gods will I cut off the graven image and the molten image: I will make thy grave; for thou art vile.

^15Behold upon the mountains the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace! O Judah, keep thy solemn feasts, perform thy vows: for the wicked shall no more pass through thee; he is utterly cut off.

II

2^1He that dasheth in pieces is come up before thy face: keep the munition, watch the way, make thy loins strong, fortify thy power mightily.

^2For the Lord hath turned away the excellency of Jacob, as the excellency of Israel: for the emptiers have emptied them out, and marred their vine branches.

^3The shield of his mighty men is made red, the valiant men are in scarlet: the chariots shall be with flaming torches in the day of his preparation, and the fir trees shall be terribly shaken.

^4The chariots shall rage in the streets, they shall justle one against another in the broad ways: they shall seem like torches, they shall run like the lightnings.

^5He shall recount his worthies: they shall stumble in their walk; they shall make haste to the wall thereof, and the defence shall be prepared.

^6The gates of the rivers shall be opened, and the palace shall be dissolved.

^7And Huzzab shall be led away captive, she shall be brought up, and her maids shall lead her as with the voice of doves, tabering upon their breasts.

^8But Nineveh is of old like a pool of water: yet they shall flee away. Stand, stand, shall they cry; but none shall look back.

^9Take ye the spoil of silver, take the spoil of gold: for there is none end of the store and glory out of all the pleasant furniture.

^10She is empty, and void, and waste: and the heart melteth, and the knees smite together, and much pain is in all loins, and the faces of them all gather blackness.

^11Where is the dwelling of the lions, and the feedingplace of the young lions, where the lion, even the old lion, walked, and the lion’s whelp, and none made them afraid?

^12The lion did tear in pieces enough for his whelps, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his holes with prey, and his dens with ravin.

^13Behold, I am against thee, saith the Lord of hosts, and I will burn her chariots in the smoke, and the sword shall devour thy young lions: and I will cut off thy prey from the earth, and the voice of thy messengers shall no more be heard.

III

3^1Woe to the bloody city! it is all full of lies and robbery; the prey departeth not;

^2The noise of a whip, and the noise of the rattling of the wheels, and of the pransing horses, and of the jumping chariots.

^3The horseman lifteth up both the bright sword and the glittering spear: and there is a multitude of slain, and a great number of carcases; and there is none end of their corpses; they stumble upon their corpses:

^4Because of the multitude of the whoredoms of the wellfavoured harlot, the mistress of witchcrafts, that selleth nations through her whoredoms, and families through her witchcrafts.

^5Behold, I am against thee, saith the Lord of hosts; and I will discover thy skirts upon thy face, and I will shew the nations thy nakedness, and the kingdoms thy shame.

^6And I will cast abominable filth upon thee, and make thee vile, and will set thee as a gazingstock.

^7And it shall come to pass, that all they that look upon thee shall flee from thee, and say, Nineveh is laid waste: who will bemoan her? whence shall I seek comforters for thee?

^8Art thou better than populous No, that was situate among the rivers, that had the waters round about it, whose rampart was the sea, and her wall was from the sea?

^9Ethiopia and Egypt were her strength, and it was infinite; Put and Lubim were thy helpers.

^10Yet was she carried away, she went into captivity: her young children also were dashed in pieces at the top of all the streets: and they cast lots for her honourable men, and all her great men were bound in chains.

^11Thou also shalt be drunken: thou shalt be hid, thou also shalt seek strength because of the enemy.

^12All thy strong holds shall be like fig trees with the firstripe figs: if they be shaken, they shall even fall into the mouth of the eater.

^13Behold, thy people in the midst of thee are women: the gates of thy land shall be set wide open unto thine enemies: the fire shall devour thy bars.

^14Draw thee waters for the siege, fortify thy strong holds: go into clay, and tread the morter, make strong the brickkiln.

^15There shall the fire devour thee; the sword shall cut thee off, it shall eat thee up like the cankerworm: make thyself many as the cankerworm, make thyself many as the locusts.

^16Thou hast multiplied thy merchants above the stars of heaven: the cankerworm spoileth, and fleeth away.

^17Thy crowned are as the locusts, and thy captains as the great grasshoppers, which camp in the hedges in the cold day, but when the sun ariseth they flee away, and their place is not known where they are.

^18Thy shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria: thy nobles shall dwell in the dust: thy people is scattered upon the mountains, and no man gathereth them.

^19There is no healing of thy bruise; thy wound is grievous: all that hear the bruit of thee shall clap the hands over thee: for upon whom hath not thy wickedness passed continually?

Habakkuk

The Book of

Habakkuk

I

1^1The burden which Habakkuk the prophet did see. ^2O Lord, how long shall I cry, and thou wilt not hear! even cry out unto thee of violence, and thou wilt not save! ^3Why dost thou shew me iniquity, and cause me to behold grievance? for spoiling and violence are before me: and there are that raise up strife and contention. ^4Therefore the law is slacked, and judgment doth never go forth: for the wicked doth compass about the righteous; therefore wrong judgment proceedeth.

^5Behold ye among the heathen, and regard, and wonder marvelously: for I will work a work in your days which ye will not believe, though it be told you. ^6For, lo, I raise up the Chaldeans, that bitter and hasty nation, which shall march through the breadth of the land, to possess the dwellingplaces that are not their’s. ^7They are terrible and dreadful: their judgment and their dignity shall proceed of themselves. ^8Their horses also are swifter than the leopards, and are more fierce than the evening wolves: and their horsemen shall spread themselves, and their horsemen shall come from far; they shall fly as the eagle that hasteth to eat.

^9They shall come all for violence: their faces shall sup up as the east wind, and they shall gather the captivity as the sand. ^10And they shall scoff at the kings, and the princes shall be a scorn unto them: they shall deride every strong hold; for they shall heap dust, and take it. ^11Then shall his mind change, and he shall pass over, and offend, imputing this his power unto his god.

^12Art thou not from everlasting, O Lord my God, mine Holy One? we shall not die. O Lord, thou hast ordained them for judgment; and, O mighty God, thou hast established them for correction. ^13Thou art of purer eyes than to behold evil, and canst not look on iniquity: wherefore lookest thou upon them that deal treacherously, and holdest thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than he? ^14And makest men as the fishes of the sea, as the creeping things, that have no ruler over them?

^15They take up all of them with the angle, they catch them in their net, and gather them in their drag: therefore they rejoice and are glad. ^16Therefore they sacrifice unto their net, and burn incense unto their drag; because by them their portion is fat, and their meat plenteous. ^17Shall they therefore empty their net, and not spare continually to slay the nations?

II

2^1I will stand upon my watch, and set me upon the tower, and will watch to see what he will say unto me, and what I shall answer when I am reproved. ^2And the Lord answered me, and said, Write the vision, and make it plain upon tables, that he may run that readeth it. ^3For the vision is yet for an appointed time, but at the end it shall speak, and not lie: though it tarry, wait for it; because it will surely come, it will not tarry. ^4Behold, his soul which is lifted up is not upright in him: but the just shall live by his faith.

^5Yea also, because he transgresseth by wine, he is a proud man, neither keepeth at home, who enlargeth his desire as hell, and is as death, and cannot be satisfied, but gathereth unto him all nations, and heapeth unto him all people: ^6shall not all these take up a parable against him, and a taunting proverb against him, and say, Woe to him that increaseth that which is not his! how long? and to him that ladeth himself with thick clay! ^7Shall they not rise up suddenly that shall bite thee, and awake that shall vex thee, and thou shalt be for booties unto them? ^8Because thou hast spoiled many nations, all the remnant of the people shall spoil thee; because of men’s blood, and for the violence of the land, of the city, and of all that dwell therein.

^9Woe to him that coveteth an evil covetousness to his house, that he may set his nest on high, that he may be delivered from the power of evil! ^10Thou hast consulted shame to thy house by cutting off many people, and hast sinned against thy soul. ^11For the stone shall cry out of the wall, and the beam out of the timber shall answer it.

^12Woe to him that buildeth a town with blood, and stablisheth a city by iniquity! ^13Behold, is it not of the Lord of hosts that the people shall labour in the very fire, and the people shall weary themselves for very vanity? ^14For the earth shall be filled with the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the waters cover the sea.

^15Woe unto him that giveth his neighbour drink, that puttest thy bottle to him, and makest him drunken also, that thou mayest look on their nakedness! ^16Thou art filled with shame for glory: drink thou also, and let thy foreskin be uncovered: the cup of the Lord’s right hand shall be turned unto thee, and shameful spewing shall be on thy glory. ^17For the violence of Lebanon shall cover thee, and the spoil of beasts, which made them afraid, because of men’s blood, and for the violence of the land, of the city, and of all that dwell therein.

^18What profiteth the graven image that the maker thereof hath graven it; the molten image, and a teacher of lies, that the maker of his work trusteth therein, to make dumb idols? ^19Woe unto him that saith to the wood, Awake; to the dumb stone, Arise, it shall teach! Behold, it is laid over with gold and silver, and there is no breath at all in the midst of it. ^20But the Lord is in his holy temple: let all the earth keep silence before him.

III

3^1A prayer of Habakkuk the prophet upon Shigionoth.

^2O Lord, I have heard thy speech, and was afraid:
O Lord, revive thy work in the midst of the years,
In the midst of the years make known;
In wrath remember mercy.
^3God came from Teman,
And the Holy One from mount Paran.
Selah.
His glory covered the heavens,
And the earth was full of his praise.
^4And his brightness was as the light;
He had horns coming out of his hand:
And there was the hiding of his power.
^5Before him went the pestilence,
And burning coals went forth at his feet.
^6He stood, and measured the earth:
He beheld, and drove asunder the nations;
And the everlasting mountains were scattered,
The perpetual hills did bow:
His ways are everlasting.
^7I saw the tents of Cushan in affliction:
And the curtains of the land of Midian did tremble.
^8Was the Lord displeased against the rivers?
Was thine anger against the rivers?
Was thy wrath against the sea,
That thou didst ride upon thine horses
And thy chariots of salvation?
^9Thy bow was made quite naked,
According to the oaths of the tribes, even thy word.
Selah.
Thou didst cleave the earth with rivers.
^10The mountains saw thee, and they trembled:
The overflowing of the water passed by:
The deep uttered his voice,
And lifted up his hands on high.
^11The sun and moon stood still in their habitation:
At the light of thine arrows they went,
And at the shining of thy glittering spear.
^12Thou didst march through the land in indignation,
Thou didst thresh the heathen in anger.
^13Thou wentest forth for the salvation of thy people,
Even for salvation with thine anointed;
Thou woundedst the head out of the house of the wicked,
By discovering the foundation unto the neck.
Selah.
^14Thou didst strike through with his staves the head of his villages:
They came out as a whirlwind to scatter me:
Their rejoicing was as to devour the poor secretly.
^15Thou didst walk through the sea with thine horses,
Through the heap of great waters.

^16When I heard, my belly trembled;
My lips quivered at the voice:
Rottenness entered into my bones, and I trembled in myself,
That I might rest in the day of trouble:
When he cometh up unto the people,
He will invade them with his troops.
^17Although the fig tree shall not blossom,
Neither shall fruit be in the vines;
The labour of the olive shall fail,
And the fields shall yield no meat;
The flock shall be cut off from the fold,
And there shall be no herd in the stalls:
^18Yet I will rejoice in the Lord,
I will joy in the God of my salvation.
^19The Lord God is my strength,
And he will make my feet like hinds’ feet,
And he will make me to walk upon mine high places.

To the chief singer on my stringed instruments.

Book 36 Zephaniah

36:001:001 The word of the Lord which came unto Zephaniah the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hizkiah, in the days of Josiah the son of Amon, king of Judah.

36:001:002 I will utterly consume all things from off the land, saith the Lord.

36:001:003 I will consume man and beast; I will consume the fowls of the heaven, and the fishes of the sea, and the stumblingblocks with the wicked: and I will cut off man from off the land, saith the Lord.

36:001:004 I will also stretch out mine hand upon Judah, and upon all the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place, and the name of the Chemarims with the priests;

36:001:005 And them that worship the host of heaven upon the housetops; and them that worship and that swear by the Lord, and that swear by Malcham;

36:001:006 And them that are turned back from the Lord; and those that have not sought the Lord, nor enquired for him.

36:001:007 Hold thy peace at the presence of the Lord God: for the day of the Lord is at hand: for the Lord hath prepared a sacrifice, he hath bid his guests.

36:001:008 And it shall come to pass in the day of the Lord’s sacrifice, that I will punish the princes, and the king’s children, and all such as are clothed with strange apparel.

36:001:009 In the same day also will I punish all those that leap on the threshold, which fill their masters’ houses with violence and deceit.

36:001:010 And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord, that there shall be the noise of a cry from the fish gate, and an howling from the second, and a great crashing from the hills.

36:001:011 Howl, ye inhabitants of Maktesh, for all the merchant people are cut down; all they that bear silver are cut off.

36:001:012 And it shall come to pass at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with candles, and punish the men that are settled on their lees: that say in their heart, The Lord will not do good, neither will he do evil.

36:001:013 Therefore their goods shall become a booty, and their houses a desolation: they shall also build houses, but not inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, but not drink the wine thereof.

36:001:014 The great day of the Lord is near, it is near, and hasteth greatly, even the voice of the day of the Lord: the mighty man shall cry there bitterly.

36:001:015 That day is a day of wrath, a day of trouble and distress, a day of wasteness and desolation, a day of darkness and gloominess, a day of clouds and thick darkness,

36:001:016 A day of the trumpet and alarm against the fenced cities, and against the high towers.

36:001:017 And I will bring distress upon men, that they shall walk like blind men, because they have sinned against the Lord: and their blood shall be poured out as dust, and their flesh as the dung.

36:001:018 Neither their silver nor their gold shall be able to deliver them in the day of the Lord’s wrath; but the whole land shall be devoured by the fire of his jealousy: for he shall make even a speedy riddance of all them that dwell in the land.

36:002:001 Gather yourselves together, yea, gather together, O nation not desired;

36:002:002 Before the decree bring forth, before the day pass as the chaff, before the fierce anger of the Lord come upon you, before the day of the Lord’s anger come upon you.

36:002:003 Seek ye the Lord, all ye meek of the earth, which have wrought his judgment; seek righteousness, seek meekness: it may be ye shall be hid in the day of the Lord’s anger.

36:002:004 For Gaza shall be forsaken, and Ashkelon a desolation: they shall drive out Ashdod at the noon day, and Ekron shall be rooted up.

36:002:005 Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea coast, the nation of the Cherethites! the word of the Lord is against you; O Canaan, the land of the Philistines, I will even destroy thee, that there shall be no inhabitant.

36:002:006 And the sea coast shall be dwellings and cottages for shepherds, and folds for flocks.

36:002:007 And the coast shall be for the remnant of the house of Judah; they shall feed thereupon: in the houses of Ashkelon shall they lie down in the evening: for the Lord their God shall visit them, and turn away their captivity.

36:002:008 I have heard the reproach of Moab, and the revilings of the children of Ammon, whereby they have reproached my people, and magnified themselves against their border.

36:002:009 Therefore as I live, saith the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, Surely Moab shall be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, even the breeding of nettles, and saltpits, and a perpetual desolation: the residue of my people shall spoil them, and the remnant of my people shall possess them.

36:002:010 This shall they have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of the Lord of hosts.

36:002:011 The Lord will be terrible unto them: for he will famish all the gods of the earth; and men shall worship him, every one from his place, even all the isles of the heathen.

36:002:012 Ye Ethiopians also, ye shall be slain by my sword.

36:002:013 And he will stretch out his hand against the north, and destroy Assyria; and will make Nineveh a desolation, and dry like a wilderness.

36:002:014 And flocks shall lie down in the midst of her, all the beasts of the nations: both the cormorant and the bittern shall lodge in the upper lintels of it; their voice shall sing in the windows; desolation shall be in the thresholds; for he shall uncover the cedar work.

36:002:015 This is the rejoicing city that dwelt carelessly, that said in her heart, I am, and there is none beside me: how is she become a desolation, a place for beasts to lie down in! every one that passeth by her shall hiss, and wag his hand.

36:003:001 Woe to her that is filthy and polluted, to the oppressing city!

36:003:002 She obeyed not the voice; she received not correction; she trusted not in the Lord; she drew not near to her God.

36:003:003 Her princes within her are roaring lions; her judges are evening wolves; they gnaw not the bones till the morrow.

36:003:004 Her prophets are light and treacherous persons: her priests have polluted the sanctuary, they have done violence to the law.

36:003:005 The just Lord is in the midst thereof; he will not do iniquity: every morning doth he bring his judgment to light, he faileth not; but the unjust knoweth no shame.

36:003:006 I have cut off the nations: their towers are desolate; I made their streets waste, that none passeth by: their cities are destroyed, so that there is no man, that there is none inhabitant.

36:003:007 I said, Surely thou wilt fear me, thou wilt receive instruction; so their dwelling should not be cut off, howsoever I punished them: but they rose early, and corrupted all their doings.

36:003:008 Therefore wait ye upon me, saith the Lord, until the day that I rise up to the prey: for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may assemble the kingdoms, to pour upon them mine indignation, even all my fierce anger: for all the earth shall be devoured with the fire of my jealousy.

36:003:009 For then will I turn to the people a pure language, that they may all call upon the name of the Lord, to serve him with one consent.

36:003:010 From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia my suppliants, even the daughter of my dispersed, shall bring mine offering.

36:003:011 In that day shalt thou not be ashamed for all thy doings, wherein thou hast transgressed against me: for then I will take away out of the midst of thee them that rejoice in thy pride, and thou shalt no more be haughty because of my holy mountain.

36:003:012 I will also leave in the midst of thee an afflicted and poor people, and they shall trust in the name of the Lord.

36:003:013 The remnant of Israel shall not do iniquity, nor speak lies; neither shall a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth: for they shall feed and lie down, and none shall make them afraid.

36:003:014 Sing, O daughter of Zion; shout, O Israel; be glad and rejoice with all the heart, O daughter of Jerusalem.

36:003:015 The Lord hath taken away thy judgments, he hath cast out thine enemy: the king of Israel, even the Lord, is in the midst of thee: thou shalt not see evil any more.

36:003:016 In that day it shall be said to Jerusalem, Fear thou not: and to Zion, Let not thine hands be slack.

36:003:017 The Lord thy God in the midst of thee is mighty; he will save, he will rejoice over thee with joy; he will rest in his love, he will joy over thee with singing.

36:003:018 I will gather them that are sorrowful for the solemn assembly, who are of thee, to whom the reproach of it was a burden.

36:003:019 Behold, at that time I will undo all that afflict thee: and I will save her that halteth, and gather her that was driven out; and I will get them praise and fame in every land where they have been put to shame.

36:003:020 At that time will I bring you again, even in the time that I gather you: for I will make you a name and a praise among all people of the earth, when I turn back your captivity before your eyes, saith the Lord.

Zechariah 1

1^1In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the Lord unto Zechariah, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo the prophet, saying,

^2The Lord hath been sore displeased with your fathers.

^3Therefore say thou unto them, Thus saith the Lord of hosts; Turn ye unto me, saith the Lord of hosts, and I will turn unto you, saith the Lord of hosts.

^4Be ye not as your fathers, unto whom the former prophets have cried, saying, Thus saith the Lord of hosts; Turn ye now from your evil ways, and from your evil doings: but they did not hear, nor hearken unto me, saith the Lord.

^5Your fathers, where are they? and the prophets, do they live for ever?

^6But my words and my statutes, which I commanded my servants the prophets, did they not take hold of your fathers? and they returned and said, Like as the Lord of hosts thought to do unto us, according to our ways, and according to our doings, so hath he dealt with us.

^7Upon the four and twentieth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Sebat, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the Lord unto Zechariah, the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo the prophet, saying,

^8I saw by night, and behold a man riding upon a red horse, and he stood among the myrtle trees that were in the bottom; and behind him were there red horses, speckled, and white.

^9Then said I, O my lord, what are these? And the angel that talked with me said unto me, I will shew thee what these be.

^10And the man that stood among the myrtle trees answered and said, These are they whom the Lord hath sent to walk to and fro through the earth.

^11And they answered the angel of the Lord that stood among the myrtle trees, and said, We have walked to and fro through the earth, and, behold, all the earth sitteth still, and is at rest.

^12Then the angel of the Lord answered and said, O Lord of hosts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which thou hast had indignation these threescore and ten years?

^13And the Lord answered the angel that talked with me with good words and comfortable words.

^14So the angel that communed with me said unto me, Cry thou, saying, Thus saith the Lord of hosts; I am jealous for Jerusalem and for Zion with a great jealousy.

^15And I am very sore displeased with the heathen that are at ease: for I was but a little displeased, and they helped forward the affliction.

^16Therefore thus saith the Lord; I am returned to Jerusalem with mercies: my house shall be built in it, saith the Lord of hosts, and a line shall be stretched forth upon Jerusalem.

^17Cry yet, saying, Thus saith the Lord of hosts; My cities through prosperity shall yet be spread abroad; and the Lord shall yet comfort Zion, and shall yet choose Jerusalem.

^18Then lifted I up mine eyes, and saw, and behold four horns.

^19And I said unto the angel that talked with me, What be these? And he answered me, These are the horns which have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.

^20And the Lord shewed me four carpenters.

^21Then said I, What come these to do? And he spake, saying, These are the horns which have scattered Judah, so that no man did lift up his head: but these are come to fray them, to cast out the horns of the Gentiles, which lifted up their horn over the land of Judah to scatter it.

Zechariah 2

2^1I lifted up mine eyes again, and looked, and behold a man with a measuring line in his hand.

^2Then said I, Whither goest thou? And he said unto me, To measure Jerusalem, to see what is the breadth thereof, and what is the length thereof.

^3And, behold, the angel that talked with me went forth, and another angel went out to meet him,

^4And said unto him, Run, speak to this young man, saying, Jerusalem shall be inhabited as towns without walls for the multitude of men and cattle therein:

^5For I, saith the Lord, will be unto her a wall of fire round about, and will be the glory in the midst of her.

^6Ho, ho, come forth, and flee from the land of the north, saith the Lord: for I have spread you abroad as the four winds of the heaven, saith the Lord.

^7Deliver thyself, O Zion, that dwellest with the daughter of Babylon.

^8For thus saith the Lord of hosts; After the glory hath he sent me unto the nations which spoiled you: for he that toucheth you toucheth the apple of his eye.

^9For, behold, I will shake mine hand upon them, and they shall be a spoil to their servants: and ye shall know that the Lord of hosts hath sent me.

^10Sing and rejoice, O daughter of Zion: for, lo, I come, and I will dwell in the midst of thee, saith the Lord.

^11And many nations shall be joined to the Lord in that day, and shall be my people: and I will dwell in the midst of thee, and thou shalt know that the Lord of hosts hath sent me unto thee.

^12And the Lord shall inherit Judah his portion in the holy land, and shall choose Jerusalem again.

^13Be silent, O all flesh, before the Lord: for he is raised up out of his holy habitation.

Zechariah 3

3^1And he shewed me Joshua the high priest standing before the angel of the Lord, and Satan standing at his right hand to resist him.

^2And the Lord said unto Satan, The Lord rebuke thee, O Satan; even the Lord that hath chosen Jerusalem rebuke thee: is not this a brand plucked out of the fire?

^3Now Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and stood before the angel.

^4And he answered and spake unto those that stood before him, saying, Take away the filthy garments from him. And unto him he said, Behold, I have caused thine iniquity to pass from thee, and I will clothe thee with change of raiment.

^5And I said, Let them set a fair mitre upon his head. So they set a fair mitre upon his head, and clothed him with garments. And the angel of the Lord stood by.

^6And the angel of the Lord protested unto Joshua, saying,

^7Thus saith the Lord of hosts; If thou wilt walk in my ways, and if thou wilt keep my charge, then thou shalt also judge my house, and shalt also keep my courts, and I will give thee places to walk among these that stand by.

^8Hear now, O Joshua the high priest, thou, and thy fellows that sit before thee: for they are men wondered at: for, behold, I will bring forth my servant the branch.

^9For behold the stone that I have laid before Joshua; upon one stone shall be seven eyes: behold, I will engrave the graving thereof, saith the Lord of hosts, and I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day.

^10In that day, saith the Lord of hosts, shall ye call every man his neighbour under the vine and under the fig tree.

Zechariah 4

4^1And the angel that talked with me came again, and waked me, as a man that is wakened out of his sleep.

^2And said unto me, What seest thou? And I said, I have looked, and behold a candlestick all of gold, with a bowl upon the top of it, and his seven lamps thereon, and seven pipes to the seven lamps, which are upon the top thereof:

^3And two olive trees by it, one upon the right side of the bowl, and the other upon the left side thereof.

^4So I answered and spake to the angel that talked with me, saying, What are these, my lord?

^5Then the angel that talked with me answered and said unto me, Knowest thou not what these be? And I said, No, my lord.

^6Then he answered and spake unto me, saying, This is the word of the Lord unto Zerubbabel, saying, Not by might, nor by power, but by my spirit, saith the Lord of hosts.

^7Who art thou, O great mountain? before Zerubbabel thou shalt become a plain: and he shall bring forth the headstone thereof with shoutings, crying, Grace, grace unto it.

^8Moreover the word of the Lord came unto me, saying,

^9The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this house; his hands shall also finish it; and thou shalt know that the Lord of hosts hath sent me unto you.

^10For who hath despised the day of small things? for they shall rejoice, and shall see the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel with those seven; they are the eyes of the Lord, which run to and fro through the whole earth.

^11Then answered I, and said unto him, What are these two olive trees upon the right side of the candlestick and upon the left side thereof?

^12And I answered again, and said unto him, What be these two olive branches which through the two golden pipes empty the golden oil out of themselves?

^13And he answered me and said, Knowest thou not what these be? And I said, No, my lord.

^14Then said he, These are the two anointed ones, that stand by the Lord of the whole earth.

Zechariah 5

5^1Then I turned, and lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and behold a flying roll.

^2And he said unto me, What seest thou? And I answered, I see a flying roll; the length thereof is twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof ten cubits.

^3Then said he unto me, This is the curse that goeth forth over the face of the whole earth: for every one that stealeth shall be cut off as on this side according to it; and every one that sweareth shall be cut off as on that side according to it.

^4I will bring it forth, saith the Lord of hosts, and it shall enter into the house of the thief, and into the house of him that sweareth falsely by my name: and it shall remain in the midst of his house, and shall consume it with the timber thereof and the stones thereof.

^5Then the angel that talked with me went forth, and said unto me, Lift up now thine eyes, and see what is this that goeth forth.

^6And I said, What is it? And he said, This is an ephah that goeth forth. He said moreover, This is their resemblance through all the earth.

^7And, behold, there was lifted up a talent of lead: and this is a woman that sitteth in the midst of the ephah.

^8And he said, This is wickedness. And he cast it into the midst of the ephah; and he cast the weight of lead upon the mouth thereof.

^9Then lifted I up mine eyes, and looked, and, behold, there came out two women, and the wind was in their wings; for they had wings like the wings of a stork: and they lifted up the ephah between the earth and the heaven.

^10Then said I to the angel that talked with me, Whither do these bear the ephah?

^11And he said unto me, To build it an house in the land of Shinar: and it shall be established, and set there upon her own base.

Zechariah 6

6^1And I turned, and lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and, behold, there came four chariots out from between two mountains; and the mountains were mountains of brass.

^2In the first chariot were red horses; and in the second chariot black horses;

^3And in the third chariot white horses; and in the fourth chariot grisled and bay horses.

^4Then I answered and said unto the angel that talked with me, What are these, my lord?

^5And the angel answered and said unto me, These are the four spirits of the heavens, which go forth from standing before the Lord of all the earth.

^6The black horses which are therein go forth into the north country; and the white go forth after them; and the grisled go forth toward the south country.

^7And the bay went forth, and sought to go that they might walk to and fro through the earth: and he said, Get you hence, walk to and fro through the earth. So they walked to and fro through the earth.

^8Then cried he upon me, and spake unto me, saying, Behold, these that go toward the north country have quieted my spirit in the north country.

^9And the word of the Lord came unto me, saying,

^10Take of them of the captivity, even of Heldai, of Tobijah, and of Jedaiah, which are come from Babylon, and come thou the same day, and go into the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah;

^11Then take silver and gold, and make crowns, and set them upon the head of Joshua the son of Josedech, the high priest;

^12And speak unto him, saying, Thus speaketh the Lord of hosts, saying, Behold the man whose name is The Branch; and he shall grow up out of his place, and he shall build the temple of the Lord:

^13Even he shall build the temple of the Lord; and he shall bear the glory, and shall sit and rule upon his throne; and he shall be a priest upon his throne: and the counsel of peace shall be between them both.

^14And the crowns shall be to Helem, and to Tobijah, and to Jedaiah, and to Hen the son of Zephaniah, for a memorial in the temple of the Lord.

^15And they that are far off shall come and build in the temple of the Lord, and ye shall know that the Lord of hosts hath sent me unto you. And this shall come to pass, if ye will diligently obey the voice of the Lord your God.

Zechariah 7

7^1And it came to pass in the fourth year of king Darius, that the word of the Lord came unto Zechariah in the fourth day of the ninth month, even in Chisleu;

^2When they had sent unto the house of God Sherezer and Regemmelech, and their men, to pray before the Lord,

^3And to speak unto the priests which were in the house of the Lord of hosts, and to the prophets, saying, Should I weep in the fifth month, separating myself, as I have done these so many years?

^4Then came the word of the Lord of hosts unto me, saying,

^5Speak unto all the people of the land, and to the priests, saying, When ye fasted and mourned in the fifth and seventh month, even those seventy years, did ye at all fast unto me, even to me?

^6And when ye did eat, and when ye did drink, did not ye eat for yourselves, and drink for yourselves?

^7Should ye not hear the words which the Lord hath cried by the former prophets, when Jerusalem was inhabited and in prosperity, and the cities thereof round about her, when men inhabited the south and the plain?

^8And the word of the Lord came unto Zechariah, saying,

^9Thus speaketh the Lord of hosts, saying, Execute true judgment, and shew mercy and compassions every man to his brother:

^10And oppress not the widow, nor the fatherless, the stranger, nor the poor; and let none of you imagine evil against his brother in your heart.

^11But they refused to hearken, and pulled away the shoulder, and stopped their ears, that they should not hear.

^12Yea, they made their hearts as an adamant stone, lest they should hear the law, and the words which the Lord of hosts hath sent in his spirit by the former prophets: therefore came a great wrath from the Lord of hosts.

^13Therefore it is come to pass, that as he cried, and they would not hear; so they cried, and I would not hear, saith the Lord of hosts:

^14But I scattered them with a whirlwind among all the nations whom they knew not. Thus the land was desolate after them, that no man passed through nor returned: for they laid the pleasant land desolate.

Zechariah 8

8^1Again the word of the Lord of hosts came to me, saying,

^2Thus saith the Lord of hosts; I was jealous for Zion with great jealousy, and I was jealous for her with great fury.

^3Thus saith the Lord; I am returned unto Zion, and will dwell in the midst of Jerusalem: and Jerusalem shall be called a city of truth; and the mountain of the Lord of hosts the holy mountain.

^4Thus saith the Lord of hosts; There shall yet old men and old women dwell in the streets of Jerusalem, and every man with his staff in his hand for very age.

^5And the streets of the city shall be full of boys and girls playing in the streets thereof.

^6Thus saith the Lord of hosts; If it be marvellous in the eyes of the remnant of this people in these days, should it also be marvellous in mine eyes? saith the Lord of hosts.

^7Thus saith the Lord of hosts; Behold, I will save my people from the east country, and from the west country;

^8And I will bring them, and they shall dwell in the midst of Jerusalem: and they shall be my people, and I will be their God, in truth and in righteousness.

^9Thus saith the Lord of hosts; Let your hands be strong, ye that hear in these days these words by the mouth of the prophets, which were in the day that the foundation of the house of the Lord of hosts was laid, that the temple might be built.

^10For before these days there was no hire for man, nor any hire for beast; neither was there any peace to him that went out or came in because of the affliction: for I set all men every one against his neighbour.

^11But now I will not be unto the residue of this people as in the former days, saith the Lord of hosts.

^12For the seed shall be prosperous; the vine shall give her fruit, and the ground shall give her increase, and the heavens shall give their dew; and I will cause the remnant of this people to possess all these things.

^13And it shall come to pass, that as ye were a curse among the heathen, O house of Judah, and house of Israel; so will I save you, and ye shall be a blessing: fear not, but let your hands be strong.

^14For thus saith the Lord of hosts; As I thought to punish you, when your fathers provoked me to wrath, saith the Lord of hosts, and I repented not:

^15So again have I thought in these days to do well unto Jerusalem and to the house of Judah: fear ye not.

^16These are the things that ye shall do; Speak ye every man the truth to his neighbour; execute the judgment of truth and peace in your gates:

^17And let none of you imagine evil in your hearts against his neighbour; and love no false oath: for all these are things that I hate, saith the Lord.

^18And the word of the Lord of hosts came unto me, saying,

^19Thus saith the Lord of hosts; The fast of the fourth month, and the fast of the fifth, and the fast of the seventh, and the fast of the tenth, shall be to the house of Judah joy and gladness, and cheerful feasts; therefore love the truth and peace.

^20Thus saith the Lord of hosts; It shall yet come to pass, that there shall come people, and the inhabitants of many cities:

^21And the inhabitants of one city shall go to another, saying, Let us go speedily to pray before the Lord, and to seek the Lord of hosts: I will go also.

^22Yea, many people and strong nations shall come to seek the Lord of hosts in Jerusalem, and to pray before the Lord.

^23Thus saith the Lord of hosts; In those days it shall come to pass, that ten men shall take hold out of all languages of the nations, even shall take hold of the skirt of him that is a Jew, saying, We will go with you: for we have heard that God is with you.

Zechariah 9

9^1The burden of the word of the Lord in the land of Hadrach, and Damascus shall be the rest thereof: when the eyes of man, as of all the tribes of Israel, shall be toward the Lord.

^2And Hamath also shall border thereby; Tyrus, and Zidon, though it be very wise.

^3And Tyrus did build herself a strong hold, and heaped up silver as the dust, and fine gold as the mire of the streets.

^4Behold, the Lord will cast her out, and he will smite her power in the sea; and she shall be devoured with fire.

^5Ashkelon shall see it, and fear; Gaza also shall see it, and be very sorrowful, and Ekron; for her expectation shall be ashamed; and the king shall perish from Gaza, and Ashkelon shall not be inhabited.

^6And a bastard shall dwell in Ashdod, and I will cut off the pride of the Philistines.

^7And I will take away his blood out of his mouth, and his abominations from between his teeth: but he that remaineth, even he, shall be for our God, and he shall be as a governor in Judah, and Ekron as a Jebusite.

^8And I will encamp about mine house because of the army, because of him that passeth by, and because of him that returneth: and no oppressor shall pass through them any more: for now have I seen with mine eyes.

^9Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion; shout, O daughter of Jerusalem: behold, thy King cometh unto thee: he is just, and having salvation; lowly, and riding upon an ass, and upon a colt the foal of an ass.

^10And I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim, and the horse from Jerusalem, and the battle bow shall be cut off: and he shall speak peace unto the heathen: and his dominion shall be from sea even to sea, and from the river even to the ends of the earth.

^11As for thee also, by the blood of thy covenant I have sent forth thy prisoners out of the pit wherein is no water.

^12Turn you to the strong hold, ye prisoners of hope: even to day do I declare that I will render double unto thee;

^13When I have bent Judah for me, filled the bow with Ephraim, and raised up thy sons, O Zion, against thy sons, O Greece, and made thee as the sword of a mighty man.

^14And the Lord shall be seen over them, and his arrow shall go forth as the lightning: and the Lord God shall blow the trumpet, and shall go with whirlwinds of the south.

^15The Lord of hosts shall defend them; and they shall devour, and subdue with sling stones; and they shall drink, and make a noise as through wine; and they shall be filled like bowls, and as the corners of the altar.

^16And the Lord their God shall save them in that day as the flock of his people: for they shall be as the stones of a crown, lifted up as an ensign upon his land.

^17For how great is his goodness, and how great is his beauty! corn shall make the young men cheerful, and new wine the maids.

Zechariah 10

10^1Ask ye of the Lord rain in the time of the latter rain; so the Lord shall make bright clouds, and give them showers of rain, to every one grass in the field.

^2For the idols have spoken vanity, and the diviners have seen a lie, and have told false dreams; they comfort in vain: therefore they went their way as a flock, they were troubled, because there was no shepherd.

^3Mine anger was kindled against the shepherds, and I punished the goats: for the Lord of hosts hath visited his flock the house of Judah, and hath made them as his goodly horse in the battle.

^4Out of him came forth the corner, out of him the nail, out of him the battle bow, out of him every oppressor together.

^5And they shall be as mighty men, which tread down their enemies in the mire of the streets in the battle: and they shall fight, because the Lord is with them, and the riders on horses shall be confounded.

^6And I will strengthen the house of Judah, and I will save the house of Joseph, and I will bring them again to place them; for I have mercy upon them: and they shall be as though I had not cast them off: for I am the Lord their God, and will hear them.

^7And they of Ephraim shall be like a mighty man, and their heart shall rejoice as through wine: yea, their children shall see it, and be glad; their heart shall rejoice in the Lord.

^8I will hiss for them, and gather them; for I have redeemed them: and they shall increase as they have increased.

^9And I will sow them among the people: and they shall remember me in far countries; and they shall live with their children, and turn again.

^10I will bring them again also out of the land of Egypt, and gather them out of Assyria; and I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon; and place shall not be found for them.

^11And he shall pass through the sea with affliction, and shall smite the waves in the sea, and all the deeps of the river shall dry up: and the pride of Assyria shall be brought down, and the sceptre of Egypt shall depart away.

^12And I will strengthen them in the Lord; and they shall walk up and down in his name, saith the Lord.

Zechariah 11

11^1Open thy doors, O Lebanon, that the fire may devour thy cedars.

^2Howl, fir tree; for the cedar is fallen; because the mighty are spoiled: howl, O ye oaks of Bashan; for the forest of the vintage is come down.

^3There is a voice of the howling of the shepherds; for their glory is spoiled: a voice of the roaring of young lions; for the pride of Jordan is spoiled.

^4Thus saith the Lord my God; Feed the flock of the slaughter;

^5Whose possessors slay them, and hold themselves not guilty: and they that sell them say, Blessed be the Lord; for I am rich: and their own shepherds pity them not.

^6For I will no more pity the inhabitants of the land, saith the Lord: but, lo, I will deliver the men every one into his neighbour’s hand, and into the hand of his king: and they shall smite the land, and out of their hand I will not deliver them.

^7And I will feed the flock of slaughter, even you, O poor of the flock. And I took unto me two staves; the one I called Beauty, and the other I called Bands; and I fed the flock.

^8Three shepherds also I cut off in one month; and my soul lothed them, and their soul also abhorred me.

^9Then said I, I will not feed you: that that dieth, let it die; and that that is to be cut off, let it be cut off; and let the rest eat every one the flesh of another.

^10And I took my staff, even Beauty, and cut it asunder, that I might break my covenant which I had made with all the people.

^11And it was broken in that day: and so the poor of the flock that waited upon me knew that it was the word of the Lord.

^12And I said unto them, If ye think good, give me my price; and if not, forbear. So they weighed for my price thirty pieces of silver.

^13And the Lord said unto me, Cast it unto the potter: a goodly price that I was prised at of them. And I took the thirty pieces of silver, and cast them to the potter in the house of the Lord.

^14Then I cut asunder mine other staff, even Bands, that I might break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

^15And the Lord said unto me, Take unto thee yet the instruments of a foolish shepherd.

^16For, lo, I will raise up a shepherd in the land, which shall not visit those that be cut off, neither shall seek the young one, nor heal that that is broken, nor feed that that standeth still: but he shall eat the flesh of the fat, and tear their claws in pieces.

^17Woe to the idol shepherd that leaveth the flock! the sword shall be upon his arm, and upon his right eye: his arm shall be clean dried up, and his right eye shall be utterly darkened.

Zechariah 12

12^1The burden of the word of the Lord for Israel, saith the Lord, which stretcheth forth the heavens, and layeth the foundation of the earth, and formeth the spirit of man within him.

^2Behold, I will make Jerusalem a cup of trembling unto all the people round about, when they shall be in the siege both against Judah and against Jerusalem.

^3And in that day will I make Jerusalem a burdensome stone for all people: all that burden themselves with it shall be cut in pieces, though all the people of the earth be gathered together against it.

^4In that day, saith the Lord, I will smite every horse with astonishment, and his rider with madness: and I will open mine eyes upon the house of Judah, and will smite every horse of the people with blindness.

^5And the governors of Judah shall say in their heart, The inhabitants of Jerusalem shall be my strength in the Lord of hosts their God.

^6In that day will I make the governors of Judah like an hearth of fire among the wood, and like a torch of fire in a sheaf; and they shall devour all the people round about, on the right hand and on the left: and Jerusalem shall be inhabited again in her own place, even in Jerusalem.

^7The Lord also shall save the tents of Judah first, that the glory of the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem do not magnify themselves against Judah.

^8In that day shall the Lord defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and he that is feeble among them at that day shall be as David; and the house of David shall be as God, as the angel of the Lord before them.

^9And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will seek to destroy all the nations that come against Jerusalem.

^10And I will pour upon the house of David, and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the spirit of grace and of supplications: and they shall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they shall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only son, and shall be in bitterness for him, as one that is in bitterness for his firstborn.

^11In that day shall there be a great mourning in Jerusalem, as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon.

^12And the land shall mourn, every family apart; the family of the house of David apart, and their wives apart; the family of the house of Nathan apart, and their wives apart;

^13The family of the house of Levi apart, and their wives apart; the family of Shimei apart, and their wives apart;

^14All the families that remain, every family apart, and their wives apart.

Zechariah 13

13^1In that day there shall be a fountain opened to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem for sin and for uncleanness.

^2And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord of hosts, that I will cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they shall no more be remembered: and also I will cause the prophets and the unclean spirit to pass out of the land.

^3And it shall come to pass, that when any shall yet prophesy, then his father and his mother that begat him shall say unto him, Thou shalt not live; for thou speakest lies in the name of the Lord: and his father and his mother that begat him shall thrust him through when he prophesieth.

^4And it shall come to pass in that day, that the prophets shall be ashamed every one of his vision, when he hath prophesied; neither shall they wear a rough garment to deceive:

^5But he shall say, I am no prophet, I am an husbandman; for man taught me to keep cattle from my youth.

^6And one shall say unto him, What are these wounds in thine hands? Then he shall answer, Those with which I was wounded in the house of my friends.

^7Awake, O sword, against my shepherd, and against the man that is my fellow, saith the Lord of hosts: smite the shepherd, and the sheep shall be scattered: and I will turn mine hand upon the little ones.

^8And it shall come to pass, that in all the land, saith the Lord, two parts therein shall be cut off and die; but the third shall be left therein.

^9And I will bring the third part through the fire, and will refine them as silver is refined, and will try them as gold is tried: they shall call on my name, and I will hear them: I will say, It is my people: and they shall say, The Lord is my God.

Zechariah 14

14^1Behold, the day of the Lord cometh, and thy spoil shall be divided in the midst of thee.

^2For I will gather all nations against Jerusalem to battle; and the city shall be taken, and the houses rifled, and the women ravished; and half of the city shall go forth into captivity, and the residue of the people shall not be cut off from the city.

^3Then shall the Lord go forth, and fight against those nations, as when he fought in the day of battle.

^4And his feet shall stand in that day upon the mount of Olives, which is before Jerusalem on the east, and the mount of Olives shall cleave in the midst thereof toward the east and toward the west, and there shall be a very great valley; and half of the mountain shall remove toward the north, and half of it toward the south.

^5And ye shall flee to the valley of the mountains; for the valley of the mountains shall reach unto Azal: yea, ye shall flee, like as ye fled from before the earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah: and the Lord my God shall come, and all the saints with thee.

^6And it shall come to pass in that day, that the light shall not be clear, nor dark:

^7But it shall be one day which shall be known to the Lord, not day, nor night: but it shall come to pass, that at evening time it shall be light.

^8And it shall be in that day, that living waters shall go out from Jerusalem; half of them toward the former sea, and half of them toward the hinder sea: in summer and in winter shall it be.

^9And the Lord shall be king over all the earth: in that day shall there be one Lord, and his name one.

^10All the land shall be turned as a plain from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem: and it shall be lifted up, and inhabited in her place, from Benjamin’s gate unto the place of the first gate, unto the corner gate, and from the tower of Hananeel unto the king’s winepresses.

^11And men shall dwell in it, and there shall be no more utter destruction; but Jerusalem shall be safely inhabited.

^12And this shall be the plague wherewith the Lord will smite all the people that have fought against Jerusalem; Their flesh shall consume away while they stand upon their feet, and their eyes shall consume away in their holes, and their tongue shall consume away in their mouth.

^13And it shall come to pass in that day, that a great tumult from the Lord shall be among them; and they shall lay hold every one on the hand of his neighbour, and his hand shall rise up against the hand of his neighbour.

^14And Judah also shall fight at Jerusalem; and the wealth of all the heathen round about shall be gathered together, gold, and silver, and apparel, in great abundance.

^15And so shall be the plague of the horse, of the mule, of the camel, and of the ass, and of all the beasts that shall be in these tents, as this plague.

^16And it shall come to pass, that every one that is left of all the nations which came against Jerusalem shall even go up from year to year to worship the King, the Lord of hosts, and to keep the feast of tabernacles.

^17And it shall be, that whoso will not come up of all the families of the earth unto Jerusalem to worship the King, the Lord of hosts, even upon them shall be no rain.

^18And if the family of Egypt go not up, and come not, that have no rain; there shall be the plague, wherewith the Lord will smite the heathen that come not up to keep the feast of tabernacles.

^19This shall be the punishment of Egypt, and the punishment of all nations that come not up to keep the feast of tabernacles.

^20In that day shall there be upon the bells of the horses, Holiness unto the Lord; and the pots in the Lord’s house shall be like the bowls before the altar.

^21Yea, every pot in Jerusalem and in Judah shall be holiness unto the Lord of hosts: and all they that sacrifice shall come and take of them, and seethe therein: and in that day there shall be no more the Canaanite in the house of the Lord of hosts.

Malachi

The Book of

Malachi

I

^1The burden of the word of the Lord to Israel by Malachi.

^2I have loved you, saith the Lord. Yet ye say, Wherein hast thou loved us? Was not Esau Jacob’s brother? saith the Lord: yet I loved Jacob,

^3And I hated Esau, and laid his mountains and his heritage waste for the dragons of the wilderness.

^4Whereas Edom saith, We are impoverished, but we will return and build the desolate places; thus saith the Lord of hosts, They shall build, but I will throw down; and they shall call them, The border of wickedness, and, The people against whom the Lord hath indignation for ever.

^5And your eyes shall see, and ye shall say, The Lord will be magnified from the border of Israel.

^6A son honoureth his father, and a servant his master: if then I be a father, where is mine honour? and if I be a master, where is my fear? saith the Lord of hosts unto you, O priests, that despise my name. And ye say, Wherein have we despised thy name?

^7Ye offer polluted bread upon mine altar; and ye say, Wherein have we polluted thee? In that ye say, The table of the Lord is contemptible.

^8And if ye offer the blind for sacrifice, is it not evil? and if ye offer the lame and sick, is it not evil? offer it now unto thy governor; will he be pleased with thee, or accept thy person? saith the Lord of hosts.

^9And now, I pray you, beseech God that he will be gracious unto us: this hath been by your means: will he regard your persons? saith the Lord of hosts.

^10Who is there even among you that would shut the doors for nought? neither do ye kindle fire on mine altar for nought. I have no pleasure in you, saith the Lord of hosts, neither will I accept an offering at your hand.

^11For from the rising of the sun even unto the going down of the same my name shall be great among the Gentiles; and in every place incense shall be offered unto my name, and a pure offering: for my name shall be great among the heathen, saith the Lord of hosts.

^12But ye have profaned it, in that ye say, The table of the Lord is polluted; and the fruit thereof, even his meat, is contemptible.

^13Ye said also, Behold, what a weariness is it! and ye have snuffed at it, saith the Lord of hosts; and ye brought that which was torn, and the lame, and the sick; thus ye brought an offering: should I accept this of your hand? saith the Lord.

^14But cursed be the deceiver, which hath in his flock a male, and voweth, and sacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing: for I am a great King, saith the Lord of hosts, and my name is dreadful among the heathen.

II

^1And now, O ye priests, this commandment is for you.

^2If ye will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory unto my name, saith the Lord of hosts, I will even send a curse upon you, and I will curse your blessings: yea, I have cursed them already, because ye do not lay it to heart.

^3Behold, I will corrupt your seed, and spread dung upon your faces, even the dung of your solemn feasts; and one shall take you away with it.

^4And ye shall know that I have sent this commandment unto you, that my covenant might be with Levi, saith the Lord of hosts.

^5My covenant was with him of life and peace; and I gave them to him for the fear wherewith he feared me, and was afraid before my name.

^6The law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquity was not found in his lips: he walked with me in peace and equity, and did turn many away from iniquity.

^7For the priest’s lips should keep knowledge, and they should seek the law at his mouth: for he is the messenger of the Lord of hosts.

^8But ye are departed out of the way; ye have caused many to stumble at the law; ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi, saith the Lord of hosts.

^9Therefore have I also made you contemptible and base before all the people, according as ye have not kept my ways, but have been partial in the law.

^10Have we not all one father? hath not one God created us? why do we deal treacherously every man against his brother, by profaning the covenant of our fathers?

^11Judah hath dealt treacherously, and an abomination is committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah hath profaned the holiness of the Lord which he loved, and hath married the daughter of a strange god.

^12The Lord will cut off the man that doeth this, the master and the scholar, out of the tabernacles of Jacob, and him that offereth an offering unto the Lord of hosts.

^13And this have ye done again, covering the altar of the Lord with tears, with weeping, and with crying out, insomuch that he regardeth not the offering any more, or receiveth it with good will at your hand.

^14Yet ye say, Wherefore? Because the Lord hath been witness between thee and the wife of thy youth, against whom thou hast dealt treacherously: yet is she thy companion, and the wife of thy covenant.

^15And did not he make one? Yet had he the residue of the spirit. And wherefore one? That he might seek a godly seed. Therefore take heed to your spirit, and let none deal treacherously against the wife of his youth.

^16For the Lord, the God of Israel, saith that he hateth putting away: for one covereth violence with his garment, saith the Lord of hosts: therefore take heed to your spirit, that ye deal not treacherously.

^17Ye have wearied the Lord with your words. Yet ye say, Wherein have we wearied him? When ye say, Every one that doeth evil is good in the sight of the Lord, and he delighteth in them; or, Where is the God of judgment?

III

^1Behold, I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the Lord, whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple, even the messenger of the covenant, whom ye delight in: behold, he shall come, saith the Lord of hosts.

^2But who may abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like a refiner’s fire, and like fullers’ soap:

^3And he shall sit as a refiner and purifier of silver: and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and silver, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteousness.

^4Then shall the offering of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto the Lord, as in the days of old, and as in former years.

^5And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against false swearers, and against those that oppress the hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and that turn aside the stranger from his right, and fear not me, saith the Lord of hosts.

^6For I am the Lord, I change not; therefore ye sons of Jacob are not consumed.

^7Even from the days of your fathers ye are gone away from mine ordinances, and have not kept them. Return unto me, and I will return unto you, saith the Lord of hosts. But ye said, Wherein shall we return?

^8Will a man rob God? Yet ye have robbed me. But ye say, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings.

^9Ye are cursed with a curse: for ye have robbed me, even this whole nation.

^10Bring ye all the tithes into the storehouse, that there may be meat in mine house, and prove me now herewith, saith the Lord of hosts, if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there shall not be room enough to receive it.

^11And I will rebuke the devourer for your sakes, and he shall not destroy the fruits of your ground; neither shall your vine cast her fruit before the time in the field, saith the Lord of hosts.

^12And all nations shall call you blessed: for ye shall be a delightsome land, saith the Lord of hosts.

^13Your words have been stout against me, saith the Lord. Yet ye say, What have we spoken so much against thee?

^14Ye have said, It is vain to serve God: and what profit is it that we have kept his ordinance, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of hosts?

^15And now we call the proud happy; yea, they that work wickedness are set up; yea, they that tempt God are even delivered.

^16Then they that feared the Lord spake often one to another: and the Lord hearkened, and heard it, and a book of remembrance was written before him for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his name.

^17And they shall be mine, saith the Lord of hosts, in that day when I make up my jewels; and I will spare them, as a man spareth his own son that serveth him.

^18Then shall ye return, and discern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that serveth God and him that serveth him not.

IV

^1For, behold, the day cometh, that shall burn as an oven; and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly, shall be stubble: and the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith the Lord of hosts, that it shall leave them neither root nor branch.

^2But unto you that fear my name shall the Sun of righteousness arise with healing in his wings; and ye shall go forth, and grow up as calves of the stall.

^3And ye shall tread down the wicked; for they shall be ashes under the soles of your feet in the day that I shall do this, saith the Lord of hosts.

^4Remember ye the law of Moses my servant, which I commanded unto him in Horeb for all Israel, with the statutes and judgments.

^5Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the Lord:

^6And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse.

Luke

The Gospel According to

Luke

I

1^1Forasmuch as many have taken in hand to set forth in order a declaration of those things which are most surely believed among us,

^2Even as they delivered them unto us, which from the beginning were eyewitnesses, and ministers of the word;

^3It seemed good to me also, having had perfect understanding of all things from the very first, to write unto thee in order, most excellent Theophilus,

^4That thou mightest know the certainty of those things, wherein thou hast been instructed.

^5There was in the days of Herod, the king of Judaea, a certain priest named Zacharias, of the course of Abia: and his wife was of the daughters of Aaron, and her name was Elisabeth.

^6And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless.

^7And they had no child, because that Elisabeth was barren, and they both were now well stricken in years.

^8And it came to pass, that while he executed the priest’s office before God in the order of his course,

^9According to the custom of the priest’s office, his lot was to burn incense when he went into the temple of the Lord.

^10And the whole multitude of the people were praying without at the time of incense.

^11And there appeared unto him an angel of the Lord standing on the right side of the altar of incense.

^12And when Zacharias saw him, he was troubled, and fear fell upon him.

^13But the angel said unto him, Fear not, Zacharias: for thy prayer is heard; and thy wife Elisabeth shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt call his name John.

^14And thou shalt have joy and gladness; and many shall rejoice at his birth.

^15For he shall be great in the sight of the Lord, and shall drink neither wine nor strong drink; and he shall be filled with the Holy Ghost, even from his mother’s womb.

^16And many of the children of Israel shall he turn to the Lord their God.

^17And he shall go before him in the spirit and power of Elias, to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just; to make ready a people prepared for the Lord.

^18And Zacharias said unto the angel, Whereby shall I know this? for I am an old man, and my wife well stricken in years.

^19And the angel answering said unto him, I am Gabriel, that stand in the presence of God; and am sent to speak unto thee, and to shew thee these glad tidings.

^20And, behold, thou shalt be dumb, and not able to speak, until the day that these things shall be performed, because thou believest not my words, which shall be fulfilled in their season.

^21And the people waited for Zacharias, and marvelled that he tarried so long in the temple.

^22And when he came out, he could not speak unto them: and they perceived that he had seen a vision in the temple: for he beckoned unto them, and remained speechless.

^23And it came to pass, that, as soon as the days of his ministration were accomplished, he departed to his own house.

^24And after those days his wife Elisabeth conceived, and hid herself five months, saying,

^25Thus hath the Lord dealt with me in the days wherein he looked on me, to take away my reproach among men.

^26And in the sixth month the angel Gabriel was sent from God unto a city of Galilee, named Nazareth,

^27To a virgin espoused to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David; and the virgin’s name was Mary.

^28And the angel came in unto her, and said, Hail, thou that art highly favoured, the Lord is with thee: blessed art thou among women.

^29And when she saw him, she was troubled at his saying, and cast in her mind what manner of salutation this should be.

^30And the angel said unto her, Fear not, Mary: for thou hast found favour with God.

^31And, behold, thou shalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a son, and shalt call his name Jesus.

^32He shall be great, and shall be called the Son of the Highest: and the Lord God shall give unto him the throne of his father David:

^33And he shall reign over the house of Jacob for ever; and of his kingdom there shall be no end.

^34Then said Mary unto the angel, How shall this be, seeing I know not a man?

^35And the angel answered and said unto her, The Holy Ghost shall come upon thee, and the power of the Highest shall overshadow thee: therefore also that holy thing which shall be born of thee shall be called the Son of God.

^36And, behold, thy cousin Elisabeth, she hath also conceived a son in her old age: and this is the sixth month with her, who was called barren.

^37For with God nothing shall be impossible.

^38And Mary said, Behold the handmaid of the Lord; be it unto me according to thy word. And the angel departed from her.

^39And Mary arose in those days, and went into the hill country with haste, into a city of Juda;

^40And entered into the house of Zacharias, and saluted Elisabeth.

^41And it came to pass, that, when Elisabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the babe leaped in her womb; and Elisabeth was filled with the Holy Ghost:

^42And she spake out with a loud voice, and said, Blessed art thou among women, and blessed is the fruit of thy womb.

^43And whence is this to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me?

^44For, lo, as soon as the voice of thy salutation sounded in mine ears, the babe leaped in my womb for joy.

^45And blessed is she that believed: for there shall be a performance of those things which were told her from the Lord.

^46And Mary said, My soul doth magnify the Lord,

^47And my spirit hath rejoiced in God my Saviour.

^48For he hath regarded the low estate of his handmaiden: for, behold, from henceforth all generations shall call me blessed.

^49For he that is mighty hath done to me great things; and holy is his name.

^50And his mercy is on them that fear him from generation to generation.

^51He hath shewed strength with his arm; he hath scattered the proud in the imagination of their hearts.

^52He hath put down the mighty from their seats, and exalted them of low degree.

^53He hath filled the hungry with good things; and the rich he hath sent empty away.

^54He hath holpen his servant Israel, in remembrance of his mercy;

^55As he spake to our fathers, to Abraham, and to his seed for ever.

^56And Mary abode with her about three months, and returned to her own house.

^57Now Elisabeth’s full time came that she should be delivered; and she brought forth a son.

^58And her neighbours and her cousins heard how the Lord had shewed great mercy upon her; and they rejoiced with her.

^59And it came to pass, that on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child; and they called him Zacharias, after the name of his father.

^60And his mother answered and said, Not so; but he shall be called John.

^61And they said unto her, There is none of thy kindred that is called by this name.

^62And they made signs to his father, how he would have him called.

^63And he asked for a writing table, and wrote, saying, His name is John. And they marvelled all.

^64And his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue loosed, and he spake, and praised God.

^65And fear came on all that dwelt round about them: and all these sayings were noised abroad throughout all the hill country of Judaea.

^66And all they that heard them laid them up in their hearts, saying, What manner of child shall this be! And the hand of the Lord was with him.

^67And his father Zacharias was filled with the Holy Ghost, and prophesied, saying,

^68Blessed be the Lord God of Israel; for he hath visited and redeemed his people,

^69And hath raised up an horn of salvation for us in the house of his servant David;

^70As he spake by the mouth of his holy prophets, which have been since the world began:

^71That we should be saved from our enemies, and from the hand of all that hate us;

^72To perform the mercy promised to our fathers, and to remember his holy covenant;

^73The oath which he sware to our father Abraham,

^74That he would grant unto us, that we being delivered out of the hand of our enemies might serve him without fear,

^75In holiness and righteousness before him, all the days of our life.

^76And thou, child, shalt be called the prophet of the Highest: for thou shalt go before the face of the Lord to prepare his ways;

^77To give knowledge of salvation unto his people by the remission of their sins,

^78Through the tender mercy of our God; whereby the dayspring from on high hath visited us,

^79To give light to them that sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace.

^80And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, and was in the deserts till the day of his shewing unto Israel.

II

2^1And it came to pass in those days, that there went out a decree from Caesar Augustus that all the world should be taxed.

^2(And this taxing was first made when Cyrenius was governor of Syria.)

^3And all went to be taxed, every one into his own city.

^4And Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, into Judaea, unto the city of David, which is called Bethlehem; (because he was of the house and lineage of David:)

^5To be taxed with Mary his espoused wife, being great with child.

^6And so it was, that, while they were there, the days were accomplished that she should be delivered.

^7And she brought forth her firstborn son, and wrapped him in swaddling clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn.

^8And there were in the same country shepherds abiding in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night.

^9And, lo, the angel of the Lord came upon them, and the glory of the Lord shone round about them: and they were sore afraid.

^10And the angel said unto them, Fear not: for, behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy, which shall be to all people.

^11For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord.

^12And this shall be a sign unto you; Ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes, lying in a manger.

^13And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God, and saying,

^14Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good will toward men.

^15And it came to pass, as the angels were gone away from them into heaven, the shepherds said one to another, Let us now go even unto Bethlehem, and see this thing which is come to pass, which the Lord hath made known unto us.

^16And they came with haste, and found Mary, and Joseph, and the babe lying in a manger.

^17And when they had seen it, they made known abroad the saying which was told them concerning this child.

^18And all they that heard it wondered at those things which were told them by the shepherds.

^19But Mary kept all these things, and pondered them in her heart.

^20And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen, as it was told unto them.

^21And when eight days were accomplished for the circumcising of the child, his name was called Jesus, which was so named of the angel before he was conceived in the womb.

^22And when the days of her purification according to the law of Moses were accomplished, they brought him to Jerusalem, to present him to the Lord;

^23(As it is written in the law of the Lord, Every male that openeth the womb shall be called holy to the Lord;)

^24And to offer a sacrifice according to that which is said in the law of the Lord, A pair of turtledoves, or two young pigeons.

^25And, behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon; and the same man was just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel: and the Holy Ghost was upon him.

^26And it was revealed unto him by the Holy Ghost, that he should not see death, before he had seen the Lord’s Christ.

^27And he came by the Spirit into the temple: and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him after the custom of the law,

^28Then took he him up in his arms, and blessed God, and said,

^29Lord, now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, according to thy word:

^30For mine eyes have seen thy salvation,

^31Which thou hast prepared before the face of all people;

^32A light to lighten the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people Israel.

^33And Joseph and his mother marvelled at those things which were spoken of him.

^34And Simeon blessed them, and said unto Mary his mother, Behold, this child is set for the fall and rising again of many in Israel; and for a sign which shall be spoken against;

^35(Yea, a sword shall pierce through thy own soul also,) that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed.

^36And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Aser: she was of a great age, and had lived with an husband seven years from her virginity;

^37And she was a widow of about fourscore and four years, which departed not from the temple, but served God with fastings and prayers night and day.

^38And she coming in that instant gave thanks likewise unto the Lord, and spake of him to all them that looked for redemption in Jerusalem.

^39And when they had performed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned into Galilee, to their own city Nazareth.

^40And the child grew, and waxed strong in spirit, filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him.

^41Now his parents went to Jerusalem every year at the feast of the passover.

^42And when he was twelve years old, they went up to Jerusalem after the custom of the feast.

^43And when they had fulfilled the days, as they returned, the child Jesus tarried behind in Jerusalem; and Joseph and his mother knew not of it.

^44But they, supposing him to have been in the company, went a day’s journey; and they sought him among their kinsfolk and acquaintance.

^45And when they found him not, they turned back again to Jerusalem, seeking him.

^46And it came to pass, that after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the doctors, both hearing them, and asking them questions.

^47And all that heard him were astonished at his understanding and answers.

^48And when they saw him, they were amazed: and his mother said unto him, Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee sorrowing.

^49And he said unto them, How is it that ye sought me? wist ye not that I must be about my Father’s business?

^50And they understood not the saying which he spake unto them.

^51And he went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and was subject unto them: but his mother kept all these sayings in her heart.

^52And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man.

III

3^1Now in the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar, Pontius Pilate being governor of Judaea, and Herod being tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of Ituraea and of the region of Trachonitis, and Lysanias the tetrarch of Abilene,

^2Annas and Caiaphas being the high priests, the word of God came unto John the son of Zacharias in the wilderness.

^3And he came into all the country about Jordan, preaching the baptism of repentance for the remission of sins;

^4As it is written in the book of the words of Esaias the prophet, saying, The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths straight.

^5Every valley shall be filled, and every mountain and hill shall be brought low; and the crooked shall be made straight, and the rough ways shall be made smooth;

^6And all flesh shall see the salvation of God.

^7Then said he to the multitude that came forth to be baptized of him, O generation of vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come?

^8Bring forth therefore fruits worthy of repentance, and begin not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham to our father: for I say unto you, That God is able of these stones to raise up children unto Abraham.

^9And now also the axe is laid unto the root of the trees: every tree therefore which bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire.

^10And the people asked him, saying, What shall we do then?

^11He answereth and saith unto them, He that hath two coats, let him impart to him that hath none; and he that hath meat, let him do likewise.

^12Then came also publicans to be baptized, and said unto him, Master, what shall we do?

^13And he said unto them, Exact no more than that which is appointed you.

^14And the soldiers likewise demanded of him, saying, And what shall we do? And he said unto them, Do violence to no man, neither accuse any falsely; and be content with your wages.

^15And as the people were in expectation, and all men mused in their hearts of John, whether he were the Christ, or not;

^16John answered, saying unto them all, I indeed baptize you with water; but one mightier than I cometh, the latchet of whose shoes I am not worthy to unloose: he shall baptize you with the Holy Ghost and with fire:

^17Whose fan is in his hand, and he will throughly purge his floor, and will gather the wheat into his garner; but the chaff he will burn with fire unquenchable.

^18And many other things in his exhortation preached he unto the people.

^19But Herod the tetrarch, being reproved by him for Herodias his brother Philip’s wife, and for all the evils which Herod had done,

^20Added yet this above all, that he shut up John in prison.

^21Now when all the people were baptized, it came to pass, that Jesus also being baptized, and praying, the heaven was opened,

^22And the Holy Ghost descended in a bodily shape like a dove upon him, and a voice came from heaven, which said, Thou art my beloved Son; in thee I am well pleased.

^23And Jesus himself began to be about thirty years of age, being (as was supposed) the son of Joseph, which was the son of Heli,

^24Which was the son of Matthat, which was the son of Levi, which was the son of Melchi, which was the son of Janna, which was the son of Joseph,

^25Which was the son of Mattathias, which was the son of Amos, which was the son of Naum, which was the son of Esli, which was the son of Nagge,

^26Which was the son of Maath, which was the son of Mattathias, which was the son of Semei, which was the son of Joseph, which was the son of Juda,

^27Which was the son of Joanna, which was the son of Rhesa, which was the son of Zorobabel, which was the son of Salathiel, which was the son of Neri,

^28Which was the son of Melchi, which was the son of Addi, which was the son of Cosam, which was the son of Elmodam, which was the son of Er,

^29Which was the son of Jose, which was the son of Eliezer, which was the son of Jorim, which was the son of Matthat, which was the son of Levi,

^30Which was the son of Simeon, which was the son of Juda, which was the son of Joseph, which was the son of Jonan, which was the son of Eliakim,

^31Which was the son of Melea, which was the son of Menan, which was the son of Mattatha, which was the son of Nathan, which was the son of David,

^32Which was the son of Jesse, which was the son of Obed, which was the son of Booz, which was the son of Salmon, which was the son of Naasson,

^33Which was the son of Aminadab, which was the son of Aram, which was the son of Esrom, which was the son of Phares, which was the son of Juda,

^34Which was the son of Jacob, which was the son of Isaac, which was the son of Abraham, which was the son of Thara, which was the son of Nachor,

^35Which was the son of Saruch, which was the son of Ragau, which was the son of Phalec, which was the son of Heber, which was the son of Sala,

^36Which was the son of Cainan, which was the son of Arphaxad, which was the son of Sem, which was the son of Noe, which was the son of Lamech,

^37Which was the son of Mathusala, which was the son of Enoch, which was the son of Jared, which was the son of Maleleel, which was the son of Cainan,

^38Which was the son of Enos, which was the son of Seth, which was the son of Adam, which was the son of God.

IV

4^1And Jesus being full of the Holy Ghost returned from Jordan, and was led by the Spirit into the wilderness,

^2Being forty days tempted of the devil. And in those days he did eat nothing: and when they were ended, he afterward hungered.

^3And the devil said unto him, If thou be the Son of God, command this stone that it be made bread.

^4And Jesus answered him, saying, It is written, That man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word of God.

^5And the devil, taking him up into an high mountain, shewed unto him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time.

^6And the devil said unto him, All this power will I give thee, and the glory of them: for that is delivered unto me; and to whomsoever I will I give it.

^7If thou therefore wilt worship me, all shall be thine.

^8And Jesus answered and said unto him, Get thee behind me, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve.

^9And he brought him to Jerusalem, and set him on a pinnacle of the temple, and said unto him, If thou be the Son of God, cast thyself down from hence:

^10For it is written, He shall give his angels charge over thee, to keep thee:

^11And in their hands they shall bear thee up, lest at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone.

^12And Jesus answering said unto him, It is said, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God.

^13And when the devil had ended all the temptation, he departed from him for a season.

^14And Jesus returned in the power of the Spirit into Galilee: and there went out a fame of him through all the region round about.

^15And he taught in their synagogues, being glorified of all.

^16And he came to Nazareth, where he had been brought up: and, as his custom was, he went into the synagogue on the sabbath day, and stood up for to read.

^17And there was delivered unto him the book of the prophet Esaias. And when he had opened the book, he found the place where it was written,

^18The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, because he hath anointed me to preach the gospel to the poor; he hath sent me to heal the brokenhearted, to preach deliverance to the captives, and recovering of sight to the blind, to set at liberty them that are bruised,

^19To preach the acceptable year of the Lord.

^20And he closed the book, and he gave it again to the minister, and sat down. And the eyes of all them that were in the synagogue were fastened on him.

^21And he began to say unto them, This day is this scripture fulfilled in your ears.

^22And all bare him witness, and wondered at the gracious words which proceeded out of his mouth. And they said, Is not this Joseph’s son?

^23And he said unto them, Ye will surely say unto me this proverb, Physician, heal thyself: whatsoever we have heard done in Capernaum, do also here in thy country.

^24And he said, Verily I say unto you, No prophet is accepted in his own country.

^25But I tell you of a truth, many widows were in Israel in the days of Elias, when the heaven was shut up three years and six months, when great famine was throughout all the land;

^26But unto none of them was Elias sent, save unto Sarepta, a city of Sidon, unto a woman that was a widow.

^27And many lepers were in Israel in the time of Eliseus the prophet; and none of them was cleansed, saving Naaman the Syrian.

^28And all they in the synagogue, when they heard these things, were filled with wrath,

^29And rose up, and thrust him out of the city, and led him unto the brow of the hill whereon their city was built, that they might cast him down headlong.

^30But he passing through the midst of them went his way,

^31And came down to Capernaum, a city of Galilee, and taught them on the sabbath days.

^32And they were astonished at his doctrine: for his word was with power.

^33And in the synagogue there was a man, which had a spirit of an unclean devil, and cried out with a loud voice,

^34Saying, Let us alone; what have we to do with thee, thou Jesus of Nazareth? art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art; the Holy One of God.

^35And Jesus rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace, and come out of him. And when the devil had thrown him in the midst, he came out of him, and hurt him not.

^36And they were all amazed, and spake among themselves, saying, What a word is this! for with authority and power he commandeth the unclean spirits, and they come out.

^37And the fame of him went out into every place of the country round about.

^38And he arose out of the synagogue, and entered into Simon’s house. And Simon’s wife’s mother was taken with a great fever; and they besought him for her.

^39And he stood over her, and rebuked the fever; and it left her: and immediately she arose and ministered unto them.

^40Now when the sun was setting, all they that had any sick with divers diseases brought them unto him; and he laid his hands on every one of them, and healed them.

^41And devils also came out of many, crying out, and saying, Thou art Christ the Son of God. And he rebuking them suffered them not to speak: for they knew that he was Christ.

^42And when it was day, he departed and went into a desert place: and the people sought him, and came unto him, and stayed him, that he should not depart from them.

^43And he said unto them, I must preach the kingdom of God to other cities also: for therefore am I sent.

^44And he preached in the synagogues of Galilee.

V

5^1And it came to pass, that, as the people pressed upon him to hear the word of God, he stood by the lake of Gennesaret,

^2And saw two ships standing by the lake: but the fishermen were gone out of them, and were washing their nets.

^3And he entered into one of the ships, which was Simon’s, and prayed him that he would thrust out a little from the land. And he sat down, and taught the people out of the ship.

^4Now when he had left speaking, he said unto Simon, Launch out into the deep, and let down your nets for a draught.

^5And Simon answering said unto him, Master, we have toiled all the night, and have taken nothing: nevertheless at thy word I will let down the net.

^6And when they had this done, they inclosed a great multitude of fishes: and their net brake.

^7And they beckoned unto their partners, which were in the other ship, that they should come and help them. And they came, and filled both the ships, so that they began to sink.

^8When Simon Peter saw it, he fell down at Jesus’ knees, saying, Depart from me; for I am a sinful man, O Lord.

^9For he was astonished, and all that were with him, at the draught of the fishes which they had taken:

^10And so was also James, and John, the sons of Zebedee, which were partners with Simon. And Jesus said unto Simon, Fear not; from henceforth thou shalt catch men.

^11And when they had brought their ships to land, they forsook all, and followed him.

^12And it came to pass, when he was in a certain city, behold a man full of leprosy: who seeing Jesus fell on his face, and besought him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean.

^13And he put forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will: be thou clean. And immediately the leprosy departed from him.

^14And he charged him to tell no man: but go, and shew thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing, according as Moses commanded, for a testimony unto them.

^15But so much the more went there a fame abroad of him: and great multitudes came together to hear, and to be healed by him of their infirmities.

^16And he withdrew himself into the wilderness, and prayed.

^17And it came to pass on a certain day, as he was teaching, that there were Pharisees and doctors of the law sitting by, which were come out of every town of Galilee, and Judaea, and Jerusalem: and the power of the Lord was present to heal them.

^18And, behold, men brought in a bed a man which was taken with a palsy: and they sought means to bring him in, and to lay him before him.

^19And when they could not find by what way they might bring him in because of the multitude, they went upon the housetop, and let him down through the tiling with his couch into the midst before Jesus.

^20And when he saw their faith, he said unto him, Man, thy sins are forgiven thee.

^21And the scribes and the Pharisees began to reason, saying, Who is this which speaketh blasphemies? Who can forgive sins, but God alone?

^22But when Jesus perceived their thoughts, he answering said unto them, What reason ye in your hearts?

^23Whether is easier, to say, Thy sins be forgiven thee; or to say, Rise up and walk?

^24But that ye may know that the Son of man hath power upon earth to forgive sins, (he said unto the sick of the palsy,) I say unto thee, Arise, and take up thy couch, and go into thine house.

^25And immediately he rose up before them, and took up that whereon he lay, and departed to his own house, glorifying God.

^26And they were all amazed, and they glorified God, and were filled with fear, saying, We have seen strange things to day.

^27And after these things he went forth, and saw a publican, named Levi, sitting at the receipt of custom: and he said unto him, Follow me.

^28And he left all, rose up, and followed him.

^29And Levi made him a great feast in his own house: and there was a great company of publicans and of others that sat down with them.

^30But their scribes and Pharisees murmured against his disciples, saying, Why do ye eat and drink with publicans and sinners?

^31And Jesus answering said unto them, They that are whole need not a physician; but they that are sick.

^32I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance.

^33And they said unto him, Why do the disciples of John fast often, and make prayers, and likewise the disciples of the Pharisees; but thine eat and drink?

^34And he said unto them, Can ye make the children of the bridechamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them?

^35But the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken away from them, and then shall they fast in those days.

^36And he spake also a parable unto them; No man putteth a piece of a new garment upon an old; if otherwise, then both the new maketh a rent, and the piece that was taken out of the new agreeth not with the old.

^37And no man putteth new wine into old bottles; else the new wine will burst the bottles, and be spilled, and the bottles shall perish.

^38But new wine must be put into new bottles; and both are preserved.

^39No man also having drunk old wine straightway desireth new: for he saith, The old is better.

VI

6^1And it came to pass on the second sabbath after the first, that he went through the corn fields; and his disciples plucked the ears of corn, and did eat, rubbing them in their hands.

^2And certain of the Pharisees said unto them, Why do ye that which is not lawful to do on the sabbath days?

^3And Jesus answering them said, Have ye not read so much as this, what David did, when himself was an hungred, and they which were with him;

^4How he went into the house of God, and did take and eat the shewbread, and gave also to them that were with him; which it is not lawful to eat but for the priests alone?

^5And he said unto them, That the Son of man is Lord also of the sabbath.

^6And it came to pass also on another sabbath, that he entered into the synagogue and taught: and there was a man whose right hand was withered.

^7And the scribes and Pharisees watched him, whether he would heal on the sabbath day; that they might find an accusation against him.

^8But he knew their thoughts, and said to the man which had the withered hand, Rise up, and stand forth in the midst. And he arose and stood forth.

^9Then said Jesus unto them, I will ask you one thing; Is it lawful on the sabbath days to do good, or to do evil? to save life, or to destroy it?

^10And looking round about upon them all, he said unto the man, Stretch forth thy hand. And he did so: and his hand was restored whole as the other.

^11And they were filled with madness; and communed one with another what they might do to Jesus.

^12And it came to pass in those days, that he went out into a mountain to pray, and continued all night in prayer to God.

^13And when it was day, he called unto him his disciples: and of them he chose twelve, whom also he named apostles;

^14Simon, (whom he also named Peter,) and Andrew his brother, James and John, Philip and Bartholomew,

^15Matthew and Thomas, James the son of Alphaeus, and Simon called Zelotes,

^16And Judas the brother of James, and Judas Iscariot, which also was the traitor.

^17And he came down with them, and stood in the plain, and the company of his disciples, and a great multitude of people out of all Judaea and Jerusalem, and from the sea coast of Tyre and Sidon, which came to hear him, and to be healed of their diseases;

^18And they that were vexed with unclean spirits: and they were healed.

^19And the whole multitude sought to touch him: for there went virtue out of him, and healed them all.

^20And he lifted up his eyes on his disciples, and said, Blessed be ye poor: for yours is the kingdom of God.

^21Blessed are ye that hunger now: for ye shall be filled. Blessed are ye that weep now: for ye shall laugh.

^22Blessed are ye, when men shall hate you, and when they shall separate you from their company, and shall reproach you, and cast out your name as evil, for the Son of man’s sake.

^23Rejoice ye in that day, and leap for joy: for, behold, your reward is great in heaven: for in the like manner did their fathers unto the prophets.

^24But woe unto you that are rich! for ye have received your consolation.

^25Woe unto you that are full! for ye shall hunger. Woe unto you that laugh now! for ye shall mourn and weep.

^26Woe unto you, when all men shall speak well of you! for so did their fathers to the false prophets.

^27But I say unto you which hear, Love your enemies, do good to them which hate you,

^28Bless them that curse you, and pray for them which despitefully use you.

^29And unto him that smiteth thee on the one cheek offer also the other; and him that taketh away thy cloak forbid not to take thy coat also.

^30Give to every man that asketh of thee; and of him that taketh away thy goods ask them not again.

^31And as ye would that men should do to you, do ye also to them likewise.

^32For if ye love them which love you, what thank have ye? for sinners also love those that love them.

^33And if ye do good to them which do good to you, what thank have ye? for sinners also do even the same.

^34And if ye lend to them of whom ye hope to receive, what thank have ye? for sinners also lend to sinners, to receive as much again.

^35But love ye your enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing again; and your reward shall be great, and ye shall be the children of the Highest: for he is kind unto the unthankful and to the evil.

^36Be ye therefore merciful, as your Father also is merciful.

^37Judge not, and ye shall not be judged: condemn not, and ye shall not be condemned: forgive, and ye shall be forgiven:

^38Give, and it shall be given unto you; good measure, pressed down, and shaken together, and running over, shall men give into your bosom. For with the same measure that ye mete withal it shall be measured to you again.

^39And he spake a parable unto them, Can the blind lead the blind? shall they not both fall into the ditch?

^40The disciple is not above his master: but every one that is perfect shall be as his master.

^41And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother’s eye, but perceivest not the beam that is in thine own eye?

^42Either how canst thou say to thy brother, Brother, let me pull out the mote that is in thine eye, when thou thyself beholdest not the beam that is in thine own eye? Thou hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thine own eye, and then shalt thou see clearly to pull out the mote that is in thy brother’s eye.

^43For a good tree bringeth not forth corrupt fruit; neither doth a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.

^44For every tree is known by his own fruit. For of thorns men do not gather figs, nor of a bramble bush gather they grapes.

^45A good man out of the good treasure of his heart bringeth forth that which is good; and an evil man out of the evil treasure of his heart bringeth forth that which is evil: for of the abundance of the heart his mouth speaketh.

^46And why call ye me, Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say?

^47Whosoever cometh to me, and heareth my sayings, and doeth them, I will shew you to whom he is like:

^48He is like a man which built an house, and digged deep, and laid the foundation on a rock: and when the flood arose, the stream beat vehemently upon that house, and could not shake it: for it was founded upon a rock.

^49But he that heareth, and doeth not, is like a man that without a foundation built an house upon the earth; against which the stream did beat vehemently, and immediately it fell; and the ruin of that house was great.

VII

7^1Now when he had ended all his sayings in the audience of the people, he entered into Capernaum.

^2And a certain centurion’s servant, who was dear unto him, was sick, and ready to die.

^3And when he heard of Jesus, he sent unto him the elders of the Jews, beseeching him that he would come and heal his servant.

^4And when they came to Jesus, they besought him instantly, saying, That he was worthy for whom he should do this:

^5For he loveth our nation, and he hath built us a synagogue.

^6Then Jesus went with them. And when he was now not far from the house, the centurion sent friends to him, saying unto him, Lord, trouble not thyself: for I am not worthy that thou shouldest enter under my roof:

^7Wherefore neither thought I myself worthy to come unto thee: but say in a word, and my servant shall be healed.

^8For I also am a man set under authority, having under me soldiers, and I say unto one, Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it.

^9When Jesus heard these things, he marvelled at him, and turned him about, and said unto the people that followed him, I say unto you, I have not found so great faith, no, not in Israel.

^10And they that were sent, returning to the house, found the servant whole that had been sick.

^11And it came to pass the day after, that he went into a city called Nain; and many of his disciples went with him, and much people.

^12Now when he came nigh to the gate of the city, behold, there was a dead man carried out, the only son of his mother, and she was a widow: and much people of the city was with her.

^13And when the Lord saw her, he had compassion on her, and said unto her, Weep not.

^14And he came and touched the bier: and they that bare him stood still. And he said, Young man, I say unto thee, Arise.

^15And he that was dead sat up, and began to speak. And he delivered him to his mother.

^16And there came a fear on all: and they glorified God, saying, That a great prophet is risen up among us; and, That God hath visited his people.

^17And this rumour of him went forth throughout all Judaea, and throughout all the region round about.

^18And the disciples of John shewed him of all these things.

^19And John calling unto him two of his disciples sent them to Jesus, saying, Art thou he that should come? or look we for another?

^20When the men were come unto him, they said, John Baptist hath sent us unto thee, saying, Art thou he that should come? or look we for another?

^21And in that same hour he cured many of their infirmities and plagues, and of evil spirits; and unto many that were blind he gave sight.

^22Then Jesus answering said unto them, Go your way, and tell John what things ye have seen and heard; how that the blind see, the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear, the dead are raised, to the poor the gospel is preached.

^23And blessed is he, whosoever shall not be offended in me.

^24And when the messengers of John were departed, he began to speak unto the people concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness for to see? A reed shaken with the wind?

^25But what went ye out for to see? A man clothed in soft raiment? Behold, they which are gorgeously apparelled, and live delicately, are in kings’ courts.

^26But what went ye out for to see? A prophet? Yea, I say unto you, and much more than a prophet.

^27This is he, of whom it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, which shall prepare thy way before thee.

^28For I say unto you, Among those that are born of women there is not a greater prophet than John the Baptist: but he that is least in the kingdom of God is greater than he.

^29And all the people that heard him, and the publicans, justified God, being baptized with the baptism of John.

^30But the Pharisees and lawyers rejected the counsel of God against themselves, being not baptized of him.

^31And the Lord said, Whereunto then shall I liken the men of this generation? and to what are they like?

^32They are like unto children sitting in the marketplace, and calling one to another, and saying, We have piped unto you, and ye have not danced; we have mourned to you, and ye have not wept.

^33For John the Baptist came neither eating bread nor drinking wine; and ye say, He hath a devil.

^34The Son of man is come eating and drinking; and ye say, Behold a gluttonous man, and a winebibber, a friend of publicans and sinners!

^35But wisdom is justified of all her children.

^36And one of the Pharisees desired him that he would eat with him. And he went into the Pharisee’s house, and sat down to meat.

^37And, behold, a woman in the city, which was a sinner, when she knew that Jesus sat at meat in the Pharisee’s house, brought an alabaster box of ointment,

^38And stood at his feet behind him weeping, and began to wash his feet with tears, and did wipe them with the hairs of her head, and kissed his feet, and anointed them with the ointment.

^39Now when the Pharisee which had bidden him saw it, he spake within himself, saying, This man, if he were a prophet, would have known who and what manner of woman this is that toucheth him: for she is a sinner.

^40And Jesus answering said unto him, Simon, I have somewhat to say unto thee. And he saith, Master, say on.

^41There was a certain creditor which had two debtors: the one owed five hundred pence, and the other fifty.

^42And when they had nothing to pay, he frankly forgave them both. Tell me therefore, which of them will love him most?

^43Simon answered and said, I suppose that he, to whom he forgave most. And he said unto him, Thou hast rightly judged.

^44And he turned to the woman, and said unto Simon, Seest thou this woman? I entered into thine house, thou gavest me no water for my feet: but she hath washed my feet with tears, and wiped them with the hairs of her head.

^45Thou gavest me no kiss: but this woman since the time I came in hath not ceased to kiss my feet.

^46My head with oil thou didst not anoint: but this woman hath anointed my feet with ointment.

^47Wherefore I say unto thee, Her sins, which are many, are forgiven; for she loved much: but to whom little is forgiven, the same loveth little.

^48And he said unto her, Thy sins are forgiven.

^49And they that sat at meat with him began to say within themselves, Who is this that forgiveth sins also?

^50And he said to the woman, Thy faith hath saved thee; go in peace.

VIII

8^1And it came to pass afterward, that he went throughout every city and village, preaching and shewing the glad tidings of the kingdom of God: and the twelve were with him,

^2And certain women, which had been healed of evil spirits and infirmities, Mary called Magdalene, out of whom went seven devils,

^3And Joanna the wife of Chuza Herod’s steward, and Susanna, and many others, which ministered unto him of their substance.

^4And when much people were gathered together, and were come to him out of every city, he spake by a parable:

^5A sower went out to sow his seed: and as he sowed, some fell by the way side; and it was trodden down, and the fowls of the air devoured it.

^6And some fell upon a rock; and as soon as it was sprung up, it withered away, because it lacked moisture.

^7And some fell among thorns; and the thorns sprang up with it, and choked it.

^8And other fell on good ground, and sprang up, and bare fruit an hundredfold. And when he had said these things, he cried, He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.

^9And his disciples asked him, saying, What might this parable be?

^10And he said, Unto you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of God: but to others in parables; that seeing they might not see, and hearing they might not understand.

^11Now the parable is this: The seed is the word of God.

^12Those by the way side are they that hear; then cometh the devil, and taketh away the word out of their hearts, lest they should believe and be saved.

^13They on the rock are they, which, when they hear, receive the word with joy; and these have no root, which for a while believe, and in time of temptation fall away.

^14And that which fell among thorns are they, which, when they have heard, go forth, and are choked with cares and riches and pleasures of this life, and bring no fruit to perfection.

^15But that on the good ground are they, which in an honest and good heart, having heard the word, keep it, and bring forth fruit with patience.

^16No man, when he hath lighted a candle, covereth it with a vessel, or putteth it under a bed; but setteth it on a candlestick, that they which enter in may see the light.

^17For nothing is secret, that shall not be made manifest; neither any thing hid, that shall not be known and come abroad.

^18Take heed therefore how ye hear: for whosoever hath, to him shall be given; and whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken even that which he seemeth to have.

^19Then came to him his mother and his brethren, and could not come at him for the press.

^20And it was told him by certain which said, Thy mother and thy brethren stand without, desiring to see thee.

^21And he answered and said unto them, My mother and my brethren are these which hear the word of God, and do it.

^22Now it came to pass on a certain day, that he went into a ship with his disciples: and he said unto them, Let us go over unto the other side of the lake. And they launched forth.

^23But as they sailed he fell asleep: and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and they were filled with water, and were in jeopardy.

^24And they came to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish. Then he arose, and rebuked the wind and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm.

^25And he said unto them, Where is your faith? And they being afraid wondered, saying one to another, What manner of man is this! for he commandeth even the winds and water, and they obey him.

^26And they arrived at the country of the Gadarenes, which is over against Galilee.

^27And when he went forth to land, there met him out of the city a certain man, which had devils long time, and ware no clothes, neither abode in any house, but in the tombs.

^28When he saw Jesus, he cried out, and fell down before him, and with a loud voice said, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, thou Son of God most high? I beseech thee, torment me not.

^29(For he had commanded the unclean spirit to come out of the man. For oftentimes it had caught him: and he was kept bound with chains and in fetters; and he brake the bands, and was driven of the devil into the wilderness.)

^30And Jesus asked him, saying, What is thy name? And he said, Legion: because many devils were entered into him.

^31And they besought him that he would not command them to go out into the deep.

^32And there was there an herd of many swine feeding on the mountain: and they besought him that he would suffer them to enter into them. And he suffered them.

^33Then went the devils out of the man, and entered into the swine: and the herd ran violently down a steep place into the lake, and were choked.

^34When they that fed them saw what was done, they fled, and went and told it in the city and in the country.

^35Then they went out to see what was done; and came to Jesus, and found the man, out of whom the devils were departed, sitting at the feet of Jesus, clothed, and in his right mind: and they were afraid.

^36They also which saw it told them by what means he that was possessed of the devils was healed.

^37Then the whole multitude of the country of the Gadarenes round about besought him to depart from them; for they were taken with great fear: and he went up into the ship, and returned back again.

^38Now the man out of whom the devils were departed besought him that he might be with him: but Jesus sent him away, saying,

^39Return to thine own house, and shew how great things God hath done unto thee. And he went his way, and published throughout the whole city how great things Jesus had done unto him.

^40And it came to pass, that, when Jesus was returned, the people gladly received him: for they were all waiting for him.

^41And, behold, there came a man named Jairus, and he was a ruler of the synagogue: and he fell down at Jesus’ feet, and besought him that he would come into his house:

^42For he had one only daughter, about twelve years of age, and she lay a dying. But as he went the people thronged him.

^43And a woman having an issue of blood twelve years, which had spent all her living upon physicians, neither could be healed of any,

^44Came behind him, and touched the border of his garment: and immediately her issue of blood stanched.

^45And Jesus said, Who touched me? When all denied, Peter and they that were with him said, Master, the multitude throng thee and press thee, and sayest thou, Who touched me?

^46And Jesus said, Somebody hath touched me: for I perceive that virtue is gone out of me.

^47And when the woman saw that she was not hid, she came trembling, and falling down before him, she declared unto him before all the people for what cause she had touched him, and how she was healed immediately.

^48And he said unto her, Daughter, be of good comfort: thy faith hath made thee whole; go in peace.

^49While he yet spake, there cometh one from the ruler of the synagogue’s house, saying to him, Thy daughter is dead; trouble not the Master.

^50But when Jesus heard it, he answered him, saying, Fear not: believe only, and she shall be made whole.

^51And when he came into the house, he suffered no man to go in, save Peter, and James, and John, and the father and the mother of the maiden.

^52And all wept, and bewailed her: but he said, Weep not; she is not dead, but sleepeth.

^53And they laughed him to scorn, knowing that she was dead.

^54And he put them all out, and took her by the hand, and called, saying, Maid, arise.

^55And her spirit came again, and she arose straightway: and he commanded to give her meat.

^56And her parents were astonished: but he charged them that they should tell no man what was done.

IX

9^1Then he called his twelve disciples together, and gave them power and authority over all devils, and to cure diseases.

^2And he sent them to preach the kingdom of God, and to heal the sick.

^3And he said unto them, Take nothing for your journey, neither staves, nor scrip, neither bread, neither money; neither have two coats apiece.

^4And whatsoever house ye enter into, there abide, and thence depart.

^5And whosoever will not receive you, when ye go out of that city, shake off the very dust from your feet for a testimony against them.

^6And they departed, and went through the towns, preaching the gospel, and healing every where.

^7Now Herod the tetrarch heard of all that was done by him: and he was perplexed, because that it was said of some, that John was risen from the dead;

^8And of some, that Elias had appeared; and of others, that one of the old prophets was risen again.

^9And Herod said, John have I beheaded: but who is this, of whom I hear such things? And he desired to see him.

^10And the apostles, when they were returned, told him all that they had done. And he took them, and went aside privately into a desert place belonging to the city called Bethsaida.

^11And the people, when they knew it, followed him: and he received them, and spake unto them of the kingdom of God, and healed them that had need of healing.

^12And when the day began to wear away, then came the twelve, and said unto him, Send the multitude away, that they may go into the towns and country round about, and lodge, and get victuals: for we are here in a desert place.

^13But he said unto them, Give ye them to eat. And they said, We have no more but five loaves and two fishes; except we should go and buy meat for all this people.

^14For they were about five thousand men. And he said to his disciples, Make them sit down by fifties in a company.

^15And they did so, and made them all sit down.

^16Then he took the five loaves and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed them, and brake, and gave to the disciples to set before the multitude.

^17And they did eat, and were all filled: and there was taken up of fragments that remained to them twelve baskets.

^18And it came to pass, as he was alone praying, his disciples were with him: and he asked them, saying, Whom say the people that I am?

^19They answering said, John the Baptist; but some say, Elias; and others say, that one of the old prophets is risen again.

^20He said unto them, But whom say ye that I am? Peter answering said, The Christ of God.

^21And he straitly charged them, and commanded them to tell no man that thing;

^22Saying, The Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be slain, and be raised the third day.

^23And he said to them all, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow me.

^24For whosoever will save his life shall lose it: but whosoever will lose his life for my sake, the same shall save it.

^25For what is a man advantaged, if he gain the whole world, and lose himself, or be cast away?

^26For whosoever shall be ashamed of me and of my words, of him shall the Son of man be ashamed, when he shall come in his own glory, and in his Father’s, and of the holy angels.

^27But I tell you of a truth, there be some standing here, which shall not taste of death, till they see the kingdom of God.

^28And it came to pass about an eight days after these sayings, he took Peter and John and James, and went up into a mountain to pray.

^29And as he prayed, the fashion of his countenance was altered, and his raiment was white and glistering.

^30And, behold, there talked with him two men, which were Moses and Elias:

^31Who appeared in glory, and spake of his decease which he should accomplish at Jerusalem.

^32But Peter and they that were with him were heavy with sleep: and when they were awake, they saw his glory, and the two men that stood with him.

^33And it came to pass, as they departed from him, Peter said unto Jesus, Master, it is good for us to be here: and let us make three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elias: not knowing what he said.

^34While he thus spake, there came a cloud, and overshadowed them: and they feared as they entered into the cloud.

^35And there came a voice out of the cloud, saying, This is my beloved Son: hear him.

^36And when the voice was past, Jesus was found alone. And they kept it close, and told no man in those days any of those things which they had seen.

^37And it came to pass, that on the next day, when they were come down from the hill, much people met him.

^38And, behold, a man of the company cried out, saying, Master, I beseech thee, look upon my son: for he is mine only child.

^39And, lo, a spirit taketh him, and he suddenly crieth out; and it teareth him that he foameth again, and bruising him hardly departeth from him.

^40And I besought thy disciples to cast him out; and they could not.

^41And Jesus answering said, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you, and suffer you? Bring thy son hither.

^42And as he was yet a coming, the devil threw him down, and tare him. And Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, and healed the child, and delivered him again to his father.

^43And they were all amazed at the mighty power of God. But while they wondered every one at all things which Jesus did, he said unto his disciples,

^44Let these sayings sink down into your ears: for the Son of man shall be delivered into the hands of men.

^45But they understood not this saying, and it was hid from them, that they perceived it not: and they feared to ask him of that saying.

^46Then there arose a reasoning among them, which of them should be greatest.

^47And Jesus, perceiving the thought of their heart, took a child, and set him by him,

^48And said unto them, Whosoever shall receive this child in my name receiveth me: and whosoever shall receive me receiveth him that sent me: for he that is least among you all, the same shall be great.

^49And John answered and said, Master, we saw one casting out devils in thy name; and we forbad him, because he followeth not with us.

^50And Jesus said unto him, Forbid him not: for he that is not against us is for us.

^51And it came to pass, when the time was come that he should be received up, he stedfastly set his face to go to Jerusalem,

^52And sent messengers before his face: and they went, and entered into a village of the Samaritans, to make ready for him.

^53And they did not receive him, because his face was as though he would go to Jerusalem.

^54And when his disciples James and John saw this, they said, Lord, wilt thou that we command fire to come down from heaven, and consume them, even as Elias did?

^55But he turned, and rebuked them, and said, Ye know not what manner of spirit ye are of.

^56For the Son of man is not come to destroy men’s lives, but to save them. And they went to another village.

^57And it came to pass, that, as they went in the way, a certain man said unto him, Lord, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest.

^58And Jesus said unto him, Foxes have holes, and birds of the air have nests; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head.

^59And he said unto another, Follow me. But he said, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father.

^60Jesus said unto him, Let the dead bury their dead: but go thou and preach the kingdom of God.

^61And another also said, Lord, I will follow thee; but let me first go bid them farewell, which are at home at my house.

^62And Jesus said unto him, No man, having put his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit for the kingdom of God.

X

10^1After these things the Lord appointed other seventy also, and sent them two and two before his face into every city and place, whither he himself would come.

^2Therefore said he unto them, The harvest truly is great, but the labourers are few: pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he would send forth labourers into his harvest.

^3Go your ways: behold, I send you forth as lambs among wolves.

^4Carry neither purse, nor scrip, nor shoes: and salute no man by the way.

^5And into whatsoever house ye enter, first say, Peace be to this house.

^6And if the son of peace be there, your peace shall rest upon it: if not, it shall turn to you again.

^7And in the same house remain, eating and drinking such things as they give: for the labourer is worthy of his hire. Go not from house to house.

^8And into whatsoever city ye enter, and they receive you, eat such things as are set before you:

^9And heal the sick that are therein, and say unto them, The kingdom of God is come nigh unto you.

^10But into whatsoever city ye enter, and they receive you not, go your ways out into the streets of the same, and say,

^11Even the very dust of your city, which cleaveth on us, we do wipe off against you: notwithstanding be ye sure of this, that the kingdom of God is come nigh unto you.

^12But I say unto you, that it shall be more tolerable in that day for Sodom, than for that city.

^13Woe unto thee, Chorazin! woe unto thee, Bethsaida! for if the mighty works had been done in Tyre and Sidon, which have been done in you, they had a great while ago repented, sitting in sackcloth and ashes.

^14But it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the judgment, than for you.

^15And thou, Capernaum, which art exalted to heaven, shalt be thrust down to hell.

^16He that heareth you heareth me; and he that despiseth you despiseth me; and he that despiseth me despiseth him that sent me.

^17And the seventy returned again with joy, saying, Lord, even the devils are subject unto us through thy name.

^18And he said unto them, I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heaven.

^19Behold, I give unto you power to tread on serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy: and nothing shall by any means hurt you.

^20Notwithstanding in this rejoice not, that the spirits are subject unto you; but rather rejoice, because your names are written in heaven.

^21In that hour Jesus rejoiced in spirit, and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes: even so, Father; for so it seemed good in thy sight.

^22All things are delivered to me of my Father: and no man knoweth who the Son is, but the Father; and who the Father is, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him.

^23And he turned him unto his disciples, and said privately, Blessed are the eyes which see the things that ye see:

^24For I tell you, that many prophets and kings have desired to see those things which ye see, and have not seen them; and to hear those things which ye hear, and have not heard them.

^25And, behold, a certain lawyer stood up, and tempted him, saying, Master, what shall I do to inherit eternal life?

^26He said unto him, What is written in the law? how readest thou?

^27And he answering said, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind; and thy neighbour as thyself.

^28And he said unto him, Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt live.

^29But he, willing to justify himself, said unto Jesus, And who is my neighbour?

^30And Jesus answering said, A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Jericho, and fell among thieves, which stripped him of his raiment, and wounded him, and departed, leaving him half dead.

^31And by chance there came down a certain priest that way: and when he saw him, he passed by on the other side.

^32And likewise a Levite, when he was at the place, came and looked on him, and passed by on the other side.

^33But a certain Samaritan, as he journeyed, came where he was: and when he saw him, he had compassion on him,

^34And went to him, and bound up his wounds, pouring in oil and wine, and set him on his own beast, and brought him to an inn, and took care of him.

^35And on the morrow when he departed, he took out two pence, and gave them to the host, and said unto him, Take care of him; and whatsoever thou spendest more, when I come again, I will repay thee.

^36Which now of these three, thinkest thou, was neighbour unto him that fell among the thieves?

^37And he said, He that shewed mercy on him. Then said Jesus unto him, Go, and do thou likewise.

^38Now it came to pass, as they went, that he entered into a certain village: and a certain woman named Martha received him into her house.

^39And she had a sister called Mary, which also sat at Jesus’ feet, and heard his word.

^40But Martha was cumbered about much serving, and came to him, and said, Lord, dost thou not care that my sister hath left me to serve alone? bid her therefore that she help me.

^41And Jesus answered and said unto her, Martha, Martha, thou art careful and troubled about many things:

^42But one thing is needful: and Mary hath chosen that good part, which shall not be taken away from her.

XI

11^1And it came to pass, that, as he was praying in a certain place, when he ceased, one of his disciples said unto him, Lord, teach us to pray, as John also taught his disciples.

^2And he said unto them, When ye pray, say, Our Father which art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done, as in heaven, so in earth.

^3Give us day by day our daily bread.

^4And forgive us our sins; for we also forgive every one that is indebted to us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from evil.

^5And he said unto them, Which of you shall have a friend, and shall go unto him at midnight, and say unto him, Friend, lend me three loaves;

^6For a friend of mine in his journey is come to me, and I have nothing to set before him?

^7And he from within shall answer and say, Trouble me not: the door is now shut, and my children are with me in bed; I cannot rise and give thee.

^8I say unto you, Though he will not rise and give him, because he is his friend, yet because of his importunity he will rise and give him as many as he needeth.

^9And I say unto you, Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you.

^10For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth; and to him that knocketh it shall be opened.

^11If a son shall ask bread of any of you that is a father, will he give him a stone? or if he ask a fish, will he for a fish give him a serpent?

^12Or if he shall ask an egg, will he offer him a scorpion?

^13If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your children: how much more shall your heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him?

^14And he was casting out a devil, and it was dumb. And it came to pass, when the devil was gone out, the dumb spake; and the people wondered.

^15But some of them said, He casteth out devils through Beelzebub the chief of the devils.

^16And others, tempting him, sought of him a sign from heaven.

^17But he, knowing their thoughts, said unto them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and a house divided against a house falleth.

^18If Satan also be divided against himself, how shall his kingdom stand? because ye say that I cast out devils through Beelzebub.

^19And if I by Beelzebub cast out devils, by whom do your sons cast them out? therefore shall they be your judges.

^20But if I with the finger of God cast out devils, no doubt the kingdom of God is come upon you.

^21When a strong man armed keepeth his palace, his goods are in peace:

^22But when a stronger than he shall come upon him, and overcome him, he taketh from him all his armour wherein he trusted, and divideth his spoils.

^23He that is not with me is against me: and he that gathereth not with me scattereth.

^24When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, seeking rest; and finding none, he saith, I will return unto my house whence I came out.

^25And when he cometh, he findeth it swept and garnished.

^26Then goeth he, and taketh to him seven other spirits more wicked than himself; and they enter in, and dwell there: and the last state of that man is worse than the first.

^27And it came to pass, as he spake these things, a certain woman of the company lifted up her voice, and said unto him, Blessed is the womb that bare thee, and the paps which thou hast sucked.

^28But he said, Yea rather, blessed are they that hear the word of God, and keep it.

^29And when the people were gathered thick together, he began to say, This is an evil generation: they seek a sign; and there shall no sign be given it, but the sign of Jonas the prophet.

^30For as Jonas was a sign unto the Ninevites, so shall also the Son of man be to this generation.

^31The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with the men of this generation, and condemn them: for she came from the utmost parts of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and, behold, a greater than Solomon is here.

^32The men of Nineve shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for they repented at the preaching of Jonas; and, behold, a greater than Jonas is here.

^33No man, when he hath lighted a candle, putteth it in a secret place, neither under a bushel, but on a candlestick, that they which come in may see the light.

^34The light of the body is the eye: therefore when thine eye is single, thy whole body also is full of light; but when thine eye is evil, thy body also is full of darkness.

^35Take heed therefore that the light which is in thee be not darkness.

^36If thy whole body therefore be full of light, having no part dark, the whole shall be full of light, as when the bright shining of a candle doth give thee light.

^37And as he spake, a certain Pharisee besought him to dine with him: and he went in, and sat down to meat.

^38And when the Pharisee saw it, he marvelled that he had not first washed before dinner.

^39And the Lord said unto him, Now do ye Pharisees make clean the outside of the cup and the platter; but your inward part is full of ravening and wickedness.

^40Ye fools, did not he that made that which is without make that which is within also?

^41But rather give alms of such things as ye have; and, behold, all things are clean unto you.

^42But woe unto you, Pharisees! for ye tithe mint and rue and all manner of herbs, and pass over judgment and the love of God: these ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone.

^43Woe unto you, Pharisees! for ye love the uppermost seats in the synagogues, and greetings in the markets.

^44Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are as graves which appear not, and the men that walk over them are not aware of them.

^45Then answered one of the lawyers, and said unto him, Master, thus saying thou reproachest us also.

^46And he said, Woe unto you also, ye lawyers! for ye lade men with burdens grievous to be borne, and ye yourselves touch not the burdens with one of your fingers.

^47Woe unto you! for ye build the sepulchres of the prophets, and your fathers killed them.

^48Truly ye bear witness that ye allow the deeds of your fathers: for they indeed killed them, and ye build their sepulchres.

^49Therefore also said the wisdom of God, I will send them prophets and apostles, and some of them they shall slay and persecute:

^50That the blood of all the prophets, which was shed from the foundation of the world, may be required of this generation;

^51From the blood of Abel unto the blood of Zacharias which perished between the altar and the temple: verily I say unto you, It shall be required of this generation.

^52Woe unto you, lawyers! for ye have taken away the key of knowledge: ye entered not in yourselves, and them that were entering in ye hindered.

^53And as he said these things unto them, the scribes and the Pharisees began to urge him vehemently, and to provoke him to speak of many things:

^54Laying wait for him, and seeking to catch something out of his mouth, that they might accuse him.

XII

12^1In the mean time, when there were gathered together an innumerable multitude of people, insomuch that they trode one upon another, he began to say unto his disciples first of all, Beware ye of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy.

^2For there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; neither hid, that shall not be known.

^3Therefore whatsoever ye have spoken in darkness shall be heard in the light; and that which ye have spoken in the ear in closets shall be proclaimed upon the housetops.

^4And I say unto you my friends, Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do.

^5But I will forewarn you whom ye shall fear: Fear him, which after he hath killed hath power to cast into hell; yea, I say unto you, Fear him.

^6Are not five sparrows sold for two farthings, and not one of them is forgotten before God?

^7But even the very hairs of your head are all numbered. Fear not therefore: ye are of more value than many sparrows.

^8Also I say unto you, Whosoever shall confess me before men, him shall the Son of man also confess before the angels of God:

^9But he that denieth me before men shall be denied before the angels of God.

^10And whosoever shall speak a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but unto him that blasphemeth against the Holy Ghost it shall not be forgiven.

^11And when they bring you unto the synagogues, and unto magistrates, and powers, take ye no thought how or what thing ye shall answer, or what ye shall say:

^12For the Holy Ghost shall teach you in the same hour what ye ought to say.

^13And one of the company said unto him, Master, speak to my brother, that he divide the inheritance with me.

^14And he said unto him, Man, who made me a judge or a divider over you?

^15And he said unto them, Take heed, and beware of covetousness: for a man’s life consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he possesseth.

^16And he spake a parable unto them, saying, The ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully:

^17And he thought within himself, saying, What shall I do, because I have no room where to bestow my fruits?

^18And he said, This will I do: I will pull down my barns, and build greater; and there will I bestow all my fruits and my goods.

^19And I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast much goods laid up for many years; take thine ease, eat, drink, and be merry.

^20But God said unto him, Thou fool, this night thy soul shall be required of thee: then whose shall those things be, which thou hast provided?

^21So is he that layeth up treasure for himself, and is not rich toward God.

^22And he said unto his disciples, Therefore I say unto you, Take no thought for your life, what ye shall eat; neither for the body, what ye shall put on.

^23The life is more than meat, and the body is more than raiment.

^24Consider the ravens: for they neither sow nor reap; which neither have storehouse nor barn; and God feedeth them: how much more are ye better than the fowls?

^25And which of you with taking thought can add to his stature one cubit?

^26If ye then be not able to do that thing which is least, why take ye thought for the rest?

^27Consider the lilies how they grow: they toil not, they spin not; and yet I say unto you, that Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these.

^28If then God so clothe the grass, which is to day in the field, and to morrow is cast into the oven; how much more will he clothe you, O ye of little faith?

^29And seek not ye what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink, neither be ye of doubtful mind.

^30For all these things do the nations of the world seek after: and your Father knoweth that ye have need of these things.

^31But rather seek ye the kingdom of God; and all these things shall be added unto you.

^32Fear not, little flock; for it is your Father’s good pleasure to give you the kingdom.

^33Sell that ye have, and give alms; provide yourselves bags which wax not old, a treasure in the heavens that faileth not, where no thief approacheth, neither moth corrupteth.

^34For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.

^35Let your loins be girded about, and your lights burning;

^36And ye yourselves like unto men that wait for their lord, when he will return from the wedding; that when he cometh and knocketh, they may open unto him immediately.

^37Blessed are those servants, whom the lord when he cometh shall find watching: verily I say unto you, that he shall gird himself, and make them to sit down to meat, and will come forth and serve them.

^38And if he shall come in the second watch, or come in the third watch, and find them so, blessed are those servants.

^39And this know, that if the goodman of the house had known what hour the thief would come, he would have watched, and not have suffered his house to be broken through.

^40Be ye therefore ready also: for the Son of man cometh at an hour when ye think not.

^41Then Peter said unto him, Lord, speakest thou this parable unto us, or even to all?

^42And the Lord said, Who then is that faithful and wise steward, whom his lord shall make ruler over his household, to give them their portion of meat in due season?

^43Blessed is that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find so doing.

^44Of a truth I say unto you, that he will make him ruler over all that he hath.

^45But and if that servant say in his heart, My lord delayeth his coming; and shall begin to beat the menservants and maidens, and to eat and drink, and to be drunken;

^46The lord of that servant will come in a day when he looketh not for him, and at an hour when he is not aware, and will cut him in sunder, and will appoint him his portion with the unbelievers.

^47And that servant, which knew his lord’s will, and prepared not himself, neither did according to his will, shall be beaten with many stripes.

^48But he that knew not, and did commit things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few stripes. For unto whomsoever much is given, of him shall be much required: and to whom men have committed much, of him they will ask the more.

^49I am come to send fire on the earth; and what will I, if it be already kindled?

^50But I have a baptism to be baptized with; and how am I straitened till it be accomplished!

^51Suppose ye that I am come to give peace on earth? I tell you, Nay; but rather division:

^52For from henceforth there shall be five in one house divided, three against two, and two against three.

^53The father shall be divided against the son, and the son against the father; the mother against the daughter, and the daughter against the mother; the mother in law against her daughter in law, and the daughter in law against her mother in law.

^54And he said also to the people, When ye see a cloud rise out of the west, straightway ye say, There cometh a shower; and so it is.

^55And when ye see the south wind blow, ye say, There will be heat; and it cometh to pass.

^56Ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky and of the earth; but how is it that ye do not discern this time?

^57Yea, and why even of yourselves judge ye not what is right?

^58When thou goest with thine adversary to the magistrate, as thou art in the way, give diligence that thou mayest be delivered from him; lest he hale thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and the officer cast thee into prison.

^59I tell thee, thou shalt not depart thence, till thou hast paid the very last mite.

XIII

13^1There were present at that season some that told him of the Galilaeans, whose blood Pilate had mingled with their sacrifices.

^2And Jesus answering said unto them, Suppose ye that these Galilaeans were sinners above all the Galilaeans, because they suffered such things?

^3I tell you, Nay: but, except ye repent, ye shall all likewise perish.

^4Or those eighteen, upon whom the tower in Siloam fell, and slew them, think ye that they were sinners above all men that dwelt in Jerusalem?

^5I tell you, Nay: but, except ye repent, ye shall all likewise perish.

^6He spake also this parable; A certain man had a fig tree planted in his vineyard; and he came and sought fruit thereon, and found none.

^7Then said he unto the dresser of his vineyard, Behold, these three years I come seeking fruit on this fig tree, and find none: cut it down; why cumbereth it the ground?

^8And he answering said unto him, Lord, let it alone this year also, till I shall dig about it, and dung it:

^9And if it bear fruit, well: and if not, then after that thou shalt cut it down.

^10And he was teaching in one of the synagogues on the sabbath.

^11And, behold, there was a woman which had a spirit of infirmity eighteen years, and was bowed together, and could in no wise lift up herself.

^12And when Jesus saw her, he called her to him, and said unto her, Woman, thou art loosed from thine infirmity.

^13And he laid his hands on her: and immediately she was made straight, and glorified God.

^14And the ruler of the synagogue answered with indignation, because that Jesus had healed on the sabbath day, and said unto the people, There are six days in which men ought to work: in them therefore come and be healed, and not on the sabbath day.

^15The Lord then answered him, and said, Thou hypocrite, doth not each one of you on the sabbath loose his ox or his ass from the stall, and lead him away to watering?

^16And ought not this woman, being a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan hath bound, lo, these eighteen years, be loosed from this bond on the sabbath day?

^17And when he had said these things, all his adversaries were ashamed: and all the people rejoiced for all the glorious things that were done by him.

^18Then said he, Unto what is the kingdom of God like? and whereunto shall I resemble it?

^19It is like a grain of mustard seed, which a man took, and cast into his garden; and it grew, and waxed a great tree; and the fowls of the air lodged in the branches of it.

^20And again he said, Whereunto shall I liken the kingdom of God?

^21It is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of meal, till the whole was leavened.

^22And he went through the cities and villages, teaching, and journeying toward Jerusalem.

^23Then said one unto him, Lord, are there few that be saved? And he said unto them,

^24Strive to enter in at the strait gate: for many, I say unto you, will seek to enter in, and shall not be able.

^25When once the master of the house is risen up, and hath shut to the door, and ye begin to stand without, and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, Lord, open unto us; and he shall answer and say unto you, I know you not whence ye are:

^26Then shall ye begin to say, We have eaten and drunk in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets.

^27But he shall say, I tell you, I know you not whence ye are; depart from me, all ye workers of iniquity.

^28There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth, when ye shall see Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the prophets, in the kingdom of God, and you yourselves thrust out.

^29And they shall come from the east, and from the west, and from the north, and from the south, and shall sit down in the kingdom of God.

^30And, behold, there are last which shall be first, and there are first which shall be last.

^31The same day there came certain of the Pharisees, saying unto him, Get thee out, and depart hence: for Herod will kill thee.

^32And he said unto them, Go ye, and tell that fox, Behold, I cast out devils, and I do cures to day and to morrow, and the third day I shall be perfected.

^33Nevertheless I must walk to day, and to morrow, and the day following: for it cannot be that a prophet perish out of Jerusalem.

^34O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, which killest the prophets, and stonest them that are sent unto thee; how often would I have gathered thy children together, as a hen doth gather her brood under her wings, and ye would not!

^35Behold, your house is left unto you desolate: and verily I say unto you, Ye shall not see me, until the time come when ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.

XIV

14^1And it came to pass, as he went into the house of one of the chief Pharisees to eat bread on the sabbath day, that they watched him.

^2And, behold, there was a certain man before him which had the dropsy.

^3And Jesus answering spake unto the lawyers and Pharisees, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath day?

^4And they held their peace. And he took him, and healed him, and let him go;

^5And answered them, saying, Which of you shall have an ass or an ox fallen into a pit, and will not straightway pull him out on the sabbath day?

^6And they could not answer him again to these things.

^7And he put forth a parable to those which were bidden, when he marked how they chose out the chief rooms; saying unto them.

^8When thou art bidden of any man to a wedding, sit not down in the highest room; lest a more honourable man than thou be bidden of him;

^9And he that bade thee and him come and say to thee, Give this man place; and thou begin with shame to take the lowest room.

^10But when thou art bidden, go and sit down in the lowest room; that when he that bade thee cometh, he may say unto thee, Friend, go up higher: then shalt thou have worship in the presence of them that sit at meat with thee.

^11For whosoever exalteth himself shall be abased; and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted.

^12Then said he also to him that bade him, When thou makest a dinner or a supper, call not thy friends, nor thy brethren, neither thy kinsmen, nor thy rich neighbours; lest they also bid thee again, and a recompence be made thee.

^13But when thou makest a feast, call the poor, the maimed, the lame, the blind:

^14And thou shalt be blessed; for they cannot recompense thee: for thou shalt be recompensed at the resurrection of the just.

^15And when one of them that sat at meat with him heard these things, he said unto him, Blessed is he that shall eat bread in the kingdom of God.

^16Then said he unto him, A certain man made a great supper, and bade many:

^17And sent his servant at supper time to say to them that were bidden, Come; for all things are now ready.

^18And they all with one consent began to make excuse. The first said unto him, I have bought a piece of ground, and I must needs go and see it: I pray thee have me excused.

^19And another said, I have bought five yoke of oxen, and I go to prove them: I pray thee have me excused.

^20And another said, I have married a wife, and therefore I cannot come.

^21So that servant came, and shewed his lord these things. Then the master of the house being angry said to his servant, Go out quickly into the streets and lanes of the city, and bring in hither the poor, and the maimed, and the halt, and the blind.

^22And the servant said, Lord, it is done as thou hast commanded, and yet there is room.

^23And the lord said unto the servant, Go out into the highways and hedges, and compel them to come in, that my house may be filled.

^24For I say unto you, That none of those men which were bidden shall taste of my supper.

^25And there went great multitudes with him: and he turned, and said unto them,

^26If any man come to me, and hate not his father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and sisters, yea, and his own life also, he cannot be my disciple.

^27And whosoever doth not bear his cross, and come after me, cannot be my disciple.

^28For which of you, intending to build a tower, sitteth not down first, and counteth the cost, whether he have sufficient to finish it?

^29Lest haply, after he hath laid the foundation, and is not able to finish it, all that behold it begin to mock him,

^30Saying, This man began to build, and was not able to finish.

^31Or what king, going to make war against another king, sitteth not down first, and consulteth whether he be able with ten thousand to meet him that cometh against him with twenty thousand?

^32Or else, while the other is yet a great way off, he sendeth an ambassage, and desireth conditions of peace.

^33So likewise, whosoever he be of you that forsaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my disciple.

^34Salt is good: but if the salt have lost his savour, wherewith shall it be seasoned?

^35It is neither fit for the land, nor yet for the dunghill; but men cast it out. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.

XV

15^1Then drew near unto him all the publicans and sinners for to hear him.

^2And the Pharisees and scribes murmured, saying, This man receiveth sinners, and eateth with them.

^3And he spake this parable unto them, saying,

^4What man of you, having an hundred sheep, if he lose one of them, doth not leave the ninety and nine in the wilderness, and go after that which is lost, until he find it?

^5And when he hath found it, he layeth it on his shoulders, rejoicing.

^6And when he cometh home, he calleth together his friends and neighbours, saying unto them, Rejoice with me; for I have found my sheep which was lost.

^7I say unto you, that likewise joy shall be in heaven over one sinner that repenteth, more than over ninety and nine just persons, which need no repentance.

^8Either what woman having ten pieces of silver, if she lose one piece, doth not light a candle, and sweep the house, and seek diligently till she find it?

^9And when she hath found it, she calleth her friends and her neighbours together, saying, Rejoice with me; for I have found the piece which I had lost.

^10Likewise, I say unto you, there is joy in the presence of the angels of God over one sinner that repenteth.

^11And he said, A certain man had two sons:

^12And the younger of them said to his father, Father, give me the portion of goods that falleth to me. And he divided unto them his living.

^13And not many days after the younger son gathered all together, and took his journey into a far country, and there wasted his substance with riotous living.

^14And when he had spent all, there arose a mighty famine in that land; and he began to be in want.

^15And he went and joined himself to a citizen of that country; and he sent him into his fields to feed swine.

^16And he would fain have filled his belly with the husks that the swine did eat: and no man gave unto him.

^17And when he came to himself, he said, How many hired servants of my father’s have bread enough and to spare, and I perish with hunger!

^18I will arise and go to my father, and will say unto him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and before thee,

^19And am no more worthy to be called thy son: make me as one of thy hired servants.

^20And he arose, and came to his father. But when he was yet a great way off, his father saw him, and had compassion, and ran, and fell on his neck, and kissed him.

^21And the son said unto him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and in thy sight, and am no more worthy to be called thy son.

^22But the father said to his servants, Bring forth the best robe, and put it on him; and put a ring on his hand, and shoes on his feet:

^23And bring hither the fatted calf, and kill it; and let us eat, and be merry:

^24For this my son was dead, and is alive again; he was lost, and is found. And they began to be merry.

^25Now his elder son was in the field: and as he came and drew nigh to the house, he heard musick and dancing.

^26And he called one of the servants, and asked what these things meant.

^27And he said unto him, Thy brother is come; and thy father hath killed the fatted calf, because he hath received him safe and sound.

^28And he was angry, and would not go in: therefore came his father out, and intreated him.

^29And he answering said to his father, Lo, these many years do I serve thee, neither transgressed I at any time thy commandment: and yet thou never gavest me a kid, that I might make merry with my friends:

^30But as soon as this thy son was come, which hath devoured thy living with harlots, thou hast killed for him the fatted calf.

^31And he said unto him, Son, thou art ever with me, and all that I have is thine.

^32It was meet that we should make merry, and be glad: for this thy brother was dead, and is alive again; and was lost, and is found.

XVI

16^1And he said also unto his disciples, There was a certain rich man, which had a steward; and the same was accused unto him that he had wasted his goods.

^2And he called him, and said unto him, How is it that I hear this of thee? give an account of thy stewardship; for thou mayest be no longer steward.

^3Then the steward said within himself, What shall I do? for my lord taketh away from me the stewardship: I cannot dig; to beg I am ashamed.

^4I am resolved what to do, that, when I am put out of the stewardship, they may receive me into their houses.

^5So he called every one of his lord’s debtors unto him, and said unto the first, How much owest thou unto my lord?

^6And he said, An hundred measures of oil. And he said unto him, Take thy bill, and sit down quickly, and write fifty.

^7Then said he to another, And how much owest thou? And he said, An hundred measures of wheat. And he said unto him, Take thy bill, and write fourscore.

^8And the lord commended the unjust steward, because he had done wisely: for the children of this world are in their generation wiser than the children of light.

^9And I say unto you, Make to yourselves friends of the mammon of unrighteousness; that, when ye fail, they may receive you into everlasting habitations.

^10He that is faithful in that which is least is faithful also in much: and he that is unjust in the least is unjust also in much.

^11If therefore ye have not been faithful in the unrighteous mammon, who will commit to your trust the true riches?

^12And if ye have not been faithful in that which is another man’s, who shall give you that which is your own?

^13No servant can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon.

^14And the Pharisees also, who were covetous, heard all these things: and they derided him.

^15And he said unto them, Ye are they which justify yourselves before men; but God knoweth your hearts: for that which is highly esteemed among men is abomination in the sight of God.

^16The law and the prophets were until John: since that time the kingdom of God is preached, and every man presseth into it.

^17And it is easier for heaven and earth to pass, than one tittle of the law to fail.

^18Whosoever putteth away his wife, and marrieth another, committeth adultery: and whosoever marrieth her that is put away from her husband committeth adultery.

^19There was a certain rich man, which was clothed in purple and fine linen, and fared sumptuously every day:

^20And there was a certain beggar named Lazarus, which was laid at his gate, full of sores,

^21And desiring to be fed with the crumbs which fell from the rich man’s table: moreover the dogs came and licked his sores.

^22And it came to pass, that the beggar died, and was carried by the angels into Abraham’s bosom: the rich man also died, and was buried;

^23And in hell he lift up his eyes, being in torments, and seeth Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom.

^24And he cried and said, Father Abraham, have mercy on me, and send Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and cool my tongue; for I am tormented in this flame.

^25But Abraham said, Son, remember that thou in thy lifetime receivedst thy good things, and likewise Lazarus evil things: but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.

^26And beside all this, between us and you there is a great gulf fixed: so that they which would pass from hence to you cannot; neither can they pass to us, that would come from thence.

^27Then he said, I pray thee therefore, father, that thou wouldest send him to my father’s house:

^28For I have five brethren; that he may testify unto them, lest they also come into this place of torment.

^29Abraham saith unto him, They have Moses and the prophets; let them hear them.

^30And he said, Nay, father Abraham: but if one went unto them from the dead, they will repent.

^31And he said unto him, If they hear not Moses and the prophets, neither will they be persuaded, though one rose from the dead.

XVII

17^1Then said he unto the disciples, It is impossible but that offences will come: but woe unto him, through whom they come!

^2It were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and he cast into the sea, than that he should offend one of these little ones.

^3Take heed to yourselves: If thy brother trespass against thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him.

^4And if he trespass against thee seven times in a day, and seven times in a day turn again to thee, saying, I repent; thou shalt forgive him.

^5And the apostles said unto the Lord, Increase our faith.

^6And the Lord said, If ye had faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye might say unto this sycamine tree, Be thou plucked up by the root, and be thou planted in the sea; and it should obey you.

^7But which of you, having a servant plowing or feeding cattle, will say unto him by and by, when he is come from the field, Go and sit down to meat?

^8And will not rather say unto him, Make ready wherewith I may sup, and gird thyself, and serve me, till I have eaten and drunken; and afterward thou shalt eat and drink?

^9Doth he thank that servant because he did the things that were commanded him? I trow not.

^10So likewise ye, when ye shall have done all those things which are commanded you, say, We are unprofitable servants: we have done that which was our duty to do.

^11And it came to pass, as he went to Jerusalem, that he passed through the midst of Samaria and Galilee.

^12And as he entered into a certain village, there met him ten men that were lepers, which stood afar off:

^13And they lifted up their voices, and said, Jesus, Master, have mercy on us.

^14And when he saw them, he said unto them, Go shew yourselves unto the priests. And it came to pass, that, as they went, they were cleansed.

^15And one of them, when he saw that he was healed, turned back, and with a loud voice glorified God,

^16And fell down on his face at his feet, giving him thanks: and he was a Samaritan.

^17And Jesus answering said, Were there not ten cleansed? but where are the nine?

^18There are not found that returned to give glory to God, save this stranger.

^19And he said unto him, Arise, go thy way: thy faith hath made thee whole.

^20And when he was demanded of the Pharisees, when the kingdom of God should come, he answered them and said, The kingdom of God cometh not with observation:

^21Neither shall they say, Lo here! or, lo there! for, behold, the kingdom of God is within you.

^22And he said unto the disciples, The days will come, when ye shall desire to see one of the days of the Son of man, and ye shall not see it.

^23And they shall say to you, See here; or, see there: go not after them, nor follow them.

^24For as the lightning, that lighteneth out of the one part under heaven, shineth unto the other part under heaven; so shall also the Son of man be in his day.

^25But first must he suffer many things, and be rejected of this generation.

^26And as it was in the days of Noe, so shall it be also in the days of the Son of man.

^27They did eat, they drank, they married wives, they were given in marriage, until the day that Noe entered into the ark, and the flood came, and destroyed them all.

^28Likewise also as it was in the days of Lot; they did eat, they drank, they bought, they sold, they planted, they builded;

^29But the same day that Lot went out of Sodom it rained fire and brimstone from heaven, and destroyed them all.

^30Even thus shall it be in the day when the Son of man is revealed.

^31In that day, he which shall be upon the housetop, and his stuff in the house, let him not come down to take it away: and he that is in the field, let him likewise not return back.

^32Remember Lot’s wife.

^33Whosoever shall seek to save his life shall lose it; and whosoever shall lose his life shall preserve it.

^34I tell you, in that night there shall be two men in one bed; the one shall be taken, and the other shall be left.

^35Two women shall be grinding together; the one shall be taken, and the other left.

^36Two men shall be in the field; the one shall be taken, and the other left.

^37And they answered and said unto him, Where, Lord? And he said unto them, Wheresoever the body is, thither will the eagles be gathered together.

XVIII

18^1And he spake a parable unto them to this end, that men ought always to pray, and not to faint;

^2Saying, There was in a city a judge, which feared not God, neither regarded man:

^3And there was a widow in that city; and she came unto him, saying, Avenge me of mine adversary.

^4And he would not for a while: but afterward he said within himself, Though I fear not God, nor regard man;

^5Yet because this widow troubleth me, I will avenge her, lest by her continual coming she weary me.

^6And the Lord said, Hear what the unjust judge saith.

^7And shall not God avenge his own elect, which cry day and night unto him, though he bear long with them?

^8I tell you that he will avenge them speedily. Nevertheless when the Son of man cometh, shall he find faith on the earth?

^9And he spake this parable unto certain which trusted in themselves that they were righteous, and despised others:

^10Two men went up into the temple to pray; the one a Pharisee, and the other a publican.

^11The Pharisee stood and prayed thus with himself, God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men are, extortioners, unjust, adulterers, or even as this publican.

^12I fast twice in the week, I give tithes of all that I possess.

^13And the publican, standing afar off, would not lift up so much as his eyes unto heaven, but smote upon his breast, saying, God be merciful to me a sinner.

^14I tell you, this man went down to his house justified rather than the other: for every one that exalteth himself shall be abased; and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted.

^15And they brought unto him also infants, that he would touch them: but when his disciples saw it, they rebuked them.

^16But Jesus called them unto him, and said, Suffer little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of such is the kingdom of God.

^17Verily I say unto you, Whosoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child shall in no wise enter therein.

^18And a certain ruler asked him, saying, Good Master, what shall I do to inherit eternal life?

^19And Jesus said unto him, Why callest thou me good? none is good, save one, that is, God.

^20Thou knowest the commandments, Do not commit adultery, Do not kill, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Honour thy father and thy mother.

^21And he said, All these have I kept from my youth up.

^22Now when Jesus heard these things, he said unto him, Yet lackest thou one thing: sell all that thou hast, and distribute unto the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, follow me.

^23And when he heard this, he was very sorrowful: for he was very rich.

^24And when Jesus saw that he was very sorrowful, he said, How hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God!

^25For it is easier for a camel to go through a needle’s eye, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God.

^26And they that heard it said, Who then can be saved?

^27And he said, The things which are impossible with men are possible with God.

^28Then Peter said, Lo, we have left all, and followed thee.

^29And he said unto them, Verily I say unto you, There is no man that hath left house, or parents, or brethren, or wife, or children, for the kingdom of God’s sake,

^30Who shall not receive manifold more in this present time, and in the world to come life everlasting.

^31Then he took unto him the twelve, and said unto them, Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and all things that are written by the prophets concerning the Son of man shall be accomplished.

^32For he shall be delivered unto the Gentiles, and shall be mocked, and spitefully entreated, and spitted on:

^33And they shall scourge him, and put him to death: and the third day he shall rise again.

^34And they understood none of these things: and this saying was hid from them, neither knew they the things which were spoken.

^35And it came to pass, that as he was come nigh unto Jericho, a certain blind man sat by the way side begging:

^36And hearing the multitude pass by, he asked what it meant.

^37And they told him, that Jesus of Nazareth passeth by.

^38And he cried, saying, Jesus, thou son of David, have mercy on me.

^39And they which went before rebuked him, that he should hold his peace: but he cried so much the more, Thou son of David, have mercy on me.

^40And Jesus stood, and commanded him to be brought unto him: and when he was come near, he asked him,

^41Saying, What wilt thou that I shall do unto thee? And he said, Lord, that I may receive my sight.

^42And Jesus said unto him, Receive thy sight: thy faith hath saved thee.

^43And immediately he received his sight, and followed him, glorifying God: and all the people, when they saw it, gave praise unto God.

XIX

19^1And Jesus entered and passed through Jericho.

^2And, behold, there was a man named Zacchaeus, which was the chief among the publicans, and he was rich.

^3And he sought to see Jesus who he was; and could not for the press, because he was little of stature.

^4And he ran before, and climbed up into a sycomore tree to see him: for he was to pass that way.

^5And when Jesus came to the place, he looked up, and saw him, and said unto him, Zacchaeus, make haste, and come down; for to day I must abide at thy house.

^6And he made haste, and came down, and received him joyfully.

^7And when they saw it, they all murmured, saying, That he was gone to be guest with a man that is a sinner.

^8And Zacchaeus stood, and said unto the Lord: Behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor; and if I have taken any thing from any man by false accusation, I restore him fourfold.

^9And Jesus said unto him, This day is salvation come to this house, forsomuch as he also is a son of Abraham.

^10For the Son of man is come to seek and to save that which was lost.

^11And as they heard these things, he added and spake a parable, because he was nigh to Jerusalem, and because they thought that the kingdom of God should immediately appear.

^12He said therefore, A certain nobleman went into a far country to receive for himself a kingdom, and to return.

^13And he called his ten servants, and delivered them ten pounds, and said unto them, Occupy till I come.

^14But his citizens hated him, and sent a message after him, saying, We will not have this man to reign over us.

^15And it came to pass, that when he was returned, having received the kingdom, then he commanded these servants to be called unto him, to whom he had given the money, that he might know how much every man had gained by trading.

^16Then came the first, saying, Lord, thy pound hath gained ten pounds.

^17And he said unto him, Well, thou good servant: because thou hast been faithful in a very little, have thou authority over ten cities.

^18And the second came, saying, Lord, thy pound hath gained five pounds.

^19And he said likewise to him, Be thou also over five cities.

^20And another came, saying, Lord, behold, here is thy pound, which I have kept laid up in a napkin:

^21For I feared thee, because thou art an austere man: thou takest up that thou layedst not down, and reapest that thou didst not sow.

^22And he saith unto him, Out of thine own mouth will I judge thee, thou wicked servant. Thou knewest that I was an austere man, taking up that I laid not down, and reaping that I did not sow:

^23Wherefore then gavest not thou my money into the bank, that at my coming I might have required mine own with usury?

^24And he said unto them that stood by, Take from him the pound, and give it to him that hath ten pounds.

^25(And they said unto him, Lord, he hath ten pounds.)

^26For I say unto you, That unto every one which hath shall be given; and from him that hath not, even that he hath shall be taken away from him.

^27But those mine enemies, which would not that I should reign over them, bring hither, and slay them before me.

^28And when he had thus spoken, he went before, ascending up to Jerusalem.

^29And it came to pass, when he was come nigh to Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount called the mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples,

^30Saying, Go ye into the village over against you; in the which at your entering ye shall find a colt tied, whereon yet never man sat: loose him, and bring him hither.

^31And if any man ask you, Why do ye loose him? thus shall ye say unto him, Because the Lord hath need of him.

^32And they that were sent went their way, and found even as he had said unto them.

^33And as they were loosing the colt, the owners thereof said unto them, Why loose ye the colt?

^34And they said, The Lord hath need of him.

^35And they brought him to Jesus: and they cast their garments upon the colt, and they set Jesus thereon.

^36And as he went, they spread their clothes in the way.

^37And when he was come nigh, even now at the descent of the mount of Olives, the whole multitude of the disciples began to rejoice and praise God with a loud voice for all the mighty works that they had seen;

^38Saying, Blessed be the King that cometh in the name of the Lord: peace in heaven, and glory in the highest.

^39And some of the Pharisees from among the multitude said unto him, Master, rebuke thy disciples.

^40And he answered and said unto them, I tell you that, if these should hold their peace, the stones would immediately cry out.

^41And when he was come near, he beheld the city, and wept over it,

^42Saying, If thou hadst known, even thou, at least in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes.

^43For the days shall come upon thee, that thine enemies shall cast a trench about thee, and compass thee round, and keep thee in on every side,

^44And shall lay thee even with the ground, and thy children within thee; and they shall not leave in thee one stone upon another; because thou knewest not the time of thy visitation.

^45And he went into the temple, and began to cast out them that sold therein, and them that bought;

^46Saying unto them, It is written, My house is the house of prayer: but ye have made it a den of thieves.

^47And he taught daily in the temple. But the chief priests and the scribes and the chief of the people sought to destroy him,

^48And could not find what they might do: for all the people were very attentive to hear him.

XX

20^1And it came to pass, that on one of those days, as he taught the people in the temple, and preached the gospel, the chief priests and the scribes came upon him with the elders,

^2And spake unto him, saying, Tell us, by what authority doest thou these things? or who is he that gave thee this authority?

^3And he answered and said unto them, I will also ask you one thing; and answer me:

^4The baptism of John, was it from heaven, or of men?

^5And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; he will say, Why then believed ye him not?

^6But and if we say, Of men; all the people will stone us: for they be persuaded that John was a prophet.

^7And they answered, that they could not tell whence it was.

^8And Jesus said unto them, Neither tell I you by what authority I do these things.

^9Then began he to speak to the people this parable; A certain man planted a vineyard, and let it forth to husbandmen, and went into a far country for a long time.

^10And at the season he sent a servant to the husbandmen, that they should give him of the fruit of the vineyard: but the husbandmen beat him, and sent him away empty.

^11And again he sent another servant: and they beat him also, and entreated him shamefully, and sent him away empty.

^12And again he sent a third: and they wounded him also, and cast him out.

^13Then said the lord of the vineyard, What shall I do? I will send my beloved son: it may be they will reverence him when they see him.

^14But when the husbandmen saw him, they reasoned among themselves, saying, This is the heir: come, let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.

^15So they cast him out of the vineyard, and killed him. What therefore shall the lord of the vineyard do unto them?

^16He shall come and destroy these husbandmen, and shall give the vineyard to others. And when they heard it, they said, God forbid.

^17And he beheld them, and said, What is this then that is written, The stone which the builders rejected, the same is become the head of the corner?

^18Whosoever shall fall upon that stone shall be broken; but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder.

^19And the chief priests and the scribes the same hour sought to lay hands on him; and they feared the people: for they perceived that he had spoken this parable against them.

^20And they watched him, and sent forth spies, which should feign themselves just men, that they might take hold of his words, that so they might deliver him unto the power and authority of the governor.

^21And they asked him, saying, Master, we know that thou sayest and teachest rightly, neither acceptest thou the person of any, but teachest the way of God truly:

^22Is it lawful for us to give tribute unto Caesar, or no?

^23But he perceived their craftiness, and said unto them, Why tempt ye me?

^24Shew me a penny. Whose image and superscription hath it? They answered and said, Caesar’s.

^25And he said unto them, Render therefore unto Caesar the things which be Caesar’s, and unto God the things which be God’s.

^26And they could not take hold of his words before the people: and they marvelled at his answer, and held their peace.

^27Then came to him certain of the Sadducees, which deny that there is any resurrection; and they asked him,

^28Saying, Master, Moses wrote unto us, If any man’s brother die, having a wife, and he die without children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise up seed unto his brother.

^29There were therefore seven brethren: and the first took a wife, and died without children.

^30And the second took her to wife, and he died childless.

^31And the third took her; and in like manner the seven also: and they left no children, and died.

^32Last of all the woman died also.

^33Therefore in the resurrection whose wife of them is she? for seven had her to wife.

^34And Jesus answering said unto them, The children of this world marry, and are given in marriage:

^35But they which shall be accounted worthy to obtain that world, and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry, nor are given in marriage:

^36Neither can they die any more: for they are equal unto the angels; and are the children of God, being the children of the resurrection.

^37Now that the dead are raised, even Moses shewed at the bush, when he calleth the Lord the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob.

^38For he is not a God of the dead, but of the living: for all live unto him.

^39Then certain of the scribes answering said, Master, thou hast well said.

^40And after that they durst not ask him any question at all.

^41And he said unto them, How say they that Christ is David’s son?

^42And David himself saith in the book of Psalms, The Lord said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand,

^43Till I make thine enemies thy footstool.

^44David therefore calleth him Lord, how is he then his son?

^45Then in the audience of all the people he said unto his disciples,

^46Beware of the scribes, which desire to walk in long robes, and love greetings in the markets, and the highest seats in the synagogues, and the chief rooms at feasts;

^47Which devour widows’ houses, and for a shew make long prayers: the same shall receive greater damnation.

XXI

21^1And he looked up, and saw the rich men casting their gifts into the treasury.

^2And he saw also a certain poor widow casting in thither two mites.

^3And he said, Of a truth I say unto you, that this poor widow hath cast in more than they all:

^4For all these have of their abundance cast in unto the offerings of God: but she of her penury hath cast in all the living that she had.

^5And as some spake of the temple, how it was adorned with goodly stones and gifts, he said,

^6As for these things which ye behold, the days will come, in the which there shall not be left one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down.

^7And they asked him, saying, Master, but when shall these things be? and what sign will there be when these things shall come to pass?

^8And he said, Take heed that ye be not deceived: for many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ; and the time draweth near: go ye not therefore after them.

^9But when ye shall hear of wars and commotions, be not terrified: for these things must first come to pass; but the end is not by and by.

^10Then said he unto them, Nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom:

^11And great earthquakes shall be in divers places, and famines, and pestilences; and fearful sights and great signs shall there be from heaven.

^12But before all these, they shall lay their hands on you, and persecute you, delivering you up to the synagogues, and into prisons, being brought before kings and rulers for my name’s sake.

^13And it shall turn to you for a testimony.

^14Settle it therefore in your hearts, not to meditate before what ye shall answer:

^15For I will give you a mouth and wisdom, which all your adversaries shall not be able to gainsay nor resist.

^16And ye shall be betrayed both by parents, and brethren, and kinsfolks, and friends; and some of you shall they cause to be put to death.

^17And ye shall be hated of all men for my name’s sake.

^18But there shall not an hair of your head perish.

^19In your patience possess ye your souls.

^20And when ye shall see Jerusalem compassed with armies, then know that the desolation thereof is nigh.

^21Then let them which are in Judaea flee to the mountains; and let them which are in the midst of it depart out; and let not them that are in the countries enter thereinto.

^22For these be the days of vengeance, that all things which are written may be fulfilled.

^23But woe unto them that are with child, and to them that give suck, in those days! for there shall be great distress in the land, and wrath upon this people.

^24And they shall fall by the edge of the sword, and shall be led away captive into all nations: and Jerusalem shall be trodden down of the Gentiles, until the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled.

^25And there shall be signs in the sun, and in the moon, and in the stars; and upon the earth distress of nations, with perplexity; the sea and the waves roaring;

^26Men’s hearts failing them for fear, and for looking after those things which are coming on the earth: for the powers of heaven shall be shaken.

^27And then shall they see the Son of man coming in a cloud with power and great glory.

^28And when these things begin to come to pass, then look up, and lift up your heads; for your redemption draweth nigh.

^29And he spake to them a parable; Behold the fig tree, and all the trees;

^30When they now shoot forth, ye see and know of your own selves that summer is now nigh at hand.

^31So likewise ye, when ye see these things come to pass, know ye that the kingdom of God is nigh at hand.

^32Verily I say unto you, This generation shall not pass away, till all be fulfilled.

^33Heaven and earth shall pass away: but my words shall not pass away.

^34And take heed to yourselves, lest at any time your hearts be overcharged with surfeiting, and drunkenness, and cares of this life, and so that day come upon you unawares.

^35For as a snare shall it come on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth.

^36Watch ye therefore, and pray always, that ye may be accounted worthy to escape all these things that shall come to pass, and to stand before the Son of man.

^37And in the day time he was teaching in the temple; and at night he went out, and abode in the mount that is called the mount of Olives.

^38And all the people came early in the morning to him in the temple, for to hear him.

XXII

22^1Now the feast of unleavened bread drew nigh, which is called the Passover.

^2And the chief priests and scribes sought how they might kill him; for they feared the people.

^3Then entered Satan into Judas surnamed Iscariot, being of the number of the twelve.

^4And he went his way, and communed with the chief priests and captains, how he might betray him unto them.

^5And they were glad, and covenanted to give him money.

^6And he promised, and sought opportunity to betray him unto them in the absence of the multitude.

^7Then came the day of unleavened bread, when the passover must be killed.

^8And he sent Peter and John, saying, Go and prepare us the passover, that we may eat.

^9And they said unto him, Where wilt thou that we prepare?

^10And he said unto them, Behold, when ye are entered into the city, there shall a man meet you, bearing a pitcher of water; follow him into the house where he entereth in.

^11And ye shall say unto the goodman of the house, The Master saith unto thee, Where is the guestchamber, where I shall eat the passover with my disciples?

^12And he shall shew you a large upper room furnished: there make ready.

^13And they went, and found as he had said unto them: and they made ready the passover.

^14And when the hour was come, he sat down, and the twelve apostles with him.

^15And he said unto them, With desire I have desired to eat this passover with you before I suffer:

^16For I say unto you, I will not any more eat thereof, until it be fulfilled in the kingdom of God.

^17And he took the cup, and gave thanks, and said, Take this, and divide it among yourselves:

^18For I say unto you, I will not drink of the fruit of the vine, until the kingdom of God shall come.

^19And he took bread, and gave thanks, and brake it, and gave unto them, saying, This is my body which is given for you: this do in remembrance of me.

^20Likewise also the cup after supper, saying, This cup is the new testament in my blood, which is shed for you.

^21But, behold, the hand of him that betrayeth me is with me on the table.

^22And truly the Son of man goeth, as it was determined: but woe unto that man by whom he is betrayed!

^23And they began to enquire among themselves, which of them it was that should do this thing.

^24And there was also a strife among them, which of them should be accounted the greatest.

^25And he said unto them, The kings of the Gentiles exercise lordship over them; and they that exercise authority upon them are called benefactors.

^26But ye shall not be so: but he that is greatest among you, let him be as the younger; and he that is chief, as he that doth serve.

^27For whether is greater, he that sitteth at meat, or he that serveth? is not he that sitteth at meat? but I am among you as he that serveth.

^28Ye are they which have continued with me in my temptations.

^29And I appoint unto you a kingdom, as my Father hath appointed unto me;

^30That ye may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom, and sit on thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel.

^31And the Lord said, Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath desired to have you, that he may sift you as wheat:

^32But I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not: and when thou art converted, strengthen thy brethren.

^33And he said unto him, Lord, I am ready to go with thee, both into prison, and to death.

^34And he said, I tell thee, Peter, the cock shall not crow this day, before that thou shalt thrice deny that thou knowest me.

^35And he said unto them, When I sent you without purse, and scrip, and shoes, lacked ye any thing? And they said, Nothing.

^36Then said he unto them, But now, he that hath a purse, let him take it, and likewise his scrip: and he that hath no sword, let him sell his garment, and buy one.

^37For I say unto you, that this that is written must yet be accomplished in me, And he was reckoned among the transgressors: for the things concerning me have an end.

^38And they said, Lord, behold, here are two swords. And he said unto them, It is enough.

^39And he came out, and went, as he was wont, to the mount of Olives; and his disciples also followed him.

^40And when he was at the place, he said unto them, Pray that ye enter not into temptation.

^41And he was withdrawn from them about a stone’s cast, and kneeled down, and prayed,

^42Saying, Father, if thou be willing, remove this cup from me: nevertheless not my will, but thine, be done.

^43And there appeared an angel unto him from heaven, strengthening him.

^44And being in an agony he prayed more earnestly: and his sweat was as it were great drops of blood falling down to the ground.

^45And when he rose up from prayer, and was come to his disciples, he found them sleeping for sorrow,

^46And said unto them, Why sleep ye? rise and pray, lest ye enter into temptation.

^47And while he yet spake, behold a multitude, and he that was called Judas, one of the twelve, went before them, and drew near unto Jesus to kiss him.

^48But Jesus said unto him, Judas, betrayest thou the Son of man with a kiss?

^49When they which were about him saw what would follow, they said unto him, Lord, shall we smite with the sword?

^50And one of them smote the servant of the high priest, and cut off his right ear.

^51And Jesus answered and said, Suffer ye thus far. And he touched his ear, and healed him.

^52Then Jesus said unto the chief priests, and captains of the temple, and the elders, which were come to him, Be ye come out, as against a thief, with swords and staves?

^53When I was daily with you in the temple, ye stretched forth no hands against me: but this is your hour, and the power of darkness.

^54Then took they him, and led him, and brought him into the high priest’s house. And Peter followed afar off.

^55And when they had kindled a fire in the midst of the hall, and were set down together, Peter sat down among them.

^56But a certain maid beheld him as he sat by the fire, and earnestly looked upon him, and said, This man was also with him.

^57And he denied him, saying, Woman, I know him not.

^58And after a little while another saw him, and said, Thou art also of them. And Peter said, Man, I am not.

^59And about the space of one hour after another confidently affirmed, saying, Of a truth this fellow also was with him: for he is a Galilaean.

^60And Peter said, Man, I know not what thou sayest. And immediately, while he yet spake, the cock crew.

^61And the Lord turned, and looked upon Peter. And Peter remembered the word of the Lord, how he had said unto him, Before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice.

^62And Peter went out, and wept bitterly.

^63And the men that held Jesus mocked him, and smote him.

^64And when they had blindfolded him, they struck him on the face, and asked him, saying, Prophesy, who is it that smote thee?

^65And many other things blasphemously spake they against him.

^66And as soon as it was day, the elders of the people and the chief priests and the scribes came together, and led him into their council, saying,

^67Art thou the Christ? tell us. And he said unto them, If I tell you, ye will not believe:

^68And if I also ask you, ye will not answer me, nor let me go.

^69Hereafter shall the Son of man sit on the right hand of the power of God.

^70Then said they all, Art thou then the Son of God? And he said unto them, Ye say that I am.

^71And they said, What need we any further witness? for we ourselves have heard of his own mouth.

XXIII

23^1And the whole multitude of them arose, and led him unto Pilate.

^2And they began to accuse him, saying, We found this fellow perverting the nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Caesar, saying that he himself is Christ a King.

^3And Pilate asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And he answered him and said, Thou sayest it.

^4Then said Pilate to the chief priests and to the people, I find no fault in this man.

^5And they were the more fierce, saying, He stirreth up the people, teaching throughout all Jewry, beginning from Galilee to this place.

^6When Pilate heard of Galilee, he asked whether the man were a Galilaean.

^7And as soon as he knew that he belonged unto Herod’s jurisdiction, he sent him to Herod, who himself also was at Jerusalem at that time.

^8And when Herod saw Jesus, he was exceeding glad: for he was desirous to see him of a long season, because he had heard many things of him; and he hoped to have seen some miracle done by him.

^9Then he questioned with him in many words; but he answered him nothing.

^10And the chief priests and scribes stood and vehemently accused him.

^11And Herod with his men of war set him at nought, and mocked him, and arrayed him in a gorgeous robe, and sent him again to Pilate.

^12And the same day Pilate and Herod were made friends together: for before they were at enmity between themselves.

^13And Pilate, when he had called together the chief priests and the rulers and the people,

^14Said unto them, Ye have brought this man unto me, as one that perverteth the people: and, behold, I, having examined him before you, have found no fault in this man touching those things whereof ye accuse him:

^15No, nor yet Herod: for I sent you to him; and, lo, nothing worthy of death is done unto him.

^16I will therefore chastise him, and release him.

^17(For of necessity he must release one unto them at the feast.)

^18And they cried out all at once, saying, Away with this man, and release unto us Barabbas:

^19(Who for a certain sedition made in the city, and for murder, was cast into prison.)

^20Pilate therefore, willing to release Jesus, spake again to them.

^21But they cried, saying, Crucify him, crucify him.

^22And he said unto them the third time, Why, what evil hath he done? I have found no cause of death in him: I will therefore chastise him, and let him go.

^23And they were instant with loud voices, requiring that he might be crucified. And the voices of them and of the chief priests prevailed.

^24And Pilate gave sentence that it should be as they required.

^25And he released unto them him that for sedition and murder was cast into prison, whom they had desired; but he delivered Jesus to their will.

^26And as they led him away, they laid hold upon one Simon, a Cyrenian, coming out of the country, and on him they laid the cross, that he might bear it after Jesus.

^27And there followed him a great company of people, and of women, which also bewailed and lamented him.

^28But Jesus turning unto them said, Daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me, but weep for yourselves, and for your children.

^29For, behold, the days are coming, in the which they shall say, Blessed are the barren, and the wombs that never bare, and the paps which never gave suck.

^30Then shall they begin to say to the mountains, Fall on us; and to the hills, Cover us.

^31For if they do these things in a green tree, what shall be done in the dry?

^32And there were also two other, malefactors, led with him to be put to death.

^33And when they were come to the place, which is called Calvary, there they crucified him, and the malefactors, one on the right hand, and the other on the left.

^34Then said Jesus, Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do. And they parted his raiment, and cast lots.

^35And the people stood beholding. And the rulers also with them derided him, saying, He saved others; let him save himself, if he be Christ, the chosen of God.

^36And the soldiers also mocked him, coming to him, and offering him vinegar,

^37And saying, If thou be the king of the Jews, save thyself.

^38And a superscription also was written over him in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew, This is the King of the Jews.

^39And one of the malefactors which were hanged railed on him, saying, If thou be Christ, save thyself and us.

^40But the other answering rebuked him, saying, Dost not thou fear God, seeing thou art in the same condemnation?

^41And we indeed justly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds: but this man hath done nothing amiss.

^42And he said unto Jesus, Lord, remember me when thou comest into thy kingdom.

^43And Jesus said unto him, Verily I say unto thee, To day shalt thou be with me in paradise.

^44And it was about the sixth hour, and there was a darkness over all the earth until the ninth hour.

^45And the sun was darkened, and the veil of the temple was rent in the midst.

^46And when Jesus had cried with a loud voice, he said, Father, into thy hands I commend my spirit: and having said thus, he gave up the ghost.

^47Now when the centurion saw what was done, he glorified God, saying, Certainly this was a righteous man.

^48And all the people that came together to that sight, beholding the things which were done, smote their breasts, and returned.

^49And all his acquaintance, and the women that followed him from Galilee, stood afar off, beholding these things.

^50And, behold, there was a man named Joseph, a counsellor; and he was a good man, and a just:

^51(The same had not consented to the counsel and deed of them;) he was of Arimathaea, a city of the Jews: who also himself waited for the kingdom of God.

^52This man went unto Pilate, and begged the body of Jesus.

^53And he took it down, and wrapped it in linen, and laid it in a sepulchre that was hewn in stone, wherein never man before was laid.

^54And that day was the preparation, and the sabbath drew on.

^55And the women also, which came with him from Galilee, followed after, and beheld the sepulchre, and how his body was laid.

^56And they returned, and prepared spices and ointments; and rested the sabbath day according to the commandment.

XXIV

24^1Now upon the first day of the week, very early in the morning, they came unto the sepulchre, bringing the spices which they had prepared, and certain others with them.

^2And they found the stone rolled away from the sepulchre.

^3And they entered in, and found not the body of the Lord Jesus.

^4And it came to pass, as they were much perplexed thereabout, behold, two men stood by them in shining garments:

^5And as they were afraid, and bowed down their faces to the earth, they said unto them, Why seek ye the living among the dead?

^6He is not here, but is risen: remember how he spake unto you when he was yet in Galilee,

^7Saying, The Son of man must be delivered into the hands of sinful men, and be crucified, and the third day rise again.

^8And they remembered his words,

^9And returned from the sepulchre, and told all these things unto the eleven, and to all the rest.

^10It was Mary Magdalene and Joanna, and Mary the mother of James, and other women that were with them, which told these things unto the apostles.

^11And their words seemed to them as idle tales, and they believed them not.

^12Then arose Peter, and ran unto the sepulchre; and stooping down, he beheld the linen clothes laid by themselves, and departed, wondering in himself at that which was come to pass.

^13And, behold, two of them went that same day to a village called Emmaus, which was from Jerusalem about threescore furlongs.

^14And they talked together of all these things which had happened.

^15And it came to pass, that, while they communed together and reasoned, Jesus himself drew near, and went with them.

^16But their eyes were holden that they should not know him.

^17And he said unto them, What manner of communications are these that ye have one to another, as ye walk, and are sad?

^18And the one of them, whose name was Cleopas, answering said unto him, Art thou only a stranger in Jerusalem, and hast not known the things which are come to pass there in these days?

^19And he said unto them, What things? And they said unto him, Concerning Jesus of Nazareth, which was a prophet mighty in deed and word before God and all the people:

^20And how the chief priests and our rulers delivered him to be condemned to death, and have crucified him.

^21But we trusted that it had been he which should have redeemed Israel: and beside all this, to day is the third day since these things were done.

^22Yea, and certain women also of our company made us astonished, which were early at the sepulchre;

^23And when they found not his body, they came, saying, that they had also seen a vision of angels, which said that he was alive.

^24And certain of them which were with us went to the sepulchre, and found it even so as the women had said: but him they saw not.

^25Then he said unto them, O fools, and slow of heart to believe all that the prophets have spoken:

^26Ought not Christ to have suffered these things, and to enter into his glory?

^27And beginning at Moses and all the prophets, he expounded unto them in all the scriptures the things concerning himself.

^28And they drew nigh unto the village, whither they went: and he made as though he would have gone further.

^29But they constrained him, saying, Abide with us: for it is toward evening, and the day is far spent. And he went in to tarry with them.

^30And it came to pass, as he sat at meat with them, he took bread, and blessed it, and brake, and gave to them.

^31And their eyes were opened, and they knew him; and he vanished out of their sight.

^32And they said one to another, Did not our heart burn within us, while he talked with us by the way, and while he opened to us the scriptures?

^33And they rose up the same hour, and returned to Jerusalem, and found the eleven gathered together, and them that were with them,

^34Saying, The Lord is risen indeed, and hath appeared to Simon.

^35And they told what things were done in the way, and how he was known of them in breaking of bread.

^36And as they thus spake, Jesus himself stood in the midst of them, and saith unto them, Peace be unto you.

^37But they were terrified and affrighted, and supposed that they had seen a spirit.

^38And he said unto them, Why are ye troubled? and why do thoughts arise in your hearts?

^39Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself: handle me, and see; for a spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me have.

^40And when he had thus spoken, he shewed them his hands and his feet.

^41And while they yet believed not for joy, and wondered, he said unto them, Have ye here any meat?

^42And they gave him a piece of a broiled fish, and of an honeycomb.

^43And he took it, and did eat before them.

^44And he said unto them, These are the words which I spake unto you, while I was yet with you, that all things must be fulfilled, which were written in the law of Moses, and in the prophets, and in the psalms, concerning me.

^45Then opened he their understanding, that they might understand the scriptures,

^46And said unto them, Thus it is written, and thus it behoved Christ to suffer, and to rise from the dead the third day:

^47And that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in his name among all nations, beginning at Jerusalem.

^48And ye are witnesses of these things.

^49And, behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you: but tarry ye in the city of Jerusalem, until ye be endued with power from on high.

^50And he led them out as far as to Bethany, and he lifted up his hands, and blessed them.

^51And it came to pass, while he blessed them, he was parted from them, and carried up into heaven.

^52And they worshipped him, and returned to Jerusalem with great joy:

^53And were continually in the temple, praising and blessing God. Amen.